<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../OLAC_doc.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "../OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc>
   <header>
      <status code="proposed" type="informational"/>
      <title>OLAC Metadata Usage Guidelines</title>
      <baseName>usage</baseName>
      <issued>20080229</issued>
      <previousIssued>20071115</previousIssued>
      <abstract>
         <p>This document provides guidelines on the meaning and proper usage of the metadata
            elements used in the metadata standard of the Open Language Archives Community.</p>
      </abstract>
      <editors>Gary Simons, SIL International and Graduate Institute of Applied Linguistics
            (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>) <br/>Steven Bird, University of Melbourne and
         University of Pennsylvania (<url>mailto:sb@ldc.upenn.edu</url>) <br/>Joan Spanne, SIL
         International (<url>mailto:joan_spanne@sil.org</url>)</editors>
      <copyright>2008 Gary Simons (SIL International and Graduate Institute of Applied Linguistics),
         Steven Bird (University of Melbourne and University of Pennsylvania), and Joan Spanne (SIL
         International)</copyright>
      <changes>
         <p>In section 2, paragraph on <i>xml:lang</i> was significantly updated. In section 3, many
            points clarified regarding individual elements, particularly Contributor, Coverage,
            Creator, Language, Subject, and Title. Examples expanded and added. Section 5 on the
            granularity of resources was added. The changes were in response to review comments by
            the Metadata Working Group (see
            <url>http://www.language-archives.org/wg/metadata/Issues-2007-12.htm</url> for a 
            record of the comments and responses).</p>
      </changes>
   </header>
   <!-- N.B. Style used throughout document for aspects of markup:
             DC elements are simply capitalized
             Refinements (except in the list) are in <tt></tt>
             Attribute and scheme names (except in the list) are in <i></i> 
             In the examples, the continuation of an element is indented 3 spaces,
                  while a second element in the same examples is flush left
             About 70 characters is max length for an example line, since the <PRE>
                   prevents wrapping and these the text of the section is as wide as
                   the longest example and off edge of screen and paper 
   -->
   <body>
      <section>
         <heading>Introduction</heading>
         <p>This document provides guidelines on how to describe language resources using the OLAC
            metadata standard <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>. The standard itself documents the formal
            syntax of valid metadata records, but does not explain or exemplify the use of the
            individual metadata elements. That is the purpose of this document. </p>
         <p>Section 2 below describes the usage of the attributes that may be used on metadata
            elements. Section 3 then describes usage in the OLAC context for the fifteen core
            elements of the Dublin Core metadata set. Section 4 describes other elements that may be
            used. Section 5 concludes with remarks about the granularity of resources; that is, it
            addresses the question of what size of thing (from file up to entire corpus) is treated
            as an item in an OLAC repository.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>All elements</heading>
         <p>OLAC metadata is an application of the Dublin Core metadata element set as defined in
               <cit>DCMT</cit>. The most fundamental requirement on best practice in OLAC is that
            each element should be used in a way that conforms to its definition in <cit>DCMT</cit>.
            This document therefore repeats those definitions and offers usage notes and examples to
            help the reader understand best use of the elements in the context of describing
            language resources.</p>
         <p>Eight of the elements in the Dublin Core metadata set define refinements that narrow the
            meaning of the element. A refinement shares the meaning of the generic element, but with
            a more restricted scope. When the more restricted meaning applies, it is recommended
            best practice to use the refined version of an element rather than the generic one. This
            document lists the refinements that are possible for each element.</p>
         <p>In theory, every element in the metadata set may use the <i>xsi:type</i> attribute to
            specify an encoding scheme that defines a controlled vocabulary or a controlled syntax
            for its values. This document lists possible encoding schemes for eleven of the
            elements, whether defined by <cit>DCMT</cit> or <cit>OLAC-Extensions</cit>. In the case
            of the OLAC extensions, the controlled value goes in the <i>olac:code</i> attribute
            (with the element content being available for an optional freeform elaboration of the
            coded value), while in the case of DCMI encoding schemes the controlled value goes in
            the element content. When one of these encoding schemes is applicable, it is recommended
            best practice to use it since this adds precision to the value of the element that can
            be exploited to improve accuracy in searching and to provide domain-specific services.
            Subcommunities may follow the extension mechanism defined in section 5 of
               <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit> to define new encoding schemes.</p>
         <p>Every element in the metadata set may use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute. It specifies
            the language in which the text within the content of the metadata element is written.
            Though the <cit>XML-Lang</cit> specification permits a wider range of values for this
            attribute, it is recommended for purposes of interoperation in the OLAC context that
            only identifiers that conform to the <cit>OLAC-Language</cit> specification be used. The
            OLAC harvester normalizes values of <i>xml:lang</i> in the way described in
               <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>. In the absence of an <i>xml:lang</i> attribute, the element
            content is assumed to be in English (unless it is a coded value from an encoding
            scheme). Whenever the language of the element content is other than English, recommended
            best practice is to use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute to identify the language. By using
            multiple instances of a metadata elements tagged for different languages, data providers
            may offer their metadata records in multiple languages. The use of the <i>xml:lang</i>
            attribute as the language of the metadata should not be confused with the use of the
               <i>olac:language</i> scheme with <xref>Language</xref> and <xref>Subject</xref> to
            specify, respectively, the content language of the resource itself and the subject of
            the resource. In fact, the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute may be used within these elements,
            as well, to specify an alternative name of the identified language, given in the
            language specified in <i>xml:lang</i> (see <xref>Language</xref> for an example).</p>
         <p>In the formal definition of the metadata standard <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>, every
            element and refinement is optional and repeatable. However, recommended best practice
            (as described below for particular elements and in <cit>OLAC-BP</cit>) requires that
            certain elements be present in order to give a basic breadth of description for a
            language resource. Recommended best practice also requires that one particular element
            (namely, <xref>Title</xref>) not be repeated. Since all other elements and refinements
            are repeatable, multiple values for an element or refinement should be given in multiple
            instances of the XML element rather than being listed in a single instance. This makes
            it possible for service providers to build search indexes on the individual values.</p>
         <p>To summarize, the following are recommended best practices that apply to all elements:</p>
         <element name="All elements">
            <definition><!-- Don't use. Just a trick to make export to RED/bpr.xml work. --></definition>
            <comment><!-- Ditto. --></comment>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is for the value of each metadata element to conform to
                  the definition of that element as given in <cit>DCMT</cit>.</p>
               <p>When the meaning of a particular element in a metadata record fits the definition
                  of a refinement, recommended best practice is to use the refinement rather than
                  the generic element.</p>
               <p>When applicable, recommended best practice is to use the <i>xsi:type</i> attribute
                  to specify an encoding scheme so as to express the value of the element with
                  precision.</p>
               <p>Whenever the language of the element content is other than English, recommended
                  best practice is to use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute with a value from
                     <cit>OLAC-Language</cit> to identify the language.</p>
               <p>When a resource has more than one value for a particular metadata element or
                  refinement, recommended best practice is to use a separate instance of the element
                  or refinement for each value rather than listing all the values in a single
                  instance.</p>
            </bp>
            <examples><!-- This is implemented in the stylesheet if we want to give
               examples --></examples>
         </element>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>Core elements</heading>
         <p>Each of the fifteen core elements of the Dublin Core metadata set is described in one of
            the following subsections. These elements are defined in the
               <url>http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/</url> namespace for which the prefix
            <tt>dc:</tt> is used in the examples.</p>
         <p>Each subsection heading gives the name of an element; the element is then described
            under six subheadings. <i>Definition</i> is the definition for the element as given by
            the Dublin Core Metadata Initiative <cit>DCMT</cit>. <i>Refinements</i> lists the
            refined element names that may be used in place of the generic element name to specify a
            more precise meaning for the metadata item. The refinement definitions are copied from
               <cit>DCMT</cit>. All of the refinements are defined within the
               <url>http://purl.org/dc/terms/</url> namespace for which the prefix <tt>dcterms:</tt>
            is used in the examples. <i>Schemes</i> lists the encoding schemes that may be used with
            the element (or its refinements) as the value of the <i>xsi:type</i> attribute. <i>Best
               practice</i> lists the best practices for the use of the element that are recommended
            by the OLAC community <cit>OLAC-BP</cit>. <i>Usage notes</i> offers additional notes for
            the OLAC community on how to use the element in the context of describing language
            resources. <i>Examples</i> shows samples of properly encoded elements and sample
            refinements.</p>

         <element name="Contributor">
            <definition>An entity responsible for making contributions to the resource.</definition>
            <comment>

               <p>A Contributor may be a person, an organization, or a service&#x2014;any entity
                  that has sufficient involvement in the creation or development of the resource to
                  warrant explicit identification. A term from <i>olac:role</i> should be used to
                  specify the role of the Contributor. Contributor is related to
                  <xref>Creator</xref> since many of the terms in the role vocabulary (like
                     <i>author</i> or <i>photographer</i>) name the role of the primary creator of a
                  resource. The OLAC recommendation is that Contributor (with the appropriate role
                  designation) be used in these cases, and that Creator be used only when there is
                  not an appropriate term in the <i>olac:role</i> vocabulary for the role played by
                  the entity that created the resource. A participating OLAC repository need not be
                  concerned about the fact that other metadata services based on Dublin Core may
                  prefer and even require the use of the Creator element. The OLAC-to-Simple-DC
                  crosswalk built into the OLAC Aggregator automatically maps certain OLAC
                  Contributor roles like <i>author</i> and <i>photographer</i> to the Creator
                  element. See the discussion of <xref>Creator</xref> for more on its use.</p>
               <p>Contributor and <xref>Publisher</xref> are also somewhat related elements. In
                  particular, the <i>olac:role</i> “sponsor” can come close to one aspect of
                  participation that a publisher may have in regard to making a given resource
                  available to the public. The <i>olac:role</i> “editor” can encompass a spectrum of
                  tasks that are collectively performed by the publisher of a work. A sponsor or
                  editor that is not also the formal publisher of a resource may be entered in a
                  Contributor element (with the proper <i>olac:role</i> specified), but the
                  publisher should not be repeated in a Contributor element.</p>
               <p>The form of a personal name should follow the form in which the person's name
                  would normally be listed in an alphabetical index in his or her own language or
                  country of residence, <i>e.g.,</i> “FamilyName, GivenName” for an English speaker.
                  If the first element is the family name, follow the family name with a comma. If
                  the first element is the given name, do not follow it with a comma. Consult the
                  Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules, 2nd ed., rev., <cit>AACR2r</cit> chapter 22 for
                  additional guidance in determining the normal ordering and forms of names based on
                  language and country, as well as other name characteristics.</p>
               <p>The form of a corporate name (<i>e.g.,</i> name of an institution or organization
                  or any other corporate body) should also be ready for sorting in an alphabetical
                  index. This means that an initial article should be omitted. In cases where a
                  hierarchy present, list the parts of the hierarchy from largest to smallest,
                  separated by period (full stop) and space. Location should generally be omitted
                  from the name unless location is an integral part of the proper name of the unit.
                  Do not use quotation marks to enclose corporate names. If the name is a
                  translation from its usual form or is not usually given in English, use the
                     <i>xml:lang</i> attribute on the element. More guidance on the forms of
                  corporate names may be found in <cit>AACR2r</cit>, chapter 24.</p>
               <p>In general, if there is no suitable role in the <i>olac:role</i> scheme, no
                  additional information regarding the particular role of the contributor should be
                  included in content of the element, as this would have the effect of making
                  separate indexed forms for the same person based on engaging in different kinds of
                  contributory activities.</p>
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>olac:role</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The <i>olac:role</i> scheme is optionally used to specify the role (such as
                        author, transcriber, sponsor, and so on) played by the named entity in the
                        creation of the resource. The role is expressed by means of a controlled
                        vocabulary; see <cit>OLAC-Role</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary.
                     </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is to identify a Contributor by means of a name in a
                  form that is ready for sorting within an alphabetical index. </p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>olac:role</i> scheme to indicate the
                  role of the Contributor.</p>
            </bp>
            <examples>
               <p>A personal author:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="author"&gt;Bloomfield, 
   Leonard&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
               <p>An editor:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="editor"&gt;Sapir, 
   Edward&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
               <p>A funding agency with a hierarchical corporate name:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="sponsor"&gt;Smithsonian 
   Institution. Office of Fellowships and Grants.&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
               <p>The person who performed a role for which there is not a suitable code:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor&gt;Smith, John L.&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
               <p>An institutional author whose name is given in the Czech language:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="author" 
   xml:lang="ces"&gt;Česká akademie věd a umění&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>

         <element name="Coverage">
            <definition>The spatial or temporal topic of the resource, the spatial applicability of
               the resource, or the jurisdiction under which the resource is relevant.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p> Coverage will typically include spatial location (a place name or geographic
                  coordinates), temporal period (a period label, date, or date range) or
                  jurisdiction (such as a named administrative entity). <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>Coverage is related to <xref>Subject</xref> in having a topical orientation.
                  Coverage in its temporal aspect should not be confused with <xref>Date</xref> or
                  one of its refinements (<i>e.g.,</i> created, or available). Thus, a data set that
                  was compiled over an extended period of time should be described via a
                     <tt>dcterms:created</tt> element whose content is a date range, rather than
                  with Coverage or <tt>dcterms:temporal</tt>. A data set (or any kind of resource)
                  that contains or addresses historical information would correctly use Coverage or
                     <tt>dcterms:temporal</tt> to specify the date, date range or period in focus.</p>
               <p>Coverage should be used geographically when the language variety in focus in the
                  resource has a different or narrower distribution than the language has in
                  general. It should also be used when the resource deals with a topic of study in
                  which the location or region itself is in focus, <i>e.g.,</i> multilingualism,
                  language policy, languages in contact, in a given locale.</p>
               <p>Geospatial coordinates are appropriate Coverage metadata for a text recording when
                  they identify the location where the exemplified speech variety is spoken.
                  Typically this coincides with the location where the text was collected, but not
                  always. If the text was collected outside a community where it is spoken (such as
                  in a laboratory setting), then information about the circumstances of collection
                  would be included in the Description element. </p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:spatial</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Spatial characteristics of the intellectual content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:temporal</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Temporal characteristics of the intellectual content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:Box</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Identifies a region of space using its geographic limits
                        <cit>DCMI-Box</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:ISO3166</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Codes for the representation of names of countries <cit>ISO3166</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:Period</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Specifies the limits of a time interval <cit>DCMI-Period</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:Point</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Identifies a point in space using its geographic coordinates
                        <cit>DCMI-Point</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:TGN</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names <cit>TGN</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that a metadata record should contain at least one
                  Coverage (or one of its refinements) or Description (or one of its refinements) or
                  Subject element in order to give the prospective user some idea of the content of
                  the resource that goes beyond the informative potential of just a title alone.
                  Using all of these elements is encouraged.</p>
               <p>In the case of spatial coverage, recommended best practice is to use an encoding
                  scheme to give precise geocoding of the resource.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A resource about English in India:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="en"/&gt;
&lt;dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:ISO3166"&gt;IN&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource about languages spoken on Guadalcanal:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:TGN"&gt;Guadalcanal (island)&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource involving a diaspora group from a language community:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;“Como Se Hayan”: Zapotec Indigenous Migrant
   Expressions of Belonging&lt;/dc:title&gt;
&lt;dc:coverage&gt;Los Angeles, California&lt;/dc:coverage&gt;
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="zpu"/&gt;</eg>
               <!-- example resource URI: http://www.allacademic.com/meta/p114114_index.html -->
               <p>A resource about language use in the 19th century:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:temporal&gt;19th century&lt;/dcterms:temporal&gt;</eg>
               <p>A dataset covering a period of time, relating to a particular community, collected
                  over a span of time:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;Agta Demographic Database: chronicle of a hunter-gatherer 
   community in transition&lt;/dc:title&gt;
&lt;dcterms:temporal xsi:type="dcterms:Period"&gt;start=1900; end=2006;
   &lt;/dcterms:temporal&gt;
&lt;dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:TGN"&gt;San Ildefonso, Cape (cape)
   &lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;
&lt;dcterms:created xsi:type=dcterms:Period&gt;start=1962; end=2006;
   &lt;/dcterms:created&gt;</eg>
               <!-- example resource URI: http://www.sil.org/silepubs/abstract.asp?id=49227 -->
            </examples>
         </element>

         <element name="Creator">
            <definition>An entity primarily responsible for making the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>A Creator may be a person, an organization, or a service. It refers to an entity
                  with a primary role in the creation of the intellectual or artistic content of the
                  resource <cit>DC-Lib</cit>. Creator is closely related to
                  <xref>Contributor</xref>. The OLAC recommendation is that Creator be viewed
                  semantically as a <i>refinement</i> of Contributor, though it retains its status
                  (and therefore its syntax) as an element for backward compatibility. (This is in
                  line with the latest recommendations of the DCMI; see <cit>DCMT</cit> and
                     <cit>DC-Lib</cit>.) Thus, Creator is appropriate to use in cases where the
                  entity to be identified has significant involvement as a primary originator of the
                  content, but in such a way that none of the role terms available in the
                     <i>olac:role</i> scheme is a suitable description of that involvement. Examples
                  are <i>artist</i> (<i>e.g.,</i> sculptor, carver, weaver) or <i>modeler</i>.</p>
               <p>A participating OLAC repository need not be concerned about the fact that other
                  metadata services based on Dublin Core may prefer and even require the use of the
                  Creator element. The OLAC-to-Simple-DC crosswalk built into the OLAC Aggregator
                  automatically maps certain OLAC Contributor roles like <i>author</i> and
                     <i>photographer</i> to the Creator element.</p>
               <p>See the <xref>Contributor</xref> element for information about the proper form for
                  a personal name or a corporate name. </p>
            </comment>

            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is to use the Contributor element instead of Creator,
                  except in cases where there is significant creative involvement by the person or
                  organization and there is no suitable refinement term from the <i>olac:role</i>
                  scheme to use with Contributor.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A weaver of a basket or textile resource that accompanies a description of its
                  making:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:creator&gt;Datsolalee&lt;/dc:creator&gt;</eg>
               <p>See <xref>Contributor</xref> for examples of author and other creative roles.</p>
            </examples>
         </element>

         <element name="Date">
            <definition>A point or period of time associated with an event in the lifecycle of the
               resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>A WSCDTF-conformant value may be for the year alone, for the year and month, or
                  for an exact date. A range of years is also a valid value; in this case both years
                  must be four-digit values and the earliest year should come first. Thus, the
                  element value may match one of the four following patterns: <tt>YYYY</tt>,
                     <tt>YYYY-MM</tt>, <tt>YYYY-MM-DD</tt>, or <tt>YYYY-YYYY</tt>.</p>
               <p>A Date with no refinement will be assumed to be the date of issue (<i>i.e.</i>
                  publication). Date of publication may differ from its creation date; thus it can
                  be helpful to prospective users to include more than one kind of Date element
                  (refinement). However, a single resource should not have more than one instance of
                  each date refinement, with the possible exception of <tt>dcterms:modified</tt>.
                  Where the modification history of a resource is significant, it is appropriate to
                  enter this information in a <xref>Provenance</xref> element, which allows for
                  explanation of modifications in a way that <tt>dcterms:modified</tt> does not.</p>
               <p>‘Available’ as a refinement pertains to Date, not to other aspects of
                  availability.</p>
               <p>Do not use additional terms such as “recorded on” or “donated on” in the element
                  text.</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:available</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date (often a range) that the resource will become or did become
                     available.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:created</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date of creation of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:dateAccepted</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date of acceptance of the resource (<i>e.g.,</i> of thesis by university
                        department, of article by journal, etc.).</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:dateCopyrighted</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date of a statement of copyright.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:dateSubmitted</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date of submission of the resource (<i>e.g.,</i> thesis, article, etc.).</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:issued</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date of formal issuance (<i>e.g.,</i> publication) of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:modified</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date on which the resource was changed.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:valid</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date (often a range) of validity of a resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:W3CDTF</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>W3C Encoding rules for dates and times - a profile based on ISO 8601
                           <cit>W3CDTF</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:Period</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A specification of the limits of a time interval <cit>DCMI-Period</cit></p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that a record have at least one instance of Date (or
                  one of its refinements).</p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that every instance of Date (or one of its
                  refinements) use the <i>dcterms:W3CDTF</i> scheme, or enclose the element value in
                  square brackets if the value does not conform to the encoding scheme (<i>e.g.,</i>
                  if it is supplied by the cataloger, is approximate, or is in some doubt). </p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A typical year of publication:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">1992&lt;/dc:date&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource modified on October 16, 1996:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:modified xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">1996-10-16&lt;/dcterms:modified&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource from approximately 1950:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:date>[circa 1950]&lt;/dc:date&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource for which the date has been supplied by the cataloger from external
                  informaiton:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:issued>[1932]&lt;/dcterms:issued&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>

         <element name="Description">
            <definition>An account of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>

               <p>Description may include but is not limited to: an abstract, table of contents,
                  reference to a graphical representation of content, or a free-text summary account
                  of the content. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>Description may also offer an annotation, or a qualitative or evaluative comment
                  about the resource, such as a statement about suitability for a particular
                  application or context.</p>
               <p> Description element is not a “catch-all” category. The Description element should
                  not be confused with Subject. Description contains free-text (prose) statements,
                  while Subject contains subject headings, faceted terms, or specific subject
                  descriptors, <i>e.g.,</i> Library of Congress Subject Headings, or Linguistics and
                  Language Behavior Abstracts thesaurus descriptors. Description should likewise not
                  be used in place of Extent to contain information solely about the length,
                  duration, or size of a work.</p>
               <p>No formatting conventions are defined within the text of Description. Service
                  providers may format the entire Description as a single paragraph, collapsing
                  adjacent white space characters into a single space.</p>
               <p>When there is a URL for a document that describes the resource, use a separate
                  Description element to encode just that URL. A Description that begins with
                  “http:” will be interpreted by service providers as consisting solely of a URL and
                  will be presented as a link in user interfaces. Service providers are not obliged
                  to search other Description text for the occurrence of URLs.</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:abstract</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A summary of the content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:tableOfContents</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A list of subunits of the content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <bp>

               <p>Recommended best practice is that a metadata record should contain at least one
                  Description (or one of its refinements) or Coverage (or one of its refinements) or
                  Subject element in order to give the prospective user some idea of the content of
                  the resource that goes beyond the informative potential of just a title alone.
                  Using all of these elements is encouraged.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A prose description of a resource:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:description&gt;The CALLHOME Japanese corpus of telephone speech consists of 
   120 unscripted telephone conversations between native speakers of Japanese. 
   All calls, which lasted up to 30 minutes, originated in North America and 
   were placed to locations overseas (typically Japan). Most participants called 
   family members or close friends. This corpus contains speech data files 
   ONLY, along with the minimal amount of documentation needed to describe the 
   contents and format of the speech files and the software packages needed 
   to uncompress the speech data.&lt;/dc:description&gt;</eg>
               <p>A contents note for a resource:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:tableOfContents&gt;v. 1: Thesaurus of Khmu dialects in Southeast Asia; 
   v. 2: Dictionary of Khmu in China; v. 3: Dictionary of Khmu in Laos; 
   v. 4: Dictionary of Khmu in Vietnam; v. 5: Dictionary of Khmu in Thailand
   &lt;/dcterms:tableOfContents&gt;</eg>
               <p>A reference to an existing on-line description:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:description&gt;http://www.ldc.upenn.edu/Catalog/LDC96S37.html&lt;/dc:description&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Format">
            <definition>The file format, physical medium, or dimensions of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>

               <p>Typically, Format may include the media-type, physical material, and/or dimensions
                  of the resource. Format may be used to determine the software, hardware or other
                  equipment needed to display or operate the resource. Examples of dimensions
                  include size and duration. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>In the case of a physical object, the refinements medium and extent are most
                  applicable. These may respectively contain the physical material of the object
                     (<i>e.g.,</i> parchment; reel-to-reel tape; 35 mm slide; NTSC encoded VHS
                  cassette), and the size/duration (<i>e.g.,</i> number of pages and dimensions of a
                  book; length of a recording).</p>
               <p>Format (and its refinement 'medium'), which encompasses the notion of physical
                  media categories such as photograph, should not be confused with
                  <xref>Type</xref>, which categorizes the nature or genre of the content of the
                  resource based on the mode in which the user experiences or interacts with the
                  resource, and as such includes terms that describe general categories, functions,
                  or aggregation levels for content.</p>
               <!--<p>OLAC had 5 refinements (cpu, encoding, markup, os, sourcecode) but each of these was used very
						little, if at all  http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf    </p> -->

            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:extent</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The size or duration of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:medium</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The material or physical carrier of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>

            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:IMT</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The Internet media type of the resource <cit>IMT</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>In the case of a digital resource, recommended best practice is to express the
                  Format using a MIME type from the <i>dcterms:IMT</i> scheme. </p>
            </bp>
            <examples>
               <p>For a digitally encoded dictionary:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;text/xml&lt;/dc:format&gt;
&lt;dcterms:extent&gt;5,237 entries in a 1.2M XML file.&lt;/dcterms:extent&gt;</eg>
               <p>For a digitally recorded text:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;audio/wav&lt;/dc:format&gt;
&lt;dc:format&gt;Sampling: 1 channel, 22 KHz, 8 bits.&lt;/dc:format&gt;
&lt;dcterms:extent&gt;Duration: 153 seconds. Size: 3.3M.&lt;/dcterms:extent&gt;</eg>
               <p>For 16mm film with sound track</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:medium&gt;sound, color;  16mm film&lt;/dcterms:medium&gt;
&lt;dcterms:extent&gt;30 min.&lt;/dcterms:extent&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>

         <element name="Identifier">
            <definition>An unambiguous reference to the resource within a given context.</definition>
            <comment>

               <p>In the case of a resource that is not electronically encoded, but is housed in a
                  conventional archive, Identifier may be used to give a local shelf or box number,
                  or whatever scheme is used to locate a resource within the collection.</p>
               <p>Identifiers that begin with “http:” will be interpreted by service providers as
                  URLs and be presented as links in user interfaces. Complete relative link paths
                  with the base server so that the link will be valid outside the search system of
                  the host archives.</p>
               <p>Identifier is of particular value in enabling other resources to unambiguously
                  refer to the resource in focus in terms of a specific relationship. See
                     <xref>Relation</xref> for best practice and usage notes in creating
                  relationship links between resources.</p>
               <p>When using the <i>bibliographicCitation</i> refinement, there is no prescription
                  as to a bibliographic style to use in forming the citation. The only requirement
                  is that sufficient bibliographic detail be included to identify the resource
                  unambiguously.</p>
               <p>A unique identifier that has been assigned to a digital resource by the
                  researcher, a research organization or department, or an archives or library for
                  internal reference may continue to be useful in identifying the resource alongside
                  a URI assigned in the context of a digital repository. Such a unique identifier
                  may be significant for continuity of identification for a digital resource
                  throughout its lifecycle, as other resources may have used such an identifier in
                  referencing the object prior to the assignment of the URI later in its lifecycle.</p>
               <p>Do not specify the “oai:” identifier for the resource itself as a value of
                  Identifier, since it is already given in <tt>&lt;identifier&gt;</tt> in
                  the <tt>&lt;header&gt;</tt> of the <tt>&lt;record&gt;</tt>s
                  returned by the OAI protocol.</p>
               <p>Do not use Identifier for a URL intended to direct the searcher to a
                     <xref>Description</xref>, availability or usage or other
                  <xref>Rights</xref>-related information. A URI may be used in each of those
                  elements or refinements to link to such information. Likewise, Identifier should
                  not be used to refer to a general collection site in which the resource is one of
                  many works available.</p>

            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:bibliographicCitation</dt>
                  <dd>

                     <p>A bibliographic reference for the resource. </p>

                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A Uniform Resource Identifier <cit>URI</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>When the value of Identifier is a Uniform Resource Locator (URL), recommended best
                  practice is to specify the <i>dcterms:URI</i> scheme.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A Uniform Resource Locator for retrieval of an electronically encoded resource:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:identifier xsi:type="dcterms:URI"
   &gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/cs.CL/0010033&lt;/dc:identifier&gt;</eg>
               <p>A local identifier for retrieval within a physical collection:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:identifier&gt;Series: A, Box 7&lt;/dc:identifier&gt;</eg>
               <p>The citation for a chapter that was published in a book:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:bibliographicCitation&gt;In Joel Sherzer and Greg Urban (eds.), 
   Native South American discourse, 237-306. Berlin: Mouton. 
   &lt;dcterms:bibliographicCitation&gt;</eg>

            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Language">
            <definition>A language of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Language is used for a language the resource is in, as opposed to the language it
                  describes (see <xref>Subject</xref>). When a resource is in more than one
                  language, use a separate Language element for each language.</p>
               <p>Best practice is to specify a language code in the <i>olac:code</i> attribute. The
                  element content is typically left empty. When the controlled vocabulary does not
                  offer an appropriate code, the element content may be used to identify the
                  language. It may be used in addition to the code to supply further specificity,
                  such as to give a note about the particular variety or to name a specific dialect.
                  Element content may also be used to give an alternate name that differs from the
                  reference name given by the controlled vocabulary or to give the name of the
                  language in another language.</p>
               <p>For a resource of a particular <cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Type</cit> (see
                  <xref>Type</xref>), the uses of the Language element and the <xref>Subject</xref>
                  element with the <i>olac:language</i> scheme (hereafter referred to as
                  “Subject.language”) can be generally described as follows:</p>
               <ul>
                  <li>
                     <p>For linguistic type <i>primary_text:</i> use the Language element to specify
                        the language of the text. In addition, if it is annotated, use a second
                        Language element to specify the language in which the annotations are made,
                        as well as a Subject.language element repeating the language of the text,
                        which is (in effect) the "subject" of the annotations.</p>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <p>For linguistic type <i>lexicon:</i> use Language for the language in which
                        the definitions are written; use Subject.language for the language whose
                        words are being defined. A bilingual dictionary may have both languages
                        identified in both kinds of elements.</p>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                     <p>For linguistic type <i>language_description:</i> use Language for the
                        language the description is written in, and use Subject.language to specify
                        the language being described. In addition, if the resource contains fairly
                        extensive examples in the language being described (<i>e.g.,</i> many
                        sentence-length examples as might be the case in an extensive grammatical
                        description), it is appropriate to add a Language element for the language
                        being described in order to convey the presence of content in that
                     language.</p>
                  </li>
               </ul>
               <p>For a work of literature or other monolingual document aimed at the speakers of a
                  particular language, use Language to identify that language. For a sound
                  recording, use Language for the language being spoken in the recording.</p>
               <p>Service providers should use the <i>code</i> attribute to support searches by
                  language, and may use the element content in searches by keyword. They also may
                  supply the default language name in keyword searching when the element content is
                  missing.</p>
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>olac:language</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The set of two- and three-letter identifiers from ISO 639 for the
                        identification of individual human languages. See <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>
                        for the definition of the vocabulary. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that every record contain at least one Language
                  element. For a resource that does not include language content, include a Language
                  element containing the code <tt>zxx</tt> for “No linguistic content.”</p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>olac:language</i> scheme with the
                  Language element to identify an individual language precisely. </p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A resource in English about the Sikaiana language:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="eng"/&gt; 
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="sky"/&gt;</eg>
               <p><i>Frönsk-islenzk ordabok ; Dictionnaire français-islandais</i>, a
                  French-Icelandic dictionary, described for an audience where the French names are
                  preferred. (A system could also display the French name of the language based on
                  just the code in the metadata, if a service that maps the codes to French names
                  were available.)</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="fra" xml:lang="fra"&gt;français&lt;/dc:language&gt;
&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="isl" xml:lang="fra"&gt;islandais&lt;/dc:language&gt;
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="fra" xml:lang="fra"&gt;français&lt;/dc:subject&gt;
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="isl" xml:lang="fra"&gt;islandais&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
               <p>The <i>American Heritage Dictionary</i>, which is both in and about American
                  English:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="eng"/&gt;
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="eng"/&gt;
&lt;dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:ISO3166"&gt;US&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource in the Saracatsan dialect of modern Greek</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="ell"&gt;Saracatsan dialect&lt;/dc:language&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Publisher">
            <definition>An entity responsible for making the resource available.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Examples of a Publisher include a person, an organization, or a service.
                  Typically, the name of a Publisher should be used to indicate the entity.
                     <cit>DCMT</cit> The Publisher is generally the business, organization, or
                  sometimes individual who takes responsibility (and provides financial and
                  production resources) for putting the resource into a form suitable for making it
                  publicly available, whether in multiple hard copies (printing, pressing of a disc,
                  etc), by broadcasting (radio, television, webcast), or posting to a public
                  website. A published resource may be offered for sale or freely, but in either
                  case, it is released for public use. </p>
               <p>Many materials that are placed in archival repositories are not formally published
                  in that they have not undergone an editorial, composition and production process,
                  involving review, modification, and packaging by persons other than the original
                  creator(s). While such items may be offered publicly, they are not considered
                  “published” in a formal sense and their metadata should not ordinarily specify a
                  publisher.</p>
               <p>For an entity that has funded the creation or development of the resource in some
                  way, but has not otherwise participated in its development through editing,
                  composition, production, printing, marketing, posting, etc., use the
                     <xref>Contributor</xref> element specifying the <cit>OLAC-Role</cit> as
                     <i>sponsor</i>.</p>
               <p>The name of the publisher should be given in a form that is ready for sorting
                  within an index. See the usage notes above on <xref>Contributor</xref> for a
                  discussion of the form that should be used for personal names and for corporate
                  names.</p>
            </comment>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is to identify a Publisher by means of a name in a form
                  that is ready for sorting within an index.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A typical publisher:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:publisher&gt;Oxford University Press&lt;/dc:publisher&gt;</eg>
               <p>The URL for a publisher:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:publisher xsi:type="dcterms:URI"&gt;http://www.oup.com&lt;/dc:publisher&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Relation">
            <definition>A related resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>This element is used to document relationships between resources, for instance,
                  part-whole relationships, version relationships, dependency relationships, and so
                  on</p>
               <p>When the present resource is a derived work, the source resource is typically
                  indicated by <xref>Source</xref>. However, there are two cases in which
                  refinements of Relation are used for derived works. The <i>isVersionOf</i>
                  refinement is used when the present resource is a new version or edition with
                  added intellectual content that has been developed by the same creators. When the
                  new version is nothing more than a rendition in a new format, then the
                     <i>isForrmatOf</i> refinement is used. </p>
               <p>Metadata that is migrated from the records of a collector or depositor or an
                  earlier repository system might make use of an identifier assigned at that earlier
                  stage in specifying relationship information. Relationships metadata using such
                  internal identifiers in their referencing will be made more useful if they are
                  updated to the OAI identifier at such a time as the metadata for the related
                  resource is also migrated or uploaded to the OAI compliant system.</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:conformsTo</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>An established standard to which the described resource conforms.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:hasFormat</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource that is substantially the same as the pre-existing
                        described resource, but in another format.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:hasPart</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource that is included either physically or logically in the
                        described resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:hasVersion</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource that is a version, edition, or adaptation of the
                        described resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:isFormatOf</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource that is substantially the same as the described resource,
                        but in another format.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:isPartOf</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource in which the described resource is physically or
                        logically included.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:isReferencedBy</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource that references, cites, or otherwise points to the
                        described resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:isReplacedBy</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource that supplants, displaces, or supersedes the described
                        resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:isRequiredBy</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource that requires the described resource to support its
                        function, delivery, or coherence.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:isVersionOf</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource of which the described resource is a version, edition, or
                        adaptation. Changes in version imply substantive changes in content rather
                        than differences in format.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:references</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource that is referenced, cited, or otherwise pointed to by the
                        described resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:replaces</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource that is supplanted, displaced, or superseded by the
                        described resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:requires</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A related resource that is required by the described resource to support its
                        function, delivery, or coherence.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A Uniform Resource Identifier <cit>URI</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>When the related resource is also held in a participating archive, recommended
                  best practice is to identify the related resource by means of its OAI identifier.
                  A Relation that begins with “oai:” will typically be presented by service
                  providers as an active link that retrieves the metadata for that resource.</p>
               <p>If the related resource is not cataloged in the system of a participating archive,
                  recommended best practice is to identify the related resource through a standard
                  unique identifier. If the related resource is available online, specify the
                     <i>dcterms:URI</i> scheme and give a stable Uniform Resource Locator (URL).</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A link to a required font:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:requires&gt;oai:sil:software/ipafont&lt;/dcterms:requires&gt;</eg>
               <p>Links to the component pieces of a collected work:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding126&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding127&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding128&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding129&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding130&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;</eg>
               <p>An XML document that conforms to the TEI Lite DTD:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;text/xml&lt;/dc:format&gt;
&lt;dcterms:conformsTo xsi:type="dcterms:URI"&gt;
  http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/Lite/DTD/teixlite.dtd
  &lt;/dcterms:conformsTo&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Rights">
            <definition>Information about rights held in and over the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p> Typically, a Rights element will contain a rights management statement for the
                  resource, or reference a service providing such information. Rights information
                  often encompasses Intellectual Property Rights (IPR), Copyright, and various
                  Property Rights. If the Rights element is absent, no assumptions can be made about
                  the status of these and other rights with respect to the resource. </p>
               <p>A rights management statement that contains a license or directs a potential user
                  to a license statement that specifies conditions and granted permissions should
                  use the <i>dcterms:license</i> refinement. The <i>dcterms:accessRights</i>
                  refinement should be used to document conditions under which access to the
                  resource is granted. In either case, a statement may be included directly within
                  the metadata, or a URI reference to the statement or a service may be given.
                  Examples of license statements can be found at Creative Commons <cit>CC</cit>.</p>
               <p>Use <xref>Rights Holder</xref> (rather than Rights) to specify a person or
                  corporate body (organization, legally constituted entity representing a group or
                  community) that holds the rights to the resource. </p>
               <p>Copyright is inherent in primary linguistic and cultural research materials, such
                  as stories, descriptions, songs or art work, which researchers collect in the
                  course of their work. The rights, in most cases, belong to the creator—not the
                  researcher or sponsor—or, in some cases, to the language community (particularly,
                  if it is constituted as a legal entity). Intellectual property law as it applies
                  to personal or community cultural property is beyond the scope of these notes.
                  However, documenting the creators of such works, the conditions under which they
                  came into the hands of the researcher, and any known conditions on use (generally
                  non-commercial use) are critical aspects of archiving. To publish or otherwise
                  distribute such works should have the approval of the owner. Only with information
                  about the origins and conditions of collecting can the holding repository or
                  interested researchers make use of such resources in ways that respect the rights
                  and sensibilities of those whose languages and communities are documented.</p>
               <p>A fundamental right of a creator is the right to be associated with his or her
                  creation (whether verbal, textual, visual, etc.), regardless of the retention or
                  subsequent assignment of additional rights (to display, distribute copies,
                  modify). Upholding this right must be balanced with a person's right to privacy
                  with regard to identifying information (including the use of photographs).
                  Demographic data about a creator, contributor or research participant, along with
                  identifying information, is often included in research data. Identifying
                  information may be removed prior to deposit, or as a condition of release, or a
                  Rights element may document a statement of permission to use a resource or parts
                  of a resource in a particular way that may otherwise have been an infringement of
                  privacy.</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:accessRights</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Information about who can access the resource or an indication of its
                        security status.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:license</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A legal document giving official permission to do something with the
                        resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <examples>
               <p>A description of the terms of use:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:rights&gt;The Surrey Syncretisms Database can be accessed without 
   cost. Users agree not to pass on the Database to third parties and  
   to properly acknowledge the Surrey Syncretism Database as the source 
   of information in publications or manuscripts that make use of its 
   data.&lt;/dc:rights&gt;</eg>
               <p>Instructions on how to get access:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:accessRights&gt;Apply in writing for permission to use this 
   resource.&lt;/dcterms:accessRights&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource made available under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike
                  license:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:license&gt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/
   &lt;/dcterms:license&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Source">
            <definition>The resource from which the described resource is derived.</definition>
            <comment>
               <!-- Move to <bp><p>? -->
               <p>The present resource may be derived from the Source resource in whole or in part.
                     <cit>DCMT</cit>
               </p>
               <p> In the legal parlance of intellectual property rights, a “derivative work” is one
                  that is based on one or more preexisting works. This includes cases in which a
                  work may be recast, transformed, or adapted in any way, such as by translation,
                  abridgement, dramatization, recording, transcription, or digital encoding. A work
                  consisting of editorial revisions, annotations, elaborations, or other
                  modifications, which, as a whole, represent an original work of authorship is also
                  a derivative work <cit>Copyright</cit>.</p>
               <p>This legal definition elucidates the sense of “derived” that is intended in the
                  Dublin Core definition of Source. Note, however, that this overlaps with
                     <xref>Relation</xref>, since the <i>isFormatOf</i> and <i>isVersionOf</i>
                  refinements both refer to derivative works in the technical sense.</p>
               <p>Use Source (as opposed to one of the above two Relation refinements) in cases when
                  the present resource has a substantially different <xref>Type</xref> or
                     <xref>Creator</xref> or <xref>Title</xref> than the Source resource. When the
                  difference from the original work is only a difference of <xref>Date</xref> or
                     <xref>Format</xref> or <xref>Publisher</xref> or <xref>Identifier</xref> or
                  edition, then use Relation (or the appropriate refinement) to encode the
                  relationship to the original work.</p>
            </comment>

            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A Uniform Resource Identifier <cit>URI</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is as for the Relation element above. </p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>Source for a digital encoding of a manuscript in a participating archive:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:source&gt;oai:somearchive:holding1023&lt;/dc:source&gt;</eg>
               <p>Source for data extracted from a published source:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:source&gt;Kwara'ae flora vocabulary extracted from Guide to the Forests 
   of the British Solomon Islands, by T. C. Whitmore. Oxford University 
   Press, 1966.&lt;/dc:source&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Subject">
            <definition>The topic of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Typically, a Subject will be expressed as keywords, key phrases or classification
                  codes that describe a topic of the resource. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>The usage notes for <xref>Language</xref> are also relevant to Subject when a
                  human language is a subject of the resource. In particular, those notes discuss
                  how element content may be used in conjunction with the <i>olac:language</i>
                  scheme and how the <i>olac:language</i> scheme is used with Subject for resources
                  of different linguistic types. It is also appropriate to use the
                  <i>olac:language</i> scheme with Subject for works that are not of any particular
                     <i>olac:linguistic-type</i>, but that do treat a language (or a community of
                  its users) as a topic of study.</p>
               <p>To describe the spatial or temporal topic of the resource, use the
                  <xref>Coverage</xref> element.</p>
               <p>The Subject element should not be confused with <xref>Description</xref>. Subject
                  contains subject headings or concise individual topic terms, while Description
                  contains free-text, prose descriptions.</p>
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:LCSH</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The set of labeled concepts specified by the Library of Congress Subject
                        Headings.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>olac:language</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The set of two- and three-letter identifiers from ISO 639 for the
                        identification of individual human languages. See <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>
                        for the definition of the vocabulary and see the <xref>Language</xref>
                        element for a complete discussion (with examples) of using this scheme.</p>
                     <!-- Move to a <bp><p>? -->
                  </dd>
                  <dt>olac:linguistic-field</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The OLAC vocabulary for describing the content of a resource as relevant to
                        a particular subfield of linguistic science
                        <cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Field</cit>. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that a metadata record should contain at least one
                  Subject or Coverage (or one of its refinements) or Description element (or one of
                  its refinements) in order to give the prospective user some idea of the content of
                  the resource that goes beyond the informative potential of just a title alone.
                  Using all of these elements is encouraged.</p>
               <p>When the subject is a human language, recommended best practice is to use the
                     <i>olac:language</i> scheme with the Subject element to identify an individual
                  language precisely. </p>
               <p>When the subject matter falls within the field of linguistics, recommended best
                  practice is to use the <i>olac:linguistic-field</i> scheme to identify the
                  subfield.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A Library of Congress subject heading:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="dcterms:LCSH"&gt;African languages&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource about a language for which the controlled vocabulary does not yet
                  provide a code:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language"&gt;Medieval Greek&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource on multilingual education in Uganda involving national, regional and
                  local languages.</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:subject&gt;Multilingual education&lt;/dc:subject&gt;
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="swh"/&gt;
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="eng"/&gt;
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="xog"/&gt;
   ...
   &lt;dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:ISO3166"&gt;UG&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
               <p>See also the examples for <xref>Language</xref>.</p>
            </examples>
         </element>

         <element name="Title">
            <definition>A name given to the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Typically, a Title will be a name by which the resource is formally known.
                     <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>Normally the title of a resource is given to the resource by its creator, be that
                  an author, artist, photographer, or compiler (as the creator of a collection). For
                  a resource that has no formal title given by its creator, the cataloger or
                  archivist should give the work some brief descriptive label as a title. Such a
                  supplied title is typically enclosed in square brackets.</p>
               <p>A related use of square brackets is for supplying additional information where, in
                  the opinion of the cataloger, the title itself needs additional clarifying
                  information, or where the formal title contains a typographical or factual error.
                  In such a case, the formal title is transcribed as given, with additional or
                  corrective information supplied in square brackets.</p>
               <p>The title is generally expected to be in the language in which the work is written
                  or recorded. If the title is in a language different from the language identified
                  in a <xref>Language</xref> element, use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute on the Title
                  element to specify the language in which the title is actually given.</p>
               <p>A translation of the title is supplied in a <i>dcterms:alternative</i> element.
                  Use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute to identify the language of the translated title
                  using an identifier from <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>.</p>
               <p>The only approved use of repeated instances of the Title element is in the case of
                  a polyglot work, where the text is given in two or more languages in some kind of
                  parallel format (whether facing columns or pages, or roughly equal, separate
                  sections) and the title on the title page (or equivalent source of information
                  on/in the resource itself) is given in each of the text languages. This is what
                  librarians refer to as “parallel titles.” In this case, it is permissible to
                  repeat the Title element. It will be expected that there are also multiple
                     <xref>Language</xref> elements, and that each of the Title elements carries an
                     <i>xml:lang</i> attribute that specifies a language that is also given in one
                  of the Language elements. </p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:alternative</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Any form of the title used as a substitute or alternative to the formal
                        title of the resource. Comment: This qualifier can include an abbreviated or
                        shortened title, a "cover title" that differs from the formal title, or a
                        translated title. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that every record must have an instance of the Title
                  element. When the resource does not have a formal title, the cataloger should
                  supply a descriptive title and enclose it in square brackets.</p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that there be only one instance of the unqualified
                  Title element, namely, for the original title (except in the case of parallel
                  titles on a diglot work). All other titles (<i>e.g.,</i> translations) should be
                  specified as the <i>dcterms:alternative</i> refinement.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A typical title:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;A grammar of the Nggela language&lt;/dc:title&gt;</eg>
               <p>A vernacular title with a translated title:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title xml:lang="llu"&gt;Na tala 'uria na idulaa diana&lt;/dc:title&gt; 
&lt;dcterms:alternative xml:lang="eng"&gt;The road to good reading&lt;/dcterms:alternative&gt;</eg>
               <p>A work with parallel titles, as typically employed for a diglot work:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title xml:lang="amc"&gt;Xunivaun jau yohipahonni&lt;/dc:title&gt;
&lt;dc:title xml:lang="spa"&gt;Cuentos de nuestros antepasados&lt;/dc:title&gt;
&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="amc"/&gt;
&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="spa"/&gt;</eg>
               <p>A work (a photograph) without a formal title, for which the cataloger has supplied
                  a title:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;[J.P. Harrington with three Tule Indians, making 
   dictaphone records of language and songs of the Cuna,
   in the Smithsonian Institution]&lt;/dc:title&gt;</eg>
               <p>A title of a work to which the cataloger added some information to clarify the
                  nature of the resource (originally cataloged in a system prior to the addition of
                     <i>linguistic-type</i>):</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;Subanon [language texts]&lt;/dc:title&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>

         <element name="Type">
            <definition>The nature or genre of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p> Type includes terms describing general categories, functions, genres, or
                  aggregation levels for content. The <cit>DCMI-Type</cit> vocabulary specifies a
                  controlled vocabulary to be used to with Type. These relate to the intended use or
                  mode of perception by a user, <i>e.g.,</i> whether it is read (as text), viewed
                  (as image), heard, etc. Thus, a computer image file of a text (such as a scanned
                  document) is type <i>Text</i>, not type <i>Image</i>, because the common use
                  involves reading text. To describe the physical or digital manifestation of the
                  resource, use the <xref>Format</xref> element. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>The DCMI type <i>Collection</i> should be used in conjunction with one or more
                  other applicable type terms to represent the nature of the resource as an
                  aggregate of specific, but closely related resources, resources which could also
                  stand on their own but were grouped together as a unit by their creator or a
                  subsequent compiler. See <xref>Granularity of resources</xref> below for more
                  discussion.</p>
               <p>Whereas the DCMI Type scheme should be relevant to all resources, include a Type
                  element with the <cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Type</cit> scheme only if a resource
                  represents one of the structural types covered in that vocabulary. The element may
                  be repeated if a resource represents more than one linguistic type. So, for
                  example, a primary text accompanied by a lexicon of vocabulary items would be
                  described as both a primary text and a lexicon. </p>
               <!-- <p>In the case of a primary text
                  (or collection of such texts), adequate description of a linguistic resource will require that 
                  Linguistic Type be specified in conjunction with the Discourse Type extension of the Type element, or the Linguistic
                  extension of the Subject element. For example, a narrative text might be described as both a
                  primary text (OLAC Linguistic Type) and a narrative (OLAC Discourse Type). </p> -->
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:DCMIType</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A list of types used to categorize the nature or genre of the content of the
                        resource. <cit>DCMI-Type</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>olac:linguistic-type</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The nature or genre of the content of the resource from a linguistic
                        standpoint <cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Type</cit>. For a resource that is
                        information in or about a language, use this scheme to identify what kind of
                        information it is from a linguistic standpoint.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>olac:discourse-type</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The genre of the content of the resource as representing a particular type
                        of discourse <cit>OLAC-Discourse</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that every record should contain at least one Type
                  element that uses the <i>dcterms:DCMIType</i> scheme.</p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that every record for which it is applicable should
                  contain at least one Type element that uses the <i>olac:linguistic-type</i> scheme
                  to identify its linguistic data type. </p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>The resource is a video recording, stored in MPEG format:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage&lt;/cd:type&gt;
&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;image/mpeg&lt;/dc:format&gt;</eg>
               <p>The resource is a video recording of a story teller relating a traditional story,
                  recorded on Super-8 film:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType"&gt;MovingImage&lt;/cd:type&gt;
&lt;dc:type xsi:type="olac:linguistic-type" olac:code="primary_text"/&gt;
&lt;dc:medium&gt;Super 8mm film&lt;/dc:medium&gt;</eg>
               <p>The resource is a collection of written texts:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;Historia araona: Narrada por Bani Huali&lt;/dc:title&gt;
&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType"&gt;Collection&lt;/cd:type&gt;
&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType"&gt;Text&lt;/cd:type&gt;
&lt;dc:type xsi:type="olac:linguistic-type" olac:code="primary_text"/&gt;</eg>
               <p>A database resource (offering multiple user formats) that also integrates textual
                  reports and embedded photographs:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;Agta Demographic Database: chronicle of a hunter-gatherer 
   community in transition&lt;/dc:title&gt;
&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType"&gt;Dataset&lt;/cd:type&gt;
&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;application/msaccess&lt;/dc:format&gt;
&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;text/xml&lt;/dc:format&gt;
&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;text/csv&lt;/dc:format&gt;
&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType"&gt;Text&lt;/cd:type&gt;
&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType"&gt;StillImage&lt;/cd:type&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
            <!--
               <p>The following is leftover from 2002; do we still want it? For a resource that is a
                  software tool, Type.linguistic identifies what kind of information it processes.
                  Service providers may use this information to match data files with software tools
                  that might be applied to them.</p>
            -->
         </element>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>Other elements</heading>
         <p>The following subsections describe other elements that have been defined by the Dublin
            Core Metadata Initiative <cit>DCMT</cit>. They were not specified in the original core
            set of Dublin Core elements, but have been subsequently defined as elements in their own
            right (rather than being refinements of other elements).They are defined within the
               <url>http://purl.org/dc/terms/</url> namespace for which the prefix <tt>dcterms:</tt>
            is used in the examples below.</p>
         <element name="Provenance">
            <definition>A statement of any changes in ownership and custody of the resource since
               its creation that are significant for its authenticity, integrity and interpretation.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Provenance should be distinguished in usage from <xref>Description</xref>.
                  Provenance metadata should be used to track or convey important information
                  regarding the custody and/or management of the resource throughout its history.
                  Include any information that has a bearing on interpreting content of the resource
                  or upon its artifactual integrity and authenticity.</p>
            </comment>
            <examples>
               <p>A group of texts and recordings constituting a small collection that has undergone
                  some reorganization by a subsequent handler since original creation:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="compiler"&gt;Gardner, 
   Richard&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;
&lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="annotator"&gt;Anderson, Judi 
   Lynn&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;
&lt;dc:created&gt;1962-1976&lt;/dc:created&gt;
&lt;dc:available&gt;2007&lt;/dc:available&gt;
&lt;dc:description&gt;Collection of 23 texts, with original recordings of 17 of the 
   texts. Texts were originally transcribed using a variety of othographic 
   conventions, some with interlinear analytical transcriptions, some also 
   with Spanish free translations.&lt;/dc:description&gt;
&lt;dcterms:provenance&gt;Collection of texts recorded by Gardner, transcribed 
   with the assistance of a number of local residents. Body of materials 
   were transferred to custody of SIL Mexico Branch in 1980s, subsequently 
   organized,  collated and annotated by J. L. Anderson, a researcher in a 
   closely related Chinantec language. Annotations particularly relate to 
   changes in orthographic and tone marking conventions over the years of 
   collection and as compared to current practices.&lt;/dcterms:provenance&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>

         <element name="Rights Holder">
            <definition>A person or organization owning or managing rights over the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Use the URI or name of the Rights Holder to indicate the entity.</p>
            </comment>
            <examples>
               <p>Name of the copyright holder:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:rightsHolder&gt;	Copyright Regents of the University of California&lt;/dcterms:rightsHolder&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>

      </section>

      <section>
         <heading>Granularity of resources</heading>
         <p>Determining the right level for units to be described as language resources in the OLAC
            context involves multiple factors. The level of unit appropriate for inclusion in an
            aggregated catalog like OLAC's may be different (typically higher) than the level
            desirable for the catalog of a specific institution's holdings, which in turn is
            typically higher than the level desirable for describing the detailed contents of a
            resource. Section 6 of the <cit>OLAC-Repositories</cit> standard establishes the
            following basic guideline regarding the granularity of the records in an OLAC
            repository: “A metadata repository should not degrade the 'signal-to-noise ratio' for
            language resource discovery.” At one extreme, describing an entire institutional archive
            in one record does not give enough granularity; but at the other extreme, providing a
            descriptive record for every digital file or every piece of paper gives too much. The
            following discussion is aimed at assisting an OLAC participant to find the right level
            of description.</p>
         <p>For a resource that has been published in some form, the appropriate unit of description
            for the OLAC record is the unit of the publication itself. In this case, granularity
            does not really pose a problem. However, many archival resources have not been formally
            published. For unpublished papers presenting findings of research, these closely
            parallel typical publications, and can be treated in a comparable way as units for
            archival description.</p>
         <p>Granularity poses the greatest problem with primary source materials (<i>e.g.,</i>
            recordings, transcriptions, annotations, notes, data sets). The typical practice of
            archivists is to gather such materials into collections, which in turn become the
            primary unit of archival description (<i>i.e.,</i> the result is resources of type
               <i>collection</i>; see <xref>Type</xref>). The foremost factor in determining what
            materials belong together as a single collection is their <xref>Provenance</xref>. In
            the typical case, the collected resources have a shared provenance. In other cases, they
            may have been placed together at some point in time well after their creation (possibly
            by the archive itself). If the latter, there should be some coherent organizing
            principle or intermediate stage of development that is still relevant for the proper
            understanding and use of the resources. Materials without a common provenance generally
            should not be made to constitute a collection and should not be described collectively
            in an OLAC description.</p>
         <p>Situations of shared provenance that constitute a collection for arrangement and
            description purposes will be distinguished by the high degree of commonality of metadata
            elements, <i>e.g.,</i> same researcher(s), author(s), subject language(s), content
            language(s), approximate dates, coverage, linguistic type. Other metadata elements that
            may also be important for resource discovery but that may differ for items in the
            collection (<i>e.g.,</i> format or discourse type) can be repeated at the OLAC
            description level for as many values as are present in the collection. Alternatively,
            the collection may be divided into sub-collections by discourse genre, speaker, or other
            significant feature. The sub-collections can then be treated in distinct OLAC records
            (and related to the whole through the <i>isPartOf</i> and <i>hasPart</i> relationships;
            see <xref>Relation</xref>).</p>
         <p>Further characteristics of individual items within a collection (such as topic,
            additional contributors, event specifics, extent, format) can be documented at a finer
            level of granularity by creating a “collection description” as a structured document
            that is included within the collection. The Object Reuse and Exchange standard currently
            under development by the Open Archives Initiative <cit>OAI-ORE</cit> would offer an
            alternative of handling such descriptions as a different kind of harvestable metadata in
            the OAI-PMH context. This finer level of description typically aligns with the session
            level detail of <cit>IMDI</cit> description.</p>
         <!-- GS: I've commented out the following two paragraphs.  The first seems to go beyond
            structured metadata, and the second seems not to help with the question, "What
            do I do with what I have today?"  The point seems to be more like, At some
            point in the future you may find that you have a series of incremental
            collections as things get submitted incrementally; but someone might interpret
            it as advise to retrofit increments when it is was submitted all at once.
         <p>Some OLAC elements may be applicable at this secondary level, but other possible aspects
            of descriptions may be quite unique to the collection of materials in hand. For example,
            it could be valuable to document the orthography used for a given written text (whether
            transcription or original writing) in a collection where different orthographies are
            represented. It is at this second level that the description becomes something of its
            own creative endeavor, as the collection's compiler or the archivist creating this level
            of description seeks to offer additional detail in an organized way that will enhance
            the utility of the collection for future researchers.</p>
         <p>The timing of acquisition of materials, whether they are received as a group at one
            point in time or accrue (are submitted to the repository) over a period of time, is a
            second significant factor in determining the units of grouping for OLAC level
            description. Materials that are collected together and organized by some knowledgeable
            person (perhaps the original researcher, perhaps not) may properly constitute a single
            collection (as a single unit of OLAC description) with a complex secondary level of
            collection description. Yet those same materials, had they been deposited periodically
            over time, might just as well constitute numerous smaller collections, each with its own
            OLAC level descriptive record.</p>
            -->

      </section>


   </body>
   <references>
      <ref abbrev="AACR2r">Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules, 2nd ed., 2002 revision. Ottawa and
         Chicago: Canadian Library Association and American Library Association, 2002-.</ref>

      <!--  <ref abbrev="Copyright">Section 101, Definitions, Copyright Law of the United States of
         America and Related Laws Contained in Title 17 of the United States Code.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.loc.gov/copyright/title17/92chap1.html#101</url>&gt;</ref>
-->
      <ref abbrev="CC">Creative Commons
            Licenses.<br/>&lt;<url>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DC-Lib">DC-Library Application Profile.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/library-application-profile/index.shtml#creator</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMT">Dublin Core Metadata Terms.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMI-Box">DCMI Box Encoding Scheme: specification of the spatial limits of a
         place, and methods for encoding this in a text string.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-box/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMI-Period">DCMI Period Encoding Scheme: specification of the limits of a time
         interval, and methods for encoding this in a text
            string.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-period/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMI-Point">DCMI Point Encoding Scheme: a point location in space, and methods
         for encoding this in a text string.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-point/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMI-Type">DCMI Type Vocabulary.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-type-vocabulary/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="IMT">MIME Media
            Types.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="IMDI"> IMDI [ISLE Metadata Initiative] Metadata Elements for Session
         Descriptions.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.mpi.nl/ISLE/documents/draft/ISLE_MetaData_2.5.pdf</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="ISO3166">ISO 3166: Codes for the Representation of Names of Countries.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.iso.org/iso/country_codes/iso_3166_code_lists.htm</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="URI">Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI): Generic Syntax.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2396.txt</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OAI-ORE">Open Archives Initiative Object Reuse and
            Exchange.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/ore/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-BP">Best Practice Recommendations for Language Resource
            Description.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/bpr.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Discourse">OLAC Discourse Type Vocabulary.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/discourse.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Linguistic-Field">OLAC Linguistic Subject
            Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/field.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Linguistic-Type">OLAC Linguistic Data Type
            Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/type.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Metadata">OLAC
            Metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Language">OLAC Language
            Extension.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/language.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Role">OLAC Role
            Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/role.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="TGN">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic
            Names.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabulary/tgn/index.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Extensions">Recommended Metadata Extensions.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/olac-extensions.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Repositories">OLAC Repositories.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/repositories.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="W3CDTF">Date and Time Formats, W3C
            Note.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-datetime</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="XML-Lang">Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Fourth Edition), W3C
         Recommendation 16 August 2006. Section 2.12, Language
            Identification.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml#sec-lang-tag</url>&gt;</ref>

   </references>
</OLAC_doc>
