<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../OLAC_doc.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "../OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc>
   <header>
      <status code="draft" type="informational"/>
      <title>OLAC Metadata Usage Guidelines</title>
      <baseName>usage</baseName>
      <issued>20071115</issued>
      <previousIssued/>
      <abstract>
         <p>This document provides guidelines on the meaning and proper usage of the metadata elements used in the
            metadata standard of the Open Language Archives Community.</p>
      </abstract>
      <editors>Gary Simons, SIL International (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>) <br/>Steven Bird, University of
         Pennsylvania (<url>mailto:sb@ldc.upenn.edu</url>) <br/>Joan Spanne, SIL International
            (<url>mailto:joan_spanne@sil.org</url>)</editors>
      <copyright>2007 Gary Simons (SIL International), Steven Bird (University of Pennsylvania), and Joan Spanne (SIL
         International)</copyright>
      <changes/>
   </header>
   <body>
      <section>
         <heading>Introduction</heading>
         <p>This document provides guidelines on how to describe language resources using the OLAC metadata standard
               <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>. The standard itself documents the formal syntax of valid metadata records, but
            does not explain or exemplify the use of the individual metadata elements. That is the purpose of this
            document. </p>
         <p>Section 2 below describes the usage of the attributes that may be used on metadata elements. Section 3 then
            describes usage in the OLAC context for the fifteen core elements of the Dublin Core metadata set. Section 4
            describes other elements that may be used.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>All elements</heading>
         <p>OLAC metadata is an application of the Dublin Core metadata element set as
            defined in <cit>DCMT</cit>. The most fundamental requirement on best practice
            in OLAC is that each element should be used in a way that conforms to its
            definition in <cit>DCMT</cit>. This document therefore repeats those
            definitions and offers usage notes and examples to help the reader understand
            best use of the elements.</p>
         <p>Eight of the elements in the Dublin Core metadata set define refinements that narrow the
            meaning of the element. A refinement shares the
            meaning of the generic element, but with a more restricted scope. When the
            more restricted meaning applies, it is
            recommended best practice to use the refined version of an element rather than
            the generic one. This document lists the refinements that are possible for
            each element.</p>
         <p>In theory, every element in the metadata set may use the <i>xsi:type</i>
            attribute to specify an encoding scheme that defines a controlled vocabulary
            or a controlled syntax for its values. This document lists possible encoding
            schemes for eleven of the elements, whether defined by <cit>DCMT</cit> or 
            <cit>OLAC-Extensions</cit>. In the case of the OLAC extensions, the controlled
            value goes in the <i>olac:code</i> attribute (with the element content being
            available for an optional freeform elaboration of the coded value), while in the case of DCMI
            encoding schemes the controlled value goes in the element content. When one of these encoding schemes is applicable,
            it is recommended best practice to use it since this adds a precision to the
            value of the element that can be exploited
            to improve accuracy in searching and to provide domain-specific services.
            Subcommunities may follow the extension mechanism defined in section 5 of
            <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit> to define new encoding schemes.</p>
         <p>Every element in the metadata set may use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute. It specifies the language in which
            the text in the content of the element is written. The value for the attribute
            should be a three-letter code from the ISO 639-3 controlled
            vocabulary as defined in <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>. In the absence of an
            <i>xml:lang</i> attribute, the element content is assumed to be in
            English (unless it is from a DCMI encoding scheme).  Whenever the language of the element content is other than English, recommended best practice
            is to use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute to identify the language. By using
            multiple instances of a metadata
            elements tagged for different languages, data providers may offer their metadata records in multiple
            languages. </p>
         <p>In the formal definition of the metadata standard <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>,
            every element and refinement is optional and repeatable. However, recommended
            best practice (as described below for particular elements and in
            <cit>OLAC-BP</cit>) requires that certain elements be present in order to give
         a basic breadth of description for a language resource. Recommended best practice
         also requires that one particular element (namely, <xref>Title</xref>) not be
            repeated. Since all other elements and refinements are repeatable, multiple
            values for an element or refinement should be given in multiple instances of
            the XML element rather than being listed in a single instance. This makes it
            possible for service providers to build search indexes on the individual
            values.</p>
         <p>To summarize, the following are recommended best practices that apply to all elements:</p>
         <element name="All elements">
            <definition><!-- Don't use. Just a trick to make export to RED/bpr.xml work. --></definition>
            <comment><!-- Ditto. --></comment>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is for the value of each metadata element to conform to the definition of
                  that element as given in <cit>DCMT</cit>.</p>
               <p>When the meaning of a particular element in a metadata record fits the definition of a refinement,
               recommended best practice is to use the refinement rather than the generic element.</p>
               <p>When possible, recommended best practice is to use the <i>xsi:type</i>
                  attribute to specify an encoding scheme for adding precision to the
                  value of the element.</p>
               <p>Whenever the language of the element content is other than English, recommended best practice is to
                  use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute with a value from <cit>ISO639-3</cit> to identify the language.</p>
               <p>When a resource has more than one value for a particular metadata
                  element or refinement, recommended best practice
                  is to use a separate instance of the element or refinement for each
                  value rather than listing all the
                  values in a single instance.</p>
            </bp>
            <examples><!-- This is implemented in the stylesheet if we want to give
               examples --></examples>
         </element>

      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>Core elements</heading>
         <p>Each of the fifteen core elements of the Dublin Core metadata set is described in one of the following subsections.
            These elements are defined in the <url>http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/</url>
            namespace for which the prefix <tt>dc:</tt> is used in the examples.</p>
         <p>Each subsection heading gives the name of an element; the element is then described under six subheadings.
               <i>Definition</i> is the definition for the element as given by the Dublin Core Metadata Initiative
               <cit>DCMT</cit>. <i>Refinements</i> lists the refined element names 
            that may be used in place of the generic element name to specify a more precise meaning for the metadata
            item. The refinement definitions are copied from <cit>DCMT</cit>. All of the
            refinements are defined within the
            <url>http://purl.org/dc/terms/</url> namespace for which the prefix <tt>dcterms:</tt> is
            used in the examples. <i>Schemes</i> lists the encoding schemes
            that may be used with this element (or its refinements) as the value of the <i>xsi:type</i> attribute.
               <i>Best practice</i> lists the best practices for the use of this element that are recommended by the
            OLAC community <cit>OLAC-BP</cit>. <i>Usage notes</i> offers additional notes for the OLAC community on how
            to use the element in the context of describing language resources. <i>Examples</i> shows samples of
            properly encoded elements and sample refinements.</p>
         <!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
         <p>For many elements, you can have more than one instance. This would be the case for a work with more than one
            author, or for which you want to specify two or three languages, multiple subject terms, etc. In such cases,
            repeat the element for each person, language, etc., rather than placing all of them in a single instance of
            the field. Most elements can be repeated if needed.</p>
         <element name="Contributor">
            <definition>An entity responsible for making contributions to the resource.</definition>
            <comment>

               <p>A Contributor may be a person, an organization, or a service. Contributor is closely related to
                     <xref>Creator</xref>. A case for distinguishing the usage of the two elements can be made based on
                  the degree of responsibility for the content. The Contributor designation can be used for those
                  entities whose role in the creation of the resource is not great enough to merit recognition as a
                  primary source of the intellectual content. Thus, the Contributor element would be used to identify
                  institutions that sponsored or funded the work, or to identify individuals who played a secondary role
                  in the development of the resource (<i>e.g.</i>, roles such as consultant, depositor, responder). The
                  Creator element would be used to identify individuals or group entities that are primarily responsible
                  for the intellectual content (<i>e.g.</i>, roles such as author, performer).</p>
               <p>The application of the olac:role schema with its more precise vocabulary makes drawing a distinction
                  between the less precise concepts of Contributor and Creator of much less significance. Thus, an
                  alternative to making the above distinction between Contributor and Creator is to use only the
                  Contributor element, always specifying the more precise nature of the contribution through the use of
                  the olac:role vocabulary (as is recommended best practice in any case).</p>
               <p>Contributor and <xref>Publisher</xref> are also somewhat related elements. In particular, the
                  olac:role "sponsor" can come close to one aspect of participation that a publisher may have in regard
                  to making a given resource available to the public. The olac:role "editor" is frequently one of the
                  individual tasks that are collectively performed by the publisher of a work. A "sponsor" that is not
                  also the formal publisher of a resource may be entered in a Contributor element (with the proper
                  olac:role specified), but the publisher should not be repeated in a Contributor element.</p>
               <p>The entry element for a personal name will vary according to conventions used in a given location
                  and with a given language. General practice among librarians is to select as the entry element that 
                  part of the name under which the person would normally be listed in an authoritative alphabetical list 
                  in his or her own language or country of residence or primary activity. If the entry element is a surname, 
                  follow the surname with a comma. If the entry element is the "first name" or "given name," do not follow 
                  it with a comma. Consult the Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules, 2nd ed., rev., <cit>AACR2r</cit> chapter 22
                  for additional guidance in determining entry elements and the normal ordering and forms of names based 
                  on language and country, as well as other name characteristics.</p>
               <p>Be consistent with corporate name forms. Names that include a primary unit and subsidiary unit should
                  be ordered with the primary unit given first. Location should generally be omitted from the name
                  unless location is an integral part of the proper name of the unit. More guidance on the forms of corporate 
                  names may be found in <cit>AACR2r</cit>, chapter 24.</p>
               <p>Do not use quotation marks to enclose corporate names. If the name is a translation from its usual
                  form or is not usually given in English, use the lang attribute.</p>

            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>olac:role</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The olac:role code is optionally used to specify the role (such as transcriber, sponsor, and so
                        on) played by the named entity in the creation of the resource. The role is expressed by means
                        of a controlled vocabulary; see <cit>OLAC-Role</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is to identify a Contributor by means of a name in a form that is ready for
                  sorting within an index. For the names of persons, this means that the name should be given with the
                  usual entry element first (<i>i.e.</i>, an "inverted" order for most Western name forms where the surname
                  is the usual entry element). For the names of organizations, this means that any initial article should be omitted. </p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>olac:role</i> scheme to indicate the role of the
                  Contributor.</p>
            </bp>
            <examples>
               <p>A generic contributor:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor&gt;Smith, John L.&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
               <p>A funding agency:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="sponsor"&gt;Smithsonian Institution. 
   Office of Fellowships and Grants.&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
               <p>The person who performed a role for which there is not a suitable code:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor&gt;Smith, John L. (format conversion)&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
               <p>A corporate name given in a language differing from the majority of the metadata record:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor xml:lang="ces"&gt;Česká akademie věd a umění&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Coverage">
            <definition>The spatial or temporal topic of the resource, the spatial applicability of the resource, or the
               jurisdiction under which the resource is relevant.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p> Coverage will typically include spatial location (a place name or geographic coordinates), temporal
                  period (a period label, date, or date range) or jurisdiction (such as a named administrative entity).
                     <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>Coverage is related to <xref>Subject</xref> in having a topical orientation. Coverage in its temporal
                  aspect should not be confused with <xref>Date</xref> or one of its refinements (<i>e.g.</i>, created,
                  or available). Thus, a data set that was compiled over an extended period of time should be described
                  via <tt>dcterms:created</tt> whose content is a date range, rather than with Coverage or
                     <tt>dcterms:temporal</tt>. A data set (or any kind of resource) that contains or addresses
                  historical information would correctly use Coverage or <tt>dcterms:temporal</tt> to specify the date,
                  date range or period in focus.</p>
               <p>In the OLAC context, service providers already have a database that maps languages to the countries in
                  which they are spoken <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>. Coverage should not be used to duplicate this
                  information; rather service providers will support searches concerning languages spoken in a given
                  country by referring to the language database. Coverage should be used geographically only when the
                  language involved has a wide distribution and the resource focuses on its use in a particular region
                  or geopolitical jurisdiction, or conversely, when the resource deals with a topic of study in which
                  the region itself is in focus, <i>e.g.</i>, multilingualism, language polilcy, languages in contact,
                  in a given locale.</p>
               <p/>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>spatial</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Spatial characteristics of the intellectual content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>temporal</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Temporal characteristics of the intellectual content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:Box</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The DCMI Box identifies a region of space using its geographic limits <cit>DCMI-Box</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:ISO3166</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>ISO 3166 Codes for the representation of names of countries <cit>ISO3166</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:Period</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A specification of the limits of a time interval <cit>DCMI-Period</cit></p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:Point</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The DCMI Point identifies a point in space using its geographic coordinates
                        <cit>DCMI-Point</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:TGN</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names <cit>TGN</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that a metadata record should contain at least one Description (or one of
                  its refinements) or Coverage (or one of its refinements) or Subject element. While these are different
                  in purpose and content, they nevertheless give the prospective user some idea of the content of the
                  resource that goes beyond the informative potential of just a title alone. Using all of these elements
                  is encouraged.</p>
               <p>In the case of Spatial coverage, recommended best practice is to use an encoding scheme to give
                  precise geocoding of the resource.</p>
            </bp>


            <examples>
               <p>A resource about English in India:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639" olac:code="en"/&gt;&lt;dcterms:spatial&gt;India&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource about languages spoken on Guadalcanal:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:TGN"&gt;Guadalcanal (island)&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource about language use in the 19th century:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:temporal&gt;19th century&lt;/dcterms:temporal&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Creator">
            <definition>An entity primarily responsible for making the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>A Creator may be a person, an organization, or a service. Creator is closely related to
                     <xref>Contributor</xref>. Creator may be differentiated from Contributor based on the degree of
                  involvement as a primary source of the intellectual content. In determining whether an entity is a
                  Creator (as opposed to a Contributor), consider the role in the creation of the resource, using the
                  same criteria that are followed for deciding that an entity should be listed as an "author" in a
                  bibliographic reference of the resource. Entities that do not merit that level of recognition should
                  be treated as Contributors.</p>
               <p>The application of the olac:role schema with its more precise vocabulary makes drawing a distinction
                  between the less precise concepts of Contributor and Creator of much less significant. Thus, an
                  alternative to making the above distinction between Contributor and Creator is to use only the
                  Contributor element, always specifying the more precise nature of the contribution through the use of
                  the olac:role vocabulary (as is recommended best practice in any case).</p>

            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>olac:role</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The <i>refine</i> attribute is optionally used to specify the role (such as author, editor,
                        translator, and so on) played by the named entity in the creation of the resource. The role is
                        expressed by means of a controlled vocabulary; see <cit>OLAC-Role</cit> for the definition of
                        the vocabulary. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is as for the Contributor element above.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A personal author:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:creator&gt;Bloomfield, Leonard&lt;/dc:creator&gt;</eg>
               <p>An institutional author:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:creator&gt;Linguistic Society of America&lt;/dc:creator&gt;</eg>
               <p>An editor:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:creator xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="editor"&gt;Sapir, Edward&lt;/dc:creator&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Date">
            <definition>A point or period of time associated with an event in the lifecycle of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>A WSCDTF-conformant value may be for the year alone, for the year and month, or for an exact date. A
                  range of years is also a valid value; in this case both years must be four-digit values and the
                  earliest year should come first. Thus, the element value may match one of the four following patterns:
                     <tt>YYYY</tt>, <tt>YYYY-MM</tt>, <tt>YYYY-MM-DD</tt>, or <tt>YYYY-YYYY</tt>.</p>
               <p>Paragraph about non-W3cDTF values.</p>
               <p>A Date with no refinement will be assumed to be the date of issue (<i>i.e.</i> publication). Date of
                  publication may differ from its creation date; thus it can be helpful to prospective users to include
                  more than one kind of Date element (refinement). However, a single resource should not have more than
                  one instance of each date refinement, with the possible exception of <tt>dcterms:modified</tt>. Where
                  the modification history of a resource is significant, it is appropriate to enter this information in
                  a <xref>Provenance</xref> element, which allows for explanation of modifications in a way that
                     <tt>dcterms:modified</tt> does not.</p>
               <p>‘Available’ as a refinement pertains to Date, not to other aspects of availability.</p>
               <p>Do not use additional terms such as “recorded on” or “donated on” in the element text.</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>available</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date (often a range) that the resource will become or did become available.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>created</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date of creation of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dateAccepted</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date of acceptance of the resource (<i>e.g.</i> of thesis by university department, of article
                        by journal, etc.).</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dateCopyrighted</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date of a statement of copyright.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dateSubmitted</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date of submission of the resource (<i>e.g.</i> thesis, articles, etc.).</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>issued</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date of formal issuance (<i>e.g.</i>, publication) of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>modified</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date on which the resource was changed.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>valid</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Date (often a range) of validity of a resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:W3CDTF</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>W3C Encoding rules for dates and times - a profile based on ISO 8601 <cit>W3CDTF</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that a record have at least one instance of Date (or one of its
                  refinements).</p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that every instance of Date (or one of its refinements) use the
                     <i>dcterms:W3CDTF</i> scheme, or enclose the element value in square brackets if the value does not
                  conform to the encoding scheme (<i>e.g.</i>, if it is supplied by the cataloger, is approximate, or is
                  in some doubt). </p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A typical year of publication:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">1992&lt;/dc:date&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource modified on October 16, 1996:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:modified xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">1996-10-16&lt;/dcterms:modified&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource from approximately 1950:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:date>[circa 1950]&lt;/dc:date&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource for which the date has been supplied by the cataloger from external informaiton:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:issued>[1932]&lt;/dcterms:issued&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Description">
            <definition>An account of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>

               <p>Description may include but is not limited to: an abstract, table of contents, reference to a
                  graphical representation of content, or a free-text summary account of the content. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>Description may also offer an annotation, or a qualitative or evaluative comment about the resource,
                  such as a statement about suitability for a particular application or context.</p>
               <p> Description element is not a "catch-all" category. The Description element should not be confused
                  with Subject. Description contains free-text (prose) statements, while Subject contains subject
                  headings, faceted terms, or specific subject descriptors, <i>e.g.</i>, Library of Congress Subject
                  Headings, or Linguistics and Language Behavior Abstracts thesaurus descriptors. Description should
                  likewise not be used in place of Extent to contain information solely about the length, duration, or
                  size of a work.</p>
               <p>No formatting conventions are defined within the text of Description. Service providers may format the
                  entire Description as a single paragraph, collapsing adjacent white space characters into a single
                  space.</p>
               <p>When there is a URL for a document that describes the resource, use a separate Description element to
                  encode just that URL. A Description that begins with "http:" will be interpreted by service providers
                  as consisting solely of a URL and will be presented as a link in user interfaces. Service providers
                  are not obliged to search other Description text for the occurrence of URLs.</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>abstract</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A summary of the content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>tableOfContents</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A list of subunits of the content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <bp>

               <p>Recommended best practice is that a metadata record should contain at least one Description (or one of
                  its refinements) or Coverage (or one of its refinements) or Subject element. While these are different
                  in purpose and content, they nevertheless give the prospective user some idea of the content of the
                  resource that goes beyond the informative potential of just a title alone. Using all of these elements
                  is encouraged.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A prose description of a resource:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:description&gt;The CALLHOME Japanese corpus of telephone speech consists of 120
   unscripted telephone conversations between native speakers of Japanese. All calls, which lasted
   up to 30 minutes, originated in North America and were placed to locations overseas (typically
   Japan). Most participants called family members or close friends. This corpus contains speech
   data files ONLY, along with the minimal amount of documentation needed to describe the contents
   and format of the speech files and the software packages needed to uncompress the speech data.
   &lt;/dc:description&gt;</eg>
               <p>A contents note for a resource:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:tableOfContents&gt;v. 1: Thesaurus of Khmu dialects in Southeast Asia; v. 2:
   Dictionary of Khmu in China; v. 3: Dictionary of Khmu in Laos; v. 4: Dictionary of Khmu in
   Vietnam; v. 5: Dictionary of Khmu in Thailand&lt;/dcterms:tableOfContents&gt;</eg>
               <p>A reference to an existing on-line description:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:description&gt;http://www.ldc.upenn.edu/Catalog/LDC96S37.html&lt;/dc:description&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Format">
            <definition>The file format, physical medium, or dimensions of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>

               <p>Typically, Format may include the media-type, physical material, and/or dimensions of the resource.
                  Format may be used to determine the software, hardware or other equipment needed to display or operate
                  the resource. Examples of dimensions include size and duration. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>In the case of a physical object, the refinements medium and extent are most applicable. These may
                  respectively contain the physical material of the object (<i>e.g.</i>, parchment; reel-to-reel tape;
                  35 mm slide; NTSC encoded VHS cassette), and the size/duration (<i>e.g.</i> number of pages and
                  dimensions of a book; length of a recording).</p>
               <p>Format (and its refinement 'medium'), which encompasses the notion of physical media categories such
                  as photograph, should not be confused with <xref>Type</xref>, which categorizes the nature or genre of
                  the content of the resource based on the mode in which the user experiences or interacts with the
                  resource, and as such includes terms that describe general categories, functions, or aggregation
                  levels for content.</p>
               <!--<p>OLAC had 5 refinements (cpu, encoding, markup, os, sourcecode) but each of these was used very
						little, if at all  http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf    </p> -->

            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>extent</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The size or duration of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>medium</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The material or physical carrier of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>

            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:IMT</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The Internet media type of the resource <cit>IMT</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>In the case of a digital resource, recommended best practice is to express the Format using a MIME
                  type from the <i>dcterms:IMT</i> scheme. </p>
            </bp>
            <examples>
               <p>For a digitally encoded dictionary:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;text/xml&lt;/dc:format&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:extent&gt;5,237 entries in a 1.2M XML file.&lt;/dcterms:extent&gt;</eg>
               <p>For a digitally recorded text:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;audio/wav&lt;/dc:format&gt;
   &lt;dc:format&gt;Sampling: 1 channel, 22 KHz, 8 bits.&lt;/dc:format&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:extent&gt;Duration: 153 seconds. Size: 3.3M. &lt;/dcterms:extent&gt;</eg>
               <p>For 16mm film with sound track</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:medium&gt;sound, color;  16mm film&lt;/dcterms:medium&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:extent&gt;30 min.&lt;/dcterms:extent&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <!-- Identifier would probably benefit from a more thorough best practice document.  -->
         <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf -->
         <element name="Identifier">
            <definition>An unambiguous reference to the resource within a given context.</definition>
            <comment>

               <p>In the case of a resource that is not electronically encoded, but is housed in a conventional archive,
                  Identifier may be used to give a local shelf or box number, or whatever scheme is used to locate a
                  resource within the collection.</p>
               <p>Identifiers that begin with "http:" will be interpreted by service providers as URLs and be presented
                  as links in user interfaces. Complete relative link paths with the base server so that the link will
                  be valid outside the search system of the host archives.</p>
               <p>Identifier is of particular value in enabling other resources to unambiguously refer to the resource
                  in focus in terms of a specific relationship. See <xref>Relation</xref> for best practice and usage
                  notes in creating relationship links between resources.</p>
               <p>When using the <i>bibliographicCitation</i> refinement, there is no prescription as to a bibliographic
                  style to use in forming the citation. The only requirement is that sufficient bibliographic detail be
                  included to identify the resource unambiguously.</p>
               <p>A unique identifier that has been assigned to a digital resource by the researcher, a research
                  organization or department, or an archives or library for internal reference may continue to be useful
                  in identifying the resource alongside a URI assigned in the context of a digital repository. Such a
                  unique identifier may be significant for continuity of identification for a digital resource
                  throughout its lifecycle, as other resources may have used such an identifier in referencing the
                  object prior to the assignment of the URI later in its lifecycle.</p>
               <p>Do not specify the "oai:" identifier for the resource itself as a value of Identifier, since it is
                  already given in <tt>&lt;identifier&gt;</tt> in the <tt>&lt;header&gt;</tt> of the
                     <tt>&lt;record&gt;</tt>s returned by the OAI protocol.</p>
               <p>Do not use Identifier for a URL intended to direct the searcher to a <xref>Description</xref>,
                  availability or usage or other <xref>Rights</xref>-related information. A URI may be used in each of
                  those elements or refinements to link to such information. Likewise, Identifier should not be used to
                  refer to a general collection site in which the resource is one of many works available.</p>

            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>bibliographicCitation</dt>
                  <dd>

                     <p>A bibliographic reference for the resource. </p>

                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A Uniform Resource Identifier <cit>URI</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>When the value of Identifier is a Uniform Resource Locator (URL), recommended best practice is to
                  specify the <i>dcterms:URI</i> scheme.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A Uniform Resource Locator for retrieval of an electronically encoded resource:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:identifier xsi:type="dcterms:URI"&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/cs.CL/0010033&lt;/dc:identifier&gt;</eg>
               <p>A local identifier for retrieval within a physical collection:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:identifier&gt;Series: A, Box 7&lt;/dc:identifier&gt;</eg>
               <p>The citation for a chapter that was published in a book:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:bibliographicCitation&gt;In Joel Sherzer and Greg Urban (eds.), Native South
American discourse, 237-306. Berlin: Mouton. &lt;dcterms:bibliographicCitation&gt;</eg>

            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Language">
            <definition>A language of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Language is used for a language the resource is in, as opposed to the language it describes (see
                     <xref>Subject</xref>). It is related to the audience for the work in that it identifies a language
                  that the creator of the resource assumes that its eventual user will understand. When a resource is in
                  more than one language, use a separate Language element for each language.</p>
               <p>For a work of literature or other monolingual document aimed at the speakers of a particular language,
                  use Language to identify that language. For a sound recording, use Language for the language being
                  spoken in the recording. For a grammatical description, for instance, use Language for the language
                  the grammar is written in; use <xref>Subject</xref> with the ISO639-3 scheme (hereafter referred to as
                  "Subject.language") to specify the language whose grammar is being described. For an annotated text,
                  use Language for the language in which the annotations are made; use Subject.language for the language
                  of the base text that is being annotated. For a dictionary, use Language for the language in which the
                  definitions are written; use Subject.language for the language whose words are being defined. A
                  bilingual dictionary may have both languages identified in both kinds of elements.</p>
               <p>For scholarly works, and works intended for a wider audience of communication, Language will usually
                  be a major language (English, French, Chinese, etc.). For vernacular works in a minority language,
                  Language should contain the code for the minority language, and an appropriate OLAC Linguistic Type
                  (see <xref>Type</xref>) should be selected.</p>
               <p>Service providers should use the <i>code</i> attribute to support searches by language, and may use
                  the element content in searches by keyword. They also may supply the default language name in keyword
                  searching when the element content is missing.</p>
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>olac:ISO639-3</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The ISO 639-3 set of three-letter identifiers for the identification of human languages. See
                           <cit>OLAC-Language</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that every record contain at least one Language element. For a resource
                  that does not include language content, include a Language element containing the code <tt>zxx</tt>
                  for "No linguistic content."</p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>olac:ISO639-3</i> scheme to identify the Language
                  precisely. Specify the language in the <i>olac:code</i> attribute while leaving the element content
                  empty. Use the element content only when the controlled vocabulary does not offer an appropriate code,
                  or when further specification is needed, such as to name a specific dialect or to give an alternate
                  name that differs from the reference name given by the controlled vocabulary.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A resource in English about the Sikaiana language:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="eng"/&gt; 
   &lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="sky"/&gt;</eg>
               <p>A Yemba-French dictionary, where the alternate name Dschang is preferred.</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="fra"/&gt;
   &lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="ybb"&gt;Dschang&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
               <p>The <i>American Heritage Dictionary</i>, which is both in and about American English:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="eng"/&gt;
   &lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="eng"/&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:spatial&gt;United States&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource in the Saracatsan dialect of modern Greek</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="ell"&gt;Saracatsan dialect&lt;/dc:language&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Publisher">
            <definition>An entity responsible for making the resource available.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Examples of a Publisher include a person, an organization, or a service. Typically, the name of a
                  Publisher should be used to indicate the entity. <cit>DCMT</cit> The Publisher is generally the
                  business, organization, or sometimes individual who takes responsibility (and provides financial and
                  production resources) for putting the resource into a form suitable for making it publicly available,
                  whether in multiple hard copies (printing, pressing of a disc, etc), by broadcasting (radio,
                  television, webcast), or posting to a public website. A published resource may be offered for sale or
                  freely, but in either case, it is released for public use. </p>
               <p>Many materials that are placed in archival repositories are not formally published in that they have
                  not undergone an editorial, composition and production process, involving review, modification, and
                  packaging by persons other than the original creator(s). While such items may be offered publicly,
                  they are not considered "published" in a formal sense and their metadata should not ordinarily specify
                  a publisher.</p>
               <p>For an entity that has funded the creation or development of the resource in some way, but has not
                  otherwise participated in its development through editing, composition, production, printing,
                  marketing, posting, etc., use the <xref>Contributor</xref> element specifying the <cit>OLAC-Role</cit>
                  code="sponsor".</p>
               <p>Be consistent with corporate name forms. Names that include a primary unit and subsidiary unit should
                  be ordered with the primary unit given first. Location should generally be omitted from the name
                  unless location is an integral part of the proper name of the unit.</p>
            </comment>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is to identify a Publisher by means of a name in a form that is ready for
                  sorting within an index. For the names of persons, this means that the name should be given with the
                  surname first (<i>i.e.</i>, an "inverted" order for most Western name forms). For the names of
                  organizations, this means that any initial article should be omitted.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A typical publisher:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:publisher&gt;Oxford University Press&lt;/dc:publisher&gt;</eg>
               <p>The URL for a publisher:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:publisher xsi:type="dcterms:URI"&gt;http://www.oup.com&lt;/dc:publisher&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Relation">
            <definition>A related resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>This element is used to document relationships between resources, for instance, part-whole
                  relationships, version relationships, dependency relationships, and so on</p>
               <p>When the present resource is a derived work, the source resource is typically indicated by
                     <xref>Source</xref>. However, there are two cases in which refinements of Relation are used for
                  derived works. The <i>isVersionOf</i> refinement is used when the present resource is a new version or
                  edition with added intellectual content that has been developed by the same creators. When the new
                  version is nothing more than a rendition in a new format, then the <i>isForrmatOf</i> refinement is
                  used. </p>
               <p>Metadata that is migrated from the records of a collector or depositor or an earlier repository system
                  might make use of an identifier assigned at that earlier stage in specifying relationship information.
                  Relationships metadata using such internal identifiers in their referencing will be made more useful
                  if they are updated to the OAI identifier at such a time as the metadata for the related resource is
                  also migrated or uploaded to the OAI compliant system.</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>conformsTo</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A reference to an established standard to which the resource conforms.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>hasFormat</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource pre-existed the referenced resource, which is essentially the same
                        intellectual content presented in another format.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>hasPart</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource includes the referenced resource either physically or logically.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>hasVersion</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource has a version, edition, or adaptation, namely, the referenced
                     resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>isFormatOf</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource is the same intellectual content of the referenced resource, but
                        presented in another format.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>isPartOf</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource is a physical or logical part of the referenced resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>isReferencedBy</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource is referenced, cited, or otherwise pointed to by the referenced
                     resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>isReplacedBy</dt>
                  <dd/>
                  <dt>isRequiredBy</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource is required by the referenced resource, either physically or
                     logically.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>isVersionOf</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource is a version, edition, or adaptation of the referenced resource. Changes
                        in version imply substantive changes in content rather than differences in format.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>references</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource references, cites, or otherwise points to the referenced resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>replaces</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource supplants, displaces, or supersedes the referenced resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>requires</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The described resource requires the referenced resource to support its function, delivery, or
                        coherence of content.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A Uniform Resource Identifier <cit>URI</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>When the related resource is also held in a participating archive, recommended best practice is to
                  identify the related resource by means of its OAI identifier. A Relation that begins with "oai:" will
                  typically be presented by service providers as an active link that retrieves the metadata for that
                  resource.</p>
               <p>If the related resource is not cataloged in the system of a participating archive, recommended best
                  practice is to identify the related resource through a standard unique identifier. If the related
                  resource is available online, specify the <i>dcterms:URI</i> scheme and give a stable Uniform Resource
                  Locator (URL).</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A link to a required font:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:requires&gt;oai:sil:software/ipafont&lt;/dcterms:requires&gt;</eg>
               <p>Links to the component pieces of a collected work:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding126&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding127&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding128&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding129&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding130&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;</eg>
               <p>Link to a specification of a schema to which the resource conforms:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:conformsTo xsi:type="dcterms:URI"&gt;http://someschemadef&lt;/dcterms:conformsTo&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
            <todo>
               <p>Do we need a scheme for olac:OAI to represent an OLAC OAI identifier? Or should we just use
                  dcterms:URI and match on initial "oai:"?</p>
            </todo>
         </element>
         <element name="Rights">
            <definition>Information about rights held in and over the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p> Typically, a Rights element will contain a rights management statement for the resource, or reference
                  a service providing such information. Rights information often encompasses Intellectual Property
                  Rights (IPR), Copyright, and various Property Rights. If the Rights element is absent, no assumptions
                  can be made about the status of these and other rights with respect to the resource.
                  <cit>Copyright</cit></p>
               <p>A rights management statement that contains a license or directs a potential user to a license
                  statement that specifies conditions and granted permissions should use the <i>dcterms:license</i>
                  refinement. The <i>dcterms:accessRights</i> refinement should be used to document conditions under
                  which access to the resource is granted. In either case, a statement may be included directly within
                  the metadata, or a URI reference to the statement or a service may be given. Examples of license
                  statements can be found at Creative Commons <cit>CC</cit>.</p>
               <p>Use <xref>Rights Holder</xref> to specify a person or corporate body (organization, legally
                  constituted entity representing a group or community), rather than Rights.</p>
               <p>Copyright is inherent in primary linguistic and cultural research materials, such as stories,
                  descriptions, songs or art work, which researchers collect in the course of their work. The rights, in
                  most cases, belong to the creator—not the researcher or his organization or sponsor—or, in some cases,
                  to the language community (if it may be constituted as a legal entity). Intellectual property law as
                  it applies to personal or community cultural property is beyond the scope of these notes. However,
                  documenting the creators of such works, the conditions under which they came into the hands of the
                  researcher, and any known conditions on use (generally non-commercial use) are critical aspects of
                  archiving. To publish or otherwise distribute such works should have the approval of the owner. Only
                  with information about the origins and conditions of collecting can the holding repository or
                  interested researchers make use of such resources in ways that respect the rights and sensibilities of
                  those whose languages and communities are documented.</p>
               <p>A fundamental right of a creator is the right to be associated with his or her creation (whether
                  verbal, textual, visual, etc.), regardless of the retention or subsequent assignment of additional
                  rights (to display, distribute copies, modify). Upholding this right must be balanced with a person's
                  right to privacy with regard to identifying information (including the use of photographs).
                  Demographic data about a creator, contributor or research participant, along with identifying
                  information, is often included in research data. Identifying information may be removed prior to
                  deposit, or as a condition of release, or a Rights element may document a statement of permission to
                  use a resource or parts of a resource in a particular way that may otherwise have been an infringement
                  of privacy.</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>accessRights</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Information about who can access the resource or an indication of its security status.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>license</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A legal document giving official permission to do something with the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>

            <todo>
               <p>Mention Creative Commons in the usage notes and give an example of a CC license statement.</p>
            </todo>
         </element>
         <element name="Source">
            <definition>The resource from which the described resource is derived.</definition>
            <comment>
               <!-- Move to <bp><p>? -->
               <p>The present resource may be derived from the Source resource in whole or in part. <cit>DCMT</cit>
               </p>
               <p> In the legal parlance of intellectual property rights, a "derivative work" is one that is based on
                  one or more preexisting works. This includes cases in which a work may be recast, transformed, or
                  adapted in any way, such as by translation, abridgement, dramatization, recording, transcription, or
                  digital encoding. A work consisting of editorial revisions, annotations, elaborations, or other
                  modifications, which, as a whole, represent an original work of authorship is also a derivative work
                     <cit>Copyright</cit>.</p>
               <p>This legal definition elucidates the sense of "derived" that is intended in the Dublin Core definition
                  of Source. Note, however, that this overlaps with <xref>Relation</xref>, since the <i>isFormatOf</i>
                  and <i>isVersionOf</i> refinements both refer to derivative works in the technical sense.</p>
               <p>Use Source (as opposed to one of the above two Relation refinements) in cases when the present
                  resource has a substantially different <xref>Type</xref> or <xref>Creator</xref> or <xref>Title</xref>
                  than the Source resource. When the difference from the original work is only a difference of
                     <xref>Date</xref> or <xref>Format</xref> or <xref>Publisher</xref> or <xref>Identifier</xref> or
                  edition, then use Relation (or the appropriate refinement) to encode the relationship to the original
                  work.</p>
            </comment>

            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A Uniform Resource Identifier <cit>URI</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is as for the Relation element above. </p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>Source for a digital encoding of a manuscript in a participating archive:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:source&gt;oai:somearchive:holding1023&lt;/dc:source&gt;</eg>
               <p>Source for data extracted from a published source:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:source&gt;Kwara'ae flora vocabulary extracted from Guide to the Forests of the
   British Solomon Islands, by T. C. Whitmore. Oxford University Press, 1966.&lt;/dc:source&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Subject">
            <definition>The topic of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Typically, a Subject will be expressed as keywords, key phrases or classification codes that describe
                  a topic of the resource. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>To describe the spatial or temporal topic of the resource, use the <xref>Coverage</xref> element.</p>
               <p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_IMLS.pdf --> The Subject element should not be confused with Description.
                  Subject contains subject headings, while Description contains free-text descriptions.</p>
               <p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_KO.pdf -->Avoid mapping the DC Subject element to a variety of
                  cataloger-defined natural vocabularies such as 'topic', 'category', and 'keyword.'</p>
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>olac:ISO639-3</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The ISO 639-3 set of three-letter identifiers for the identification of human languages. See
                           <xref>Language</xref> for a complete discussion (with examples) of using this scheme.</p>
                     <!-- Move to a <bp><p>? -->
                     <p>Service providers should use the <i>code</i> attribute to support searches by language, and may
                        use the element content in searches by keyword. They also may supply the default language name
                        in keyword searching when the element content is missing.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>olac:linguistic-field</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The OLAC vocabulary for describing the content of a resource as relevant to a particular
                        subfield of linguistic science <cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Field</cit>. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that a metadata record should contain at least one Description (or one of
                  its refinements) or Coverage (or one of its refinements) or Subject element. While these are different
                  in purpose and content, they nevertheless give the prospective user some idea of the content of the
                  resource that goes beyond the informative potential of just a title alone. Using all of these elements
                  is encouraged.</p>

               <p>When the subject is a human language, recommended best practice is to use the <i>olac:ISO639-3</i>
                  scheme to identify it precisely. Specify the language in the <i>olac:code</i> attribute while leaving
                  the element content empty. Use the element content only when the controlled vocabulary does not offer
                  an appropriate code, or when further specification is needed, such as to name a specific dialect or to
                  give an alternate name that differs from the reference name given by the controlled vocabulary. </p>
               <p>When the subject matter falls within the field of linguistics, recommended best practice is to use the
                     <i>olac:linguistic-field</i> scheme to identify the subfield.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A Library of Congress subject heading:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="dcterms:LCSH"&gt;African languages&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource about a language for which the controlled vocabulary does not yet provide a code:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language"&gt;Medieval Greek&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource on multilingual education in Uganda involving national, regional and local languages.</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:subject&gt;Multilingual education&lt;/dc:subject&gt;
   &lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="swh"/&gt;
   &lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="eng"/&gt;
   &lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="xog"/&gt;
   ...
   &lt;dcterms:spacial xsi:type="dcterms:ISO3166"&gt;UG&lt;/dcterms:spacial&gt;</eg>
               
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Title">
            <definition>A name given to the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Typically, a Title will be a name by which the resource is formally known. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>A translation of the title can be supplied in a <i>dcterms:alternative</i> element. Use the
                     <i>xml:lang</i> attribute to identify the language of the metadata content using an identifier from
                     <cit>ISO639-3</cit>.</p>
               <p>The Title can be a name given to a work to identify it if a formal title is not used, such as for a
                  data set or collection of texts. A formal title (for catalogers, the title as found on a primary
                  source of information), is generally expected to be in the language in which the work is written or
                  recorded. If the title is in a language different from the language identified in a
                  <xref>Language</xref> element, use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute to specify the language in which the
                  Title is actually given. {This guidance should then mean that the second example below should not
                  employ the xsi:type with olac:code (or a lang attribute) in the main title, but should only use it in
                  the alternate}</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>alternative</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>Any form of the title used as a substitute or alternative to the formal title of the resource.
                        Comment: This qualifier can include Title abbreviations as well as translations. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that every record must have an instance of the Title element. When the
                  resource does not have an inherent title, the cataloger should supply a descriptive title and enclose
                  it in square brackets.</p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that only one instance of the unqualified
                  Title element, namely, for the original title.
                  All others (<i>e.g.</i> translations) should be specified as the Alternative
               refinement.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>A typical title:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;A Dictionary of the Nggela Language&lt;/dc:title&gt;</eg>
               <p>A vernacular title with translation:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="llu"&gt;Na tala 'uria na idulaa diana&lt;/dc:title&gt; 
   &lt;dcterms:alternative xml:lang="eng" &gt;The road to good reading&lt;/dcterms:alternative&gt;</eg>
               <p>A parallel title, as typically employed for a diglot work:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;Xunivaun jau yohipahonni = Cuentos de nuestros antepasados&lt;/dc:title&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <!-- Type:   i Exhibited perhaps the most different archivespecific
      		interpretations of its use
      		i Evidence of different vocabularies for type used
      		by numerous archives
      		i When coded, the codes were generally applied
      		correctly
      		i Abused by some poor mappings -->
         <!-- iMore thorough best practice guidelines for:
      		– Description
      		– Identifier
      		– Rights
      		– Subject qualifiers and extensions (dealing with
      		overlap, use of multiple schemes)
      		– Type and its extensions
      		iThe definitions and controlled vocabularies
      		have to be in order FIRST -->
         <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf -->
         <element name="Type">
            <definition>The nature or genre of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p> Type includes terms describing general categories, functions, genres, or aggregation levels for
                  content. The DCMIType vocabulary specifies a controlled vocabulary to be used to with Type. These
                  relate to the intended use or mode of perception by a user, <i>e.g.</i>, whether it is read (as text),
                  viewed (as image), heard, etc. Thus, a computer image file of a text (such as a scanned document) is
                  type 'text', not type 'image', because the common use involves reading text. To describe the physical
                  or digital manifestation of the resource, use the <xref>Format</xref> element. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p/>
               <p>Linguistic Type schema should only be used in a Type element if a resource represents one of the
                  structural types in the range set. The element may be repeated if a resource represents more than one
                  linguistic type. So, for example, a primary text accompanied by a lexicon of vocabulary items would be
                  described as both a primary text and a lexicon. </p>
               <!-- <p>In the case of a primary text
                  (or collection of such texts), adequate description of a linguistic resource will require that 
                  Linguistic Type be specified in conjunction with the Discourse Type extension of the Type element, or the Linguistic
                  extension of the Subject element. For example, a narrative text might be described as both a
                  primary text (OLAC Linguistic Type) and a narrative (OLAC Discourse Type). </p> -->
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:DCMIType</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>A list of types used to categorize the nature or genre of the content of the resource.
                           <cit>DCMI-Type</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>olac:linguistic-type</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The nature or genre of the content of the resource from a linguistic standpoint
                           <cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Type</cit>. For a resource that is information in or about a language,
                        use this scheme to identify what kind of information it is from a linguistic standpoint.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>olac:discourse-type</dt>
                  <!-- Omitted at this level of usage guidance? -->
                  <dd>
                     <p/>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that every record should contain at least one Type element that uses the
                     <i>dcterms:DCMIType</i> scheme.</p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that every record should contain at least one Type element that uses the
                     <i>olac:linguistic-type</i> scheme to identify its linguistic data type. When no particular data
                  type is relevant, specify the <tt>not_applicable</tt> value.</p>
            </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>The resource is a video recording, stored as a MPEG:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage&lt;/cd:type&gt;
    &lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;image/mpeg&lt;/dc:format&gt;</eg>
               <p>The resource is a video recording of a story teller relating a traditional story, recorded on Super-8 film::</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType"&gt;MovingImage&lt;/cd:type&gt;
   &lt;dc:type xsi:type="olac:linguistic-type" olac:code="primary_text"/&gt;
   &lt;dc:medium&gt;Super 8mm film&lt;/dc:medium&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
            <todo>
               <p>The following is leftover from 2002; do we still want it? For a resource that is a software tool,
                  Type.linguistic identifies what kind of information it processes. Service providers may use this
                  information to match data files with software tools that might be applied to them.</p>
            </todo>
         </element>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>Other elements</heading>
         <p>The following subsections describe other elements that have been defined by
            the Dublin Core Metadata Initiative <cit>DCMT</cit>. They are defined within the
            <url>http://purl.org/dc/terms/</url> namespace for which the prefix <tt>dcterms:</tt> is
         used in the examples.</p>
         <element name="Provenance">
            <definition>A statement of any changes in ownership and custody of the resource since its creation that are
               significant for its authenticity, integrity and interpretation.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>The Provenance element is a dcterms element, one of two element-level terms (the other is
                  <xref>RightsHolder</xref>) not specified in the original core set of Dublin Core elements, but
                  nonetheless an element and not a refinement of some other element. Its correct specification is with
                  the dcterms namespace as shown in the example.</p>
               <p>Provenance should be distinguished in usage from <xref>Description</xref>. Provenance metadata should
                  be used to track and/or convey important information regarding the custody and/or management of the
                  resource throughout its history, which has a bearing upon interpretation of the informational content
                  of the resource, or the upon its artifactual integrity and authenticity.{A WORK IN PROGRESS}</p>
            </comment>
            <examples>
               <p>A group of texts and recordings constituting a small collection that has undergone some reorganization
                  by a subsequent handler since original creation:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="researcher"&gt;Gardner, Richard&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;
                  &lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="compiler"&gt;Anderson, Judi Lynn&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;
                  &lt;dc:created&gt;1962-1976&lt;/dc:created&gt;
                  &lt;dc:available&gt;2007&lt;/dc:available&gt;
                  &lt;dc:description&gt;Collection of 23 texts, with original recordings of 17 of the texts. Texts were originally 
                  transcribed using a variety of othographic conventions, some with interlinear analytical transcriptions,
                  some also with Spanish free translations.&lt;/dc:description&gt;
                  &lt;dcterms:provenance&gt;Collection of texts recorded by Gardner, transcribed with the assistance of 
                  a number of local residents. Body of materials were transferred to branch custody in 1980s, 
                  subsequently organized, collated and annotated by J.L. Anderson, a researcher in a closely 
                  related Chinantec language. Annotations particularly relate to changes in orthographic and tone
                  marking conventions over the years of collection and as compared to current practices.&lt;/dcterms:provenance&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Rights Holder">
            <definition>A person or organization owning or managing rights over the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Use the URI or name of the Rights Holder to indicate the entity.</p>
            </comment>
         </element>
         
      </section>
      
   </body>
   <references>
      <ref abbrev="AACR2r">Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules, 2nd ed., 2002 revision. Ottawa and Chicago:
      Canadian Library Association and American Library Association, 2002-.</ref>
      
      <ref abbrev="Copyright">Section 101, Definitions, Copyright Law of the United States of America and Related Laws
         Contained in Title 17 of the United States Code.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.loc.gov/copyright/title17/92chap1.html#101</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="CC">Creative Commons Licenses.<br/>&lt;<url>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMT">Dublin Core Metadata Terms.
         <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMI-Box">DCMI Box Encoding Scheme: specification of the spatial limits of a place, and methods for encoding this in a text string.
         <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-box/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMI-Period">DCMI Period Encoding Scheme: specification of the limits of a time interval, and methods for encoding this in a text string.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-period/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMI-Point">DCMI Point Encoding Scheme: a point location in space, and methods for encoding this in a text string. <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-point/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMI-Type">DCMI Type Vocabulary.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-type-vocabulary/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="IMT">MIME Media Types.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/</url>&gt;</ref>
      
      <ref abbrev="ISO3166">ISO 3166: Codes for the representation of names of countries. 
         <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.iso.org/iso/country_codes/iso_3166_code_lists.htm</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="ISO639-3">ISO 639: Codes for the representation of names of languages - Part 3: Alpha-3 code for
         comprehensive coverage of languages.<br/> &lt;<url>http://www.sil.org/iso639-3/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="URI">Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI): Generic Syntax.
         <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2396.txt</url>&gt;</ref>

     <ref abbrev="OLAC-BP">Best Practice Recommendations for Language Resource
            Description.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/bpr.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Linguistic-Field">OLAC Linguistic Subject
            Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/field.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Linguistic-Type">OLAC Linguistic Data Type
            Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/type.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Metadata">OLAC
         Metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Language">OLAC Language
         Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/language.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Role">OLAC Role
         Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/role.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="TGN">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic
            Names.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabulary/tgn/index.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Extensions">Recommended metadata extensions.
         <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/olac-extensions.html</url>&gt;</ref>
      
      <ref abbrev="W3CDTF">Date and Time Formats, W3C
         Note.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-datetime</url>&gt;</ref>

   </references>
</OLAC_doc>
