<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../OLAC_doc.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "../OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc>
   <header>
      <status type="recommendation" code="proposed"/>
      <title>OLAC Language Extension</title>
      <baseName>language</baseName>
      <issued>20071114</issued>
      <previousIssued>20031213</previousIssued>

      <abstract>
         <p> This document specifies the metadata extension used by OLAC to uniquely
            identify languages. It uses the three-letter identifiers of ISO 639-3 as its
            controlled vocabulary. </p>
      </abstract>
      <editors>Gary Simons, SIL International
         (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>)<br/>Steven Bird, University of Melbourne
         and University of Pennsylvania (<url>mailto:sb@csse.unimelb.edu.au</url>)</editors>
      <copyright>2007 Gary Simons (SIL International) and Steven Bird (University of
         Melbourne and University of Pennsylvania)</copyright>

      <changes>
         <p>A major rework of the original 2003 recommendation. That recommendation was
            based on an assembly of identifiers from multiple sources: ISO 639-1, the SIL
            language identifiers (prefixed by "x-sil-"), and the Linguist List identifiers
            (prefixed by "x-ll-"). Now with the release of ISO 639-3, which weaves
            together the codes from these sources into a single coherent code set, the
            OLAC recommendation is simplified to use that standard.</p>
      </changes>
   </header>
   <body>
      <section>
         <heading>Introduction</heading>
         <p>Identifying the languages involved is an important dimension of language
            resource description. However, using the character-string representation of
            language names as identifiers is problematic for several reasons: </p>
         <ul>
            <li>
               <p>Different languages (in different parts of the world) may have the same
                  name.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>The same language may have different names in different languages.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>The same language may have different names in the various countries where it is
                  spoken.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Within the same country, the preferred name for a language may change
                  over time.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>In the early history of discovering languages (before their names were
                  standardized), different people referred to the same language by
                  different names.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>For languages having non-Roman orthographies, the language name may have
                  several possible romanizations.</p>
            </li>
         </ul>
         <p>These facts taken together mean that identifying languages by name
            will not work. Rather, what is needed is a standard based on unique
            identifiers that do not change, combined with accessible documentation that
            clarifies the particular speech variety denoted by each identifier. For a
            deeper discussion of these issues see <cit>CS2000</cit> and
            <cit>Simons2000</cit>.</p>
         <p>The information technology community has a well-established standard for
            language identification, namely, ISO 639.
            Part 1 of the standard specifies two-letter codes for identifying about 160 of
            the world's major languages; part 2 specifies three-letter codes for
            identifying about 380 languages <cit>ISO639-2</cit>. These code sets in turn form the core of the
            standard followed by the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF), namely, RFC
            3066 <cit>RFC3066</cit>. This is the standard used for language identification
            in the <tt>xml:lang</tt> attribute of XML <cit>XML-lang</cit>.  The Dublin Core Metadata Initiative <cit>DCMT</cit> 
            defines encoding schemes <i>dcterms:ISO639-2</i> and <i>dcterms:RFC3066</i> 
            for use in its Language element.</p>
         <p>The above standards fall short of the coverage required by the language
            archiving community since they focus on the major languages of the world that
            are most frequently represented in the total body of the world's literature. A
            new part 3 of the standard <cit>ISO639-3</cit>, adopted in 2007, has the purpose of defining
            three-letter identifiers for all known human languages. With over 7,500 codes,
            it attempts to provide a comprehensive
            enumeration of languages, including living,
            extinct, ancient, and constructed languages, whether major or minor. This is
            the standard that forms the
            basis for the OLAC recommendation on language identification in language
            resource description.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>The ISO639-3 extension</heading>
         <p>The complete vocabulary of language identifiers recommended for use by OLAC consists of all active
            codes from ISO 639-3 as documented at its official web site
            <cit>ISO639-3</cit>. This includes both individual language identifiers and
            macrolanguage identifiers <cit>ISO639-Macro</cit>. At any time the valid code
            set is the complete set of codes (both active and retired) that is
            downloadable from <cit>ISO639-3</cit>; the use of retired codes is deprecated,
         but not disallowed.</p>
         <p>Following the extension mechanism defined in <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>, a
            language identifier is expressed as the value of the <tt>olac:code</tt>
            attribute and the extension <tt>olac:ISO639-3</tt> is named in the
            <tt>xsi:type</tt> attribute. A language
            identifier may be used with the <tt>&lt;dc:language&gt;</tt> element
            to identify a language that a resource is written or spoken in. Similarly, a
            language identifier may be used with the <tt>&lt;dc:subject&gt;</tt>
            element to identify a language that a resource is about. In both cases, free
            text in the element content may be used to identify the specific variety of
            the language. For instance, the following indicates that a resource is written
            in Japanese:</p>
         <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="jpn"/&gt;</eg>
         <p>While the following indicates that a resource is sbout the Lau language of
            Solomon Islands, and specifically, the Suafa dialect:</p>
         <eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="llu"&gt;Suafa dialect&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
         <p>The formal definition of the vocabulary is in the following XML schema which
            conforms to the conventions for an OLAC metadata extension as defined in
               <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>:</p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/olac-ISO639-3.xsd</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>
         <p>That schema in turn includes another schema that contains only the simple type
            that enumerates all the recognized code values, namely, </p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/ISO639-3.xsd</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>
         <p>The latter schema provides a complete list of all language identifiers
            recognized by OLAC. Each enumerated value provides both a code (in the
               <tt>value</tt> attribute) and an associated language name (in the
            <tt>&lt;annotation&gt;</tt> element) that can be used for display purposes.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>Looking up the language for a code</heading>
         <p>Given a particular three-letter code, the ISO 639-3 web site provides a means of
            looking up documentation for what the code represents. The three letters are
            appended to the documentation page URL as the value of the <i>id</i>
            parameter, as in:</p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.sil.org/iso639-3/documentation.asp?id=abc</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>
         <p>In addition to the basic information available on this page, 
            more detailed information is available through a link to the corresponding
            page on the Ethnologue web site <cit>Ethnologue</cit> for a living or recently
         extinct language, or on the Linguist List website for an ancient
            <cit>LL-Ancient</cit> or constructed <cit>LL-Constructed</cit>
            language.</p>
      </section>
      
      <section>
         <heading>Looking up the code for a language</heading>
         <p>The
            easiest way to find the code for a living or recently extinct language is to
            type the name of a language or dialect or region into
            the Ethnologue's site search form at:</p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.ethnologue.com/site_search.asp</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>
         <p>When you know the country the language is spoken in, another approach is to
            use the country index to find a listing of all the languages in that
            particular country and then to browse the list:</p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.ethnologue.com/country_index.asp</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>
         <p>Linguist List offers a language search page based on name and country
            information downloaded from <cit>Ethnologue-Codes</cit> plus similar
            information they have compiled regarding ancient and constructed languages:</p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.linguistlist.org/forms/langs/find-a-language-or-family.html</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>
       
         <p>See <cit>ISO639-3-Changes</cit> for a description of the process by which
            changes are made to the international standard. Follow this process if you believe that
            something is missing or in error. Note
            that the standard reserves codes <tt>qaa</tt>  through <tt>qtz</tt> for local
            use. That is, those codes will
            never be assigned as language identifiers. Thus, when
            users feel that a needed code is missing from the code set, they may use
             a local use code in their own database as a temporary measure until the outcome
            of a change request is known. Note, however, that local use codes are
            undefined for information interchange and should not be submitted to the OLAC
            harvester.</p>
      </section>

   </body>
   <references>
      <ref abbrev="DCMT">DCMI Metadata
            Terms.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2006/12/18/dcmi-terms/</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Metadata">OLAC Metadata.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="RFC3066">Tags for the Identification of Languages.
         <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3066.txt</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="ISO639-2">Codes for the Representation of Names of Languages-Part 2:
         Alpha-3
            Code.<br/>&lt;<url>http://lcweb.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/langhome.html</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="ISO639-3">Codes for the Representation of Names of Languages-Part 3:
         Alpha-3 code for comprehensive coverage of
            languages.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.sil.org/iso639-3/</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="ISO639-Macro">"Macrolanguages," in Scope of Denotation for Language
            Identifiers.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.sil.org/iso639-3/scope.asp#M</url>&gt;</ref>



      <ref abbrev="Simons2000">Simons, Gary. 2000. Language identification in metadata
         descriptions of language archive holdings. Proceedings of Workshop on Web-Based
         Language Documentation and Description, 12-15 December 2000, Philadelphia, USA.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.ldc.upenn.edu/exploration/expl2000/papers/simons/simons.htm</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="CS2000">Constable, Peter, and Gary Simons. 2000. Language
         identification and IT: Addressing problems of linguistic diversity on a global
         scale. SIL Electronic Working Papers, 2000-001. Dallas: SIL
            International.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.sil.org/silewp/2000/001/SILEWP2000-001.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="Ethnologue">Ethnologue: Languages of the
            World.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.ethnologue.com/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="Ethnologue-Codes">Three-letter Codes for Identifying
            Languages.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.ethnologue.com/codes/</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="ISO639-3-Changes">ISO 639-3 Change Management.
          <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.sil.org/iso639-3/changes.asp</url>&gt;</ref>
      
      <ref abbrev="XML-lang">Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Fourth Edition), W3C
         Recommendation 16 August 2006. Section 2.12, Language
            Identification.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml#sec-lang-tag</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="LL-Ancient">Linguist List Codes for Ancient and Extinct
            Languages.<br/>&lt;<url>http://cf.linguistlist.org/cfdocs/new-website/LL-WorkingDirs/forms/langs/GetListOfAncientLgs.cfm?RequestTimeout=200</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="LL-Constructed">Linguist List Codes for Constructed
            Languages.<br/>&lt;<url>http://cf.linguistlist.org/cfdocs/new-website/LL-WorkingDirs/forms/langs/GetListOfConstructedLgs.cfm?RequestTimeout=200</url>&gt;</ref>
   </references>
</OLAC_doc>
