<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../OLAC_doc.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "../OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc>
   <header>
       <status code="adopted" type="recommendation"/>
      <!-- Promoted to Candidate on 2008-07-16 -->
      <!-- Promoted to Adopted on 2008-12-19 -->
      <title>Recommended metadata extensions</title>
      <baseName>olac-extensions</baseName>
      <issued>20080222</issued>
      <previousIssued>20021130</previousIssued>
      <abstract>
         <p>This document lists all the metadata extensions that are recommended by the
            Open Language Archives Community for use in describing language resources.
            </p>
      </abstract>
      <editors>Gary Simons, SIL International and Graduate Institute of Applied
         Linguistics (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>) <br/>Steven Bird, University
         of Melbourne and University of Pennsylvania
         (<url>mailto:sb@csse.unimelb.edu.au</url>)</editors>
      <copyright>2008 Gary Simons (SIL International and Graduate Institute of Applied
         Linguistics) and Steven Bird (University of Melbourne and University of
         Pennsylvania)</copyright>
      <changes><p>Minor changes to bring the extension descriptions and the references up
         to date for OLAC metadata version 1.1.</p></changes>
   </header>
   <body>
      <section>
         <heading>Introduction</heading>
         <p>The OLAC metadata standard <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit> follows the generic
            resource description standard known as "Qualified Dublin Core" <cit>DCQ</cit>.
            In order to meet the specific needs of the language resources community, the
            OLAC metadata standard incorporates an extension mechanism that makes it
            possible to describe language resources with greater precision. The mechanism
            uses the <tt>xsi:type</tt> attribute to override the basic definition of a
            Dublin Core metadata element with a definition that has a more precise
            semantics. For instance, the following subject description,</p>
         <eg>&lt;dc:subject&gt;Dschang language&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
         <p>can be formally identified as pertaining to a language and as relating to the
            specific language identified by the ISO 639-3 code <tt>ybb</tt>
            by employing an OLAC extension: as follows:</p>
         <eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language" olac:code="ybb"/&gt;</eg>
         <p>Details on how the extension mechanism works may be found in the last two
            sections of <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>.</p>
         <p>Any party may develop a metadata extension and use it in OLAC metadata
            records. When an extension is proven to work and is judged to have wide
            relevance across the language resources community, then it may be put forward
            to the community as a recommended best practice. If, after following the
            process described in <cit>OLAC-Process</cit>, the community reaches consensus
            that the extension should indeed be used where applicable by all OLAC member
            archives, then the extension achieves the status of an OLAC Recommendation.</p>
         <p>This document provides the complete list of all extensions that have been
            adopted as OLAC Recommendations. Each extension is described in terms of a
            title and the following six descriptors:</p>
         <dl style="list">
            <dt>Name</dt>
            <dd>
               <p>The symbolic name that is used as the value of the <tt>xsi:type</tt>
                  attribute to indicate that the extension is being used in a metadata
                  element.</p>
            </dd>
            <dt>Date</dt>
            <dd>
               <p>The latest revision date of the extension or its controlled
               vocabulary.</p>
            </dd>
            <dt>Applies to</dt>
            <dd>
               <p>The Dublin Core elements with which the extension may be used.</p>
            </dd>
            <dt>Description</dt>
            <dd>
               <p>A summary description of what the extension is used for.</p>
            </dd>
            <dt>Documentation</dt>
            <dd>
               <p>A link to a complete document that defines and exemplifies the
                  extension. If the extension involves a controlled vocabulary, the
                  document should also enumerate and define the terms of the
               vocabulary.</p>
            </dd>
            <dt>Schema</dt>
            <dd><p>A link to the XML schema that formally defines the extension.</p></dd>
         </dl>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>Recommended extensions</heading>
         <p>The Open Language Archives Community recommends that all participating data
            providers use the following metadata extensions for describing language
            resources whenever they are applicable: </p>
         <extensions>

            <extension name="discourse-type" ns="olac"
               href="../OLAC/1.1/olac-discourse-type.xsd"/>
            <extension name="language" ns="olac" href="../OLAC/1.1/olac-language.xsd"/>
            <extension name="linguistic-field" ns="olac"
               href="../OLAC/1.1/olac-linguistic-field.xsd"/>
            <extension name="linguistic-type" ns="olac"
               href="../OLAC/1.1/olac-linguistic-type.xsd"/>
            <extension name="role" ns="olac" href="../OLAC/1.1/olac-role.xsd"/>

         </extensions>
         <p/>
      </section>
   </body>
   <references>
      <ref abbrev="DCQ">"5. Qualified Dublin Core," in Guidelines for Implementing Dublin
         Core in
            XML.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2003/04/02/dc-xml-guidelines/</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Metadata">OLAC Metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Process">OLAC
            Process.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/process.html</url>&gt;</ref>
   </references>
</OLAC_doc>
