<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="OLAC_doc.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc>
  <header>
    <status code="draft" type="recommendation"/>
    <title>OLAC Linguistic Data Type Vocabulary</title>
    <baseName>type</baseName>
    <issued>20021121</issued>
    <previousIssued>20020628</previousIssued>
    <abstract><p>
              This document specifies the codes, or controlled vocabulary,
              for the Linguistic Data Type extension of the OLAC Type
              element.  These codes describe the content of a resource
              from the standpoint of recognized structural types of
              linguistic information.
    </p></abstract>
    <editors>
      Heidi Johnson (<url>mailto:ailla@ailla.org</url>)
      Helen Aristar Dry (<url>mailto:hdry@linguistlist.org</url>)
    </editors>
    <copyright>
      Heidi Johnson (University of Texas at Austin)
      Helen Aristar Dry (Eastern Michigan University)
    </copyright>
    <changes>
      <p>Adds: Grammar, Primary_Text</p>
      <p>
              Deletes: Transcription section,  Annotation section, Text
              section (changed to Primary_Text), subtypes of Dataset,
              subtypes of Lexicon, subtypes of Description.
      </p>
    </changes>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
    <heading>Introduction</heading>
<p>
Like all OLAC elements, the Type element is both optional  and repeatable.
Since it is optional, the Linguistic Data Type extension of the Type element
should only be used if a resource represents a recognized linguistic data
type. However, if a resource represents more than one linguistic data type,
the element may be repeated.  So, for example, a primary text accompanied by
a lexicon of vocabulary items would be described as both a primary text and
a lexicon.
</p>

<p>
In many cases, adequate description of a linguistic resource will require
that the Linguistic Data Type extension be used in conjunction with the
Discourse Type extension of the Type element, or the Linguistic Field
extension of the Subject element.    For example, a narrative text might  be
described as both a primary text (OLAC Linguistic Type) and a narrative
(OLAC Discourse Type). And a phoneme dataset might be describedboth as a
dataset (OLAC Linguistic Type) and as relevant to phonology (OLAC Linguistic
Field).
</p>
    </section>

<section>
<heading>Linguistic Data Type</heading>
<p>
Each term in the controlled vocabulary is described in one of the
following subsections. The heading gives the encoded value for the
term that is to be used as the value of the code attribute of the
"OLAC-Linguistic-Type" extension of the Type metadata element
<cit>OLAC-MS</cit>. Under the heading, the term is described in four
ways. <i>Name</i> gives a descriptive label for the term.
<i>Definition</i> is a one-line summary of what the term
means. <i>Comments</i> offers more details on what the term
represents. Examples may also be given to illustrate how the term is
meant to be applied.
</p>

<term>
  <code>dataset</code>
  <name>Dataset</name>
  <definition>The resource is a structured set of data items.</definition>
  <comment><p>
     A dataset is a collection of items organized in a
     structured format for some specific research purpose.</p>
  </comment>
  <examples><p>
     Examples of datasets are: a set of sentences
     illustrating deictic terms; an inflectional affix
     paradigm; a list of utterance tokens in a uniform
     context (e.g. "Say [pat] now."); a chart giving a
     phonemic inventory classified by place/manner; an audio
     recording of minimal pairs.
  </p></examples>
</term>

<term>
  <code>lexicon</code>
  <name>Lexicon</name>
  <definition>The resource includes a systematic listing of lexical items.</definition>
  <comment><p>
    Lexicon may be used to describe any resource which
    includes a systematic listing of lexical items. Each
    lexical item may, but need not,  be accompanied by a
    definition, a description of the referent (in the case
    of proper names), or an indication of the item's
    semantic relationship to other lexical items.
  </p></comment>
  <examples><p>
    Examples include word lists (including comparative word
    lists), thesauri,  wordnets, framenets, and
    dictionaries, including specialized dictionaries such
    as bilingual and multilingual dictionaries,
    dictionaries of terminology, and dictionaries of proper
    names. Non-word-based examples include phrasal lexicons
    and lexicons of intonational tunes.
  </p></examples>
</term>

<term>
  <code>primary_text</code>
  <name>Primary Text</name>
  <definition>Linguistic material which is itself the object of study.</definition>
  <comment><p>
    Primary Text is used to describe material in the
    subject language which embodies linguistic or cultural
    features which make it an object of analysis or
    research. What distinguishes a primary text from a
    lexicon, dataset, or description is its temporal
    structure. In a primary text, the timecourse of some
    external linguistic event, e.g., a conversation or
    elicitation session, is carried over into the archived
    artefact.</p>

    <p>Note:  Primary_text describes the content of the
    resource, not the physical format.  A primary text may
    be recorded in different physical media, e.g. as
    videotaped, audiotaped, or written text.  Physical
    format is described using the Format element.
  </p></comment>
  <examples><p>
    Examples of primary texts include transcribed
    interlinear texts, (audiotaped) elicitation sessions,
    (videotaped) rituals or story-telling sessions, and any
    other recorded speech or writing which exemplifies
    language structure or use in such a way as to become an
    object of study.
  </p></examples>
</term>

<term>
  <code>description</code>
  <name>Description</name>
  <definition>The resource is a linguistic description of a language
              or some aspect(s) of a language.</definition>
  <comment><p>
    Not every resource with descriptive content should be
    described with this code. Instead, it should be
    reserved for a work that describes some aspect of a
    particular language, typically in prose with
    interspersed examples.
  </p></comment>
  <examples><p>
    Examples of descriptions include a grammar, a sketch
    grammar, a phonological sketch.
  </p></examples>
</term>
</section>
</body>

<references>
  <ref abbrev="OLAC-MS">OLAC Metadata Set.<br/>
    &lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/olacms.html</url>&gt;</ref>
</references>
</OLAC_doc>
