<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="OLAC_doc.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc> 
  <header> 
    <status code="proposed" type="standard" endDate="20021211" supersededBy="metadata"/> 
      <title>OLAC Metadata Set</title> <baseName>olacms</baseName> 
      <issued>20011022</issued> <previousIssued>20010616</previousIssued> 
      <abstract> 
        <p>This document specifies the metadata set used by the Open Language
          Archives Community <cit>OLAC</cit> for the interchange of metadata within the
          framework of the Open Archives Initiative <cit>OAI</cit>.
          This document is superseded by the OLAC Metadata standard:
            <url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url></p> 
      </abstract> 
      <editors>Gary Simons, SIL International
        (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>)<br/>Steven Bird, University of
        Pennsylvania (<url>mailto:sb@ldc.upenn.edu</url>)</editors><copyright>2001 Gary
      Simons (SIL International) and Steven Bird (University of
      Pennsylvania)</copyright> 
      <changes> 
        <p>Adds <i>scheme</i> attribute (see sections 1 and 2). The <i>lang</i>
          attribute on <tt>&lt;olac&gt;</tt> is renamed to <i>langs.</i> Following
          <cit>DC-Q</cit>, adds <i>alternative</i> as a possible refinement for Title so
          that the original title can be distinguished from translations. Type.data is
          renamed as <xref>Type.linguistic</xref>. These changes are reflected in version
          0.4 of the OLAC metadata schema which is being released at the same time.
          (Another significant change to the schema is that the use of capitalization in
          element names now conforms to the usage in the examples in this document.)
          Significant addition to discussion of <xref>Coverage</xref>. Numerous minor
          editorial revisions. </p> 
      </changes> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section> 
      <heading>Introduction</heading> 
      <p>This document describes the OLAC metadata set and its implementation
        in XML. The OLAC metadata set is based on the Dublin Core metadata set and uses
        all fifteen elements defined in that standard <cit>DCMES1.1</cit>. (The
        rationale for following DC is discussed in the OLAC white paper
        <cit>OLAC-WP</cit>.) </p> 
      <p>In order to meet the specific needs of the language archiving
        community, the OLAC metadata set qualifies the fifteen DC elements following
        principles articulated in <cit>DC-Q</cit> and exemplified in
        <cit>DCQ-HTML</cit>. These documents describe three kinds of qualification:
        element refinement, encoding scheme, and content language. The OLAC
        implementation of qualified DC uses three attributes to support these kinds of
        qualification: <i>refine, scheme,</i> and <i>lang,</i> respectively.</p> 
      <p>The OLAC metadata standard prescribes a particular encoding scheme for
        many elements. In these cases, a <i>code</i> attribute is used to store the
        encoded element value, while the element content is still available for a value
        that does not conform to the prescribed scheme. (Note that when applying a
        so-called "dumb down" procedure to map the qualified OLAC metadata onto
        unqualified DC, the value of the <i>code</i> attribute would be moved into the
        content of the element. A more intelligent mapping could also translate the
        coded value to a more readable descriptive label.)</p> 
      <p>This standard also prescribes a particular encoding scheme for some
        element refinements. In these cases the refinement is implemented as a new
        element rather than via the <i>refine</i> attribute. This has been motivated by
        a limitation of XML schemas for validating XML documents&#8212;namely, the
        definition of validity for one attribute (e.g. <i>code</i>) cannot be made
        dependent on the value of another attribute (e.g. <i>refine</i>). Thus, when a
        particular refinement requires that the element value use a different encoding
        scheme, then a unique element has been defined. The names for these refined
        elements have been formed as in <cit>DCQ-HTML</cit> by concatenating the DC
        element name and the refinement name with an intervening dot (e.g.
        Subject.language).</p> 
      <p>The XML implementation of the OLAC metadata elements is based on the
        Open Archives Initiative's implementation of Dublin Core metadata elements
        <cit>OAI-DC</cit> in that OLAC defines a proper superset of OAI DC. That is, if
        the container element of a valid OAI DC record is renamed from
        <tt>&lt;dc&gt;</tt> to <tt>&lt;olac&gt;</tt>, the result is still a valid OLAC
        metadata record.</p> 
      <p>The most recent version of the XML schema for the OLAC metadata set
        (which matches this specification) is as follows:</p> 
      <ul> 
        <li> 
          <p>Schema:
            <url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/0.4/olac.xsd</url> </p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p>Example: <url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/0.4/olac.xml
            </url></p> 
        </li> 
      </ul> 
      <p>Section 2 below describes the attributes used in implementing the OLAC
        metadata set. Section 3 then describes each of the elements that make up the
        OLAC metadata set.</p> 
    </section> 
    <section> 
      <heading>Attributes</heading> 
      <p>Four attributes&#8212;<i>refine, code, scheme,</i> and
        <i>lang</i>&#8212;are used throughout the XML implementation of the metadata
        elements. A fifth attribute, <i>langs,</i> is used on complete metadata
        records. These are described in turn below.</p> 
      <p> Some elements in the OLAC metadata set use the <i>refine</i>
        attribute to identify element refinements. These qualifiers make the meaning of
        an element narrower or more specific. A refined element shares the meaning of
        the unqualified element, but with a more restricted scope <cit>DC-Q</cit>. When
        an element does use a <i>refine</i> attribute, the possible values for the
        attribute are restricted to a specified controlled vocabulary.</p> 
      <p>Some elements in the OLAC metadata set use the <i>code</i> attribute
        to hold metadata values that are taken from a specific encoding scheme. The
        attribute value is always a precise value taken from a controlled vocabulary or
        a formal notation that is described in another OLAC document. As a result, all
        service providers are able to interpret uniformly the meaning of any
        <i>code</i> value. The terms of a controlled vocabulary are also incorporated
        into the XML schema for OLAC metadata; thus every <i>code</i> value is tested
        for validity when the OLAC registration server tests a data provider for
        conformance to OLAC standards <cit>OLAC-Registration</cit>. For elements that
        have a <i>code</i> attribute, the element content may also be used to specify a
        freeform elaboration of the coded value.</p> 
      <p>Every element in the OLAC metadata set may use the <i>scheme</i>
        attribute. It specifies a standardized name for the scheme that constrains how
        the text in the content of the element is encoded. A scheme may be a controlled
        vocabulary or a formal notation. Recommended best practice is to confine the
        value of <i>scheme</i> to the label for one of the encoding schemes registered
        with the Dublin Core Metadata Initiative <cit>DCMI-Registry</cit>. Members of
        the OLAC community who want to use an unregistered scheme should submit it for
        registration <cit>DCMI-Submit</cit>. When OLAC data providers are tested for
        conformance to OLAC recommended best practice, only the value of the
        <i>scheme</i> attribute is tested for inclusion in the list of registered
        schemes. OLAC does not test the actual element content for conformance to the
        scheme; a service provider for a subcommunity that has developed a particular
        scheme could perform such a test. </p> 
      <p>Every element in the OLAC metadata set may use the <i>lang</i>
        attribute. It specifies the language in which the text in the content of the
        element is written. The value for the attribute comes from the controlled
        vocabulary defined by <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>. By default, the <i>lang</i>
        attribute has the value "en", for English. Whenever the language of the element
        content is other than English, recommended best practice is to use the
        <i>lang</i> attribute to identify the language. By using multiple instances of
        the metadata elements tagged for different languages, data providers may offer
        their metadata records in multiple languages. </p> 
      <p>The <i>langs</i> attribute is used on the <tt>&lt;olac&gt;</tt>
        element&#8212;the container for all the metadata elements of a given metadata
        record. It lists the languages in which the metadata record is designed to be
        read. This attribute holds a space-delimited list of language codes from the
        <cit>OLAC-Language</cit> controlled vocabulary. By default, this attribute has
        the value "en", for English, indicating that the record is aimed only at
        English readers. If an explicit value is given for the attribute, then the
        record is aimed at readers of all the languages listed.</p> 
      <p>Service providers should use this information in order to offer
        localized views of the metadata. When a metadata record lists only one
        language, then all elements should be displayed (regardless of their individual
        languages), unless the user has requested to suppress all records in that
        language. When a metadata record has multiple alternative languages, the user
        should be able to select one and have display of elements in the other
        languages suppressed. An element in a language not included in the list of
        alternatives should always be displayed (for instance, the vernacular title of
        a work).</p> 
    </section> 
    <section> 
      <heading>Metadata elements</heading> 
      <p>Each element of the OLAC metadata set is described in one of the
        following subsections. The heading gives the generic identifier of the XML tag
        used to encode the element. Under the heading, the element is described in five
        ways. <i>Name</i> gives a descriptive label for the tag. <i>Definition</i> is a
        one-line summary of what the element is used for. <i>Comments</i> offers
        details on how to use the element; the first paragraph typically repeats the
        comment from <cit>DCMES1.1</cit>, while the remaining paragraphs give further
        specification for how OLAC uses the element. <i>Attributes</i> describes the
        XML attributes used with the element. <i>Examples</i> shows samples of properly
        encoded elements.</p> 
      <p>In a given metadata record, every element is optional and every
        element is repeatable.</p> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Contributor</tag> 
        <name>Contributor </name> 
        <definition>An entity responsible for making contributions to the
          content of the resource.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>A Contributor may be a person, an organization, or a service.
            Contributor is closely related to <xref>Creator</xref>. The difference has to
            do with degree of responsibility for the content. The Contributor designation
            is used for those entities whose role in the creation of the resource is not
            great enough to merit recognition as a primary source of the intellectual
            content. This element may be used to identify institutions that sponsored or
            funded the work. It may be used to identify individuals who played a secondary
            role in the development of the resource. As a rule of thumb, Creator is used
            when the contribution is such that it would be cited in the "author" field of a
            bibliographic entry, and Contributor is used otherwise.</p> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to identify the entity by means of a
            name and to give the name in a form that is ready for sorting within an index.
            For the names of persons, this means that the name should be given in inverted
            order with the surname first. For the names of organizations, this means that
            any initial article should be omitted. When a resource has more than one
            contributor, use a separate Contributor element for each one.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>The <i>refine</i> attribute is optionally used to specify the role
            (such as transcriber, sponsor, and so on) played by the named entity in the
            creation of the resource. The role is expressed by means of a controlled
            vocabulary; see <cit>OLAC-Role</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. </p>
          
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A generic contributor:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;contributor&gt;Smith, John L.&lt;/contributor&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A funding agency:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;contributor refine="sponsor"&gt;National Science
    Foundation&lt;/contributor&gt;</eg> 
          <p>The person who performed a role for which there is not a suitable
            code:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;contributor&gt;Smith, John L. (format conversion)&lt;/contributor&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Coverage</tag> 
        <name>Coverage </name> 
        <definition>The extent or scope of the content of the resource.
          </definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p> Coverage will typically include spatial location (a place name or
            geographic coordinates), temporal period (a period label, date, or date range)
            or jurisdiction (such as a named administrative entity).
            <cit>DCMES1.1</cit></p> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to select a value from a controlled
            vocabulary that is identified in the <i>scheme</i> attribute (for example, the
            Thesaurus of Geographic Names <cit>TGN</cit>). Where appropriate, named places
            or time periods should be used in preference to numeric identifiers such as
            sets of coordinates or date ranges.</p> 
          <p>In the OLAC context, service providers already have a database
            that maps languages to the countries in which they are spoken
            <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>. Coverage should not be used to duplicate this
            information; rather service providers will support searches concerning
            languages spoken in a given country by referring to the language database.
            Coverage should be used geographically only when the language involved has a
            wide distribution and the resource focuses on its use in a particular region or
            geopolitical jurisdiction, or conversely, when the resource deals with a region
            that encompasses multiple languages. </p> 
        </comment> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A resource about English in India:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;subject.language code="en"/&gt;
&lt;coverage&gt;India&lt;/coverage&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A resource about languages spoken on Guadalcanal:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;coverage scheme="TGN"&gt;Guadalcanal (island)&lt;/coverage&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A resource about language use in the 19th century:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;coverage&gt;19th century&lt;/coverage&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Creator</tag> 
        <name>Creator</name> 
        <definition>An entity primarily responsible for making the content of
          the resource. </definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>A Creator may be a person, an organization, or a service. Creator
            is closely related to <xref>Contributor</xref>. In determining whether an
            entity is a Creator (as opposed to a Contributor), use the same criteria that
            are followed for deciding that an entity should be listed in the "author" slot
            of a bibliographic reference as a primary source of the intellectual content.
            Entities that do not merit that level of recognition should be treated as
            Contributors.</p> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to identify a Creator by means of a
            name and to give the name in a form that is ready for sorting within an index.
            For the names of persons, this means that the name should be given in inverted
            order with the surname first. For the names of organizations, this means that
            any initial article should be omitted. When a resource has more than one
            creator, use a separate Creator element for each one.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>The <i>refine</i> attribute is optionally used to specify the role
            (such as author, editor, translator, and so on) played by the named entity in
            the creation of the resource. The role is expressed by means of a controlled
            vocabulary; see <cit>OLAC-Role</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. </p>
          
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A personal author:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;creator&gt;Bloomfield, Leonard&lt;/creator&gt;</eg> 
          <p>An institutional author:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;creator&gt;Linguistic Society of America&lt;/creator&gt;</eg> 
          <p>An editor:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;creator refine="editor"&gt;Sapir, Edward&lt;/creator&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
        <todo> 
          <p>Develop the controlled vocabulary and write the OLAC-Role
            document. The MARC vocabulary for "relators" (i.e. the relationship between a
            named entity and a work) may be a good place to start:
            <url>http://lcweb.loc.gov/marc/relators/re0002r1.html</url></p> 
          <p>Here, and with Contributor, we recommend a format that puts
            surname first. We should probably go a step further and recommend that archives
            follow the standards described in AACR2. We need help from a librarian to give
            us a synopsis (or a pointer to such) of the rules for fomatting personal and
            corporate names. </p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Date</tag> 
        <name>Date </name> 
        <definition>A date associated with an event in the life cycle of the
          resource.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to use a coded value (see below) when
            possible, since that guarantees that a service provider can do a straight
            alphanumeric sort to put collections of metadata descriptions in correct
            chronological order. The element content may always be used to express
            date-related values or comments that cannot be fitted into the encoding
            standard.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>The <i>code</i> attribute is used to hold a standardized encoding
            of a date. Following <cit>DCMES1.1</cit>, OLAC uses the YYYY-MM-DD format as
            defined in <cit>W3CDTF</cit>. When a month or day value is less than 10, use a
            leading 0 to maintain a two-digit length. The encoded value may be for the year
            alone, for the year and month, or for an exact date. A range of years is also a
            valid value for this attribute; in this case both years must be four-digit
            values and the earliest year should come first. Thus, the encoded value may
            match one of the four following patterns: <tt>YYYY</tt>, <tt>YYYY-MM</tt>,
            <tt>YYYY-MM-DD</tt>, or <tt>YYYY-YYYY</tt>.</p> 
          <p>The <i>refine</i> attribute is optionally used to refine the
            meaning of the date using values from a controlled vocabulary (for instance,
            date of creation versus date of issue versus date of modification, and so on).
            The vocabulary for refinements to Date is defined in <cit>DC-Q</cit>. </p> 
          <p>A Date with no refinement will be assumed to be the date of issue
            (i.e. publication). A single resource should not have more than one instance of
            each date refinement. In selecting a single date to associate with a resource,
            a service provider will select the most recent of date created, issued, or
            modified.</p> 
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A typical year of publication:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;date code="1992"/&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A resource modified on October 16, 1996:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;date refine="modified" code="1996-10-16"/&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A resource from approximately 1950:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;date code="1950"&gt;circa 1950&lt;/date&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Description</tag> 
        <name>Description</name> 
        <definition>An account of the content of the resource. </definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>Description may include but is not limited to: an abstract, table
            of contents, reference to a graphical representation of content, or a free-text
            account of the content. <cit>DCMES1.1</cit></p> 
          <p>No formatting conventions are defined within the text of
            Description. Service providers may format the entire Description as a single
            paragraph, collapsing adjacent white space characters into a single space.</p> 
          <p>When there is a URL for a document that describes the resource,
            use a separate Description element to encode just that URL. A Description that
            begins with "http:" will be interpreted by service providers as consisting
            solely of a URL and will be presented as a link in user interfaces. Service
            providers are not obliged to search other Description text for the occurrence
            of URLs.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A prose description of a resource:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;description&gt;The CALLHOME Japanese corpus of telephone speech consists
    of 120 unscripted telephone conversations between native speakers
    of Japanese. All calls, which lasted up to 30 minutes, originated
    in North America and were placed to locations overseas (typically
    Japan). Most participants called family members or close friends.
    This corpus contains speech data files ONLY, along with the
    minimal amount of documentation needed to describe the contents
    and format of the speech files and the software packages needed to
    uncompress the speech data. &lt;/description&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A reference to an existing on-line description:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;description&gt;http://www.ldc.upenn.edu/Catalog/LDC96S37.html<br/>&lt;/description&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
        <todo> 
          <p><cit>DC-Q</cit> defines two refinements for Description: table of
            contents and abstract. Do we want to introduce this?</p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Format</tag> 
        <name>Format </name> 
        <definition>The physical or digital manifestation of the resource.
          </definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>Typically, Format may include the media-type or dimensions of the
            resource. Format may be used to determine the software, hardware or other
            equipment needed to display or operate the resource. Examples of dimensions
            include size and duration. <cit>DCMES1.1</cit></p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>The <i>code</i> attribute should be used to make a precise
            identification of the format using a controlled vocabulary. This is especially
            important for digital resources since service providers may use this
            information to match data resources with the software tools that are
            appropriate for manipulating them. See <cit>OLAC-Format</cit> for the
            definition of the vocabulary. </p> 
          <p>The element content may be left empty, but it would typically be
            used to add further details about the format of the resource, such as the
            sampling rate for digital recordings, the size of computer files, the number of
            pages and dimensions of a book, the appearance of a physical object, and so on.
            </p> 
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>For a digitally encoded dictionary:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;format code="text/xml"&gt;5,237 entries in a 1.2M XML
    file.&lt;/format&gt;</eg> 
          <p>For a digitally recorded text:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;format code="audio/wav"&gt;Duration: 153 seconds. Size: 3.3M.
    Sampling: 1 channel, 22 KHz, 8 bits.&lt;/format&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
        <todo> 
          <p>We need to develop the vocabulary for Format. It should be based
            on the list of Internet Media Types <cit>MIME</cit> but we will probably still
            want our own vocabulary document at least for the purpose of explaining and
            exemplifying the use of MIME types. But further than that, we may want to pull
            out a subset of MIME types. We also may want to add some new categories and
            subtypes for our purposes in order to cover archive holdings that are not
            digital, e.g. manuscript, print, microform, and so on. The library or archive
            world probably has such a controlled vocabulary already, e.g. does MARC have
            standards for this?</p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Format.cpu</tag> 
        <name>CPU Requirement</name> 
        <definition>The CPU required to use a software resource.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>This element is used in the description of executable programs to
            identify the kind of CPU that is needed to run them.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>The <i>code</i> attribute is used to make a precise identification
            of the required CPU using a controlled vocabulary. See <cit>OLAC-CPU</cit> for
            the definition of the vocabulary. </p> 
          <p>The element content is typically left empty, but it can be used to
            add further details about the hardware required for running the resource. These
            could go beyond CPU details to include memory, disk, and so on. </p> 
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>Software that runs on a Power PC:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;format.cpu code="ppc"/&gt;</eg> 
          <p>Software that runs on the Intel family of processors but needs at
            least 64 megabytes of memory:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;format.cpu code="x86"&gt;At least 64M memory&lt;/format.cpu&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
        <todo> 
          <p>We need to develop the vocabulary for CPU.</p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Format.encoding</tag> 
        <name>Character Encoding</name> 
        <definition>An encoded character set used by a digital resource.
          </definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>For a resource that is a digitally encoded text, Format.encoding
            names the encoded character set it uses. For a resource that is a font,
            Format.encoding names an encoded character set that it is able to render. For a
            resource that is a software application, Format.encoding names an encoded
            character set that it can read as input or write as output. Service providers
            will use this information to match data files with the software tools that can
            be applied to them.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>The <i>code</i> attribute should be used to identify the character
            set using a controlled vocabulary. See <cit>OLAC-Encoding</cit> for the
            definition of the vocabulary. </p> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to specify the encoding via the
            <i>code</i> attribute while leaving the element content empty. Use the element
            content only when the controlled vocabulary does not offer an appropriate code,
            or when further explanation about a custom encoding is needed. </p> 
        </attributes> 
        <todo> 
          <p>We need to develop the controlled vocabulary for Format.encoding.
            The IANA registry of character set names <cit>IANA-CS</cit> could be used as a
            starting point, but we will need to innovate beyond this. For instance, we will
            need to add something about levels of Unicode conformance as defined by our
            Character Encoding working group. Does MARC have something for this?</p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Format.markup</tag> 
        <name>Markup Scheme</name> 
        <definition>A markup scheme used by a digital resource.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>For a resource that is a text file including markup, Format.markup
            identifies the markup system it uses, such as the SGML DTD, the XML Schema, the
            set of Standard Format markers, and the like. For a resource that is a
            stylesheet or a software application, Format.markup names a markup scheme that
            it can read as input or write as output. Service providers will use this
            information to match data files with the software tools that can be applied to
            them.</p> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to identify the markup scheme by a
            URI giving an OAI identifier for the markup scheme as a resource in an OLAC
            archive. Thus, if the DTD, Schema, or markup documentation is not already
            archived in an OLAC repository, the depositor of a marked-up resource should
            also deposit the documentation for the markup scheme. </p> 
          <p>A resource identified in Format.markup should not also be listed
            with the <i>requires</i> refinement of Relation.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <todo> 
          <p>Do we want to go a step further and have markup schemes be
            deposited at OLAC so that we can try to avoid duplicate ids for the same DTD?
            They could have identifiers like <tt>oai:olac:markup:...</tt> and be defined as
            belonging to a set named <i>markup</i> at the OLAC community data provider so
            that a single OAI harvesting request would retrieve the complete set of known
            markup schemes.</p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Format.os</tag> 
        <name>Operating System Requirement</name> 
        <definition>An operating system required to use a software
          resource.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>This element is used in the description of executable programs to
            identify the operating system environment that is needed to run them. If the
            resource is a data file in a format that is typically associated with a
            particular operating system, use Format only (since cross-platform readers are
            always a possibility).</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to specify the operating system via
            the <i>code</i> attribute. See <cit>OLAC-OS</cit> for the definition of the
            controlled vocabulary used for this purpose. </p> 
          <p>The element content would typically be left empty, but it can be
            used to add further details about the specific operating system version that is
            required, or about other system software components that are required. </p> 
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>Software that runs under OS/2:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;format.os code="OS2"/&gt;</eg> 
          <p>Software that runs only under Windows NT 4.0 or higher:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;format.os code="MSWindows"&gt;NT 4.0 or higher&lt;/format.os&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Format.sourcecode</tag> 
        <name>Source Code Language</name> 
        <definition>A programming language of software distributed in source
          form. </definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>Identifies a programming language used by software that is
            distributed in source code form.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to specify the programming language
            via the <i>code</i> attribute. See <cit>OLAC-Sourcecode</cit> for the
            definition of the controlled vocabulary used for this purpose. </p> 
          <p>The element content would typically be left empty, but it can be
            used to add further details about the particular version or dialect that was
            used. </p> 
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>Source code that is written in C++:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;format.sourcecode code="C"/&gt;</eg> 
          <p>Source code that is written in Java using the version 1.2
            library:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;format.sourcecode code="Java"&gt;Version 1.2 library&lt;/format.sourcecode&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
        <todo> 
          <p>We need to develop the vocabulary for Sourcecode.</p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Identifier</tag> 
        <name>Resource Identifier </name> 
        <definition>An unambiguous reference to the resource within a given
          context.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to identify the resource by means of
            a string or number conforming to a globally-known formal identification system.
            Example formal identification systems include the Uniform Resource Identifier
            (URI) (including the Uniform Resource Locator (URL)), the Digital Object
            Identifier (DOI), and the International Standard Book Number (ISBN).
            <cit>DCMES1.1</cit></p> 
          <p>In the case of a resource that is not electronically encoded, but
            is housed in a conventional archive, Identifier may be used to give a local
            shelf or box number, or whatever scheme is used to locate a resource within the
            collection.</p> 
          <p>Identifiers that begin with "http:" will be interpreted by service
            providers as URLs and be presented as links in user interfaces. Note that
            Identifier is to be used only for a URL that retrieves the actual resource; use
            <xref>Description</xref> for a URL that retrieves just a description of the
            resource.</p> 
          <p>Do not specify the "oai:" identifier for the resource itself as a
            value of Identifier, since it is already given in <tt>&lt;identifier&gt;</tt>
            in the <tt>&lt;header&gt;</tt> of the <tt>&lt;record&gt;</tt>s returned by the
            OAI protocol.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A Uniform Resource Locator for retrieval of an electronically
            encoded resource:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;identifier&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/cs.CL/0010033&lt;/identifier&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A local identifier for retrieval within a physical collection:</p>
          
          <eg>&lt;identifier&gt;Shelf 12, Box 7&lt;/identifier&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Language</tag> 
        <name>Audience Language </name> 
        <definition>A language of the intellectual content of the
          resource.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>Language is used for a language the resource is in, as opposed to
            the language it describes (see <xref>Subject.language</xref>). It is related to
            the audience for the work in that it identifies a language that the creator of
            the resource assumes that its eventual user will understand. When a resource is
            in more than one language, use a separate Language element for each
            language.</p> 
          <p>For a work of literature or other monolingual document aimed at
            the speakers of a particular language, use Language to identify that language.
            For a sound recording, use Language for the language being spoken in the
            recording. For a grammatical description, for instance, use Language for the
            language the grammar is written in; use Subject.language for the language whose
            grammar is being described. For an annotated text, use Language for the
            language in which the annotations are made; use Subject.language for the
            language of the base text that is being annotated. For a dictionary, use
            Language for the language in which the definitions are written; use
            Subject.language for the language whose words are being defined.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>The <i>code</i> attribute should be used to make a precise
            identification of the language using a controlled vocabulary. See
            <cit>OLAC-Language</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. </p> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to specify the language via the
            <i>code</i> attribute while leaving the element content empty. Use the element
            content only when the controlled vocabulary does not offer an appropriate code,
            or when further specification is needed, such as to name a specific dialect or
            to give an alternate name that differs from the default name given by the
            controlled vocabulary. </p> 
          <p>Service providers should use the <i>code</i> attribute to support
            searches by language, and may use the element content in searches by keyword.
            They also may supply the default language name in keyword searching when the
            element content is missing.</p> 
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A resource in English about the Sikaiana language:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;language code="en"/&gt;
&lt;subject.language code="x-sil-SKY"/&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A Yemba-French dictionary, where the alternate name Dschang is
            preferred.</p> 
          <eg>&lt;language code="fr"/&gt;
&lt;subject.language code="x-sil-BAN"&gt;Dschang&lt;/subject.language&gt;</eg> 
          <p>The <i>American Heritage Dictionary</i>, which is both in and
            about American English:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;language code="en"/&gt;
&lt;subject.language code="en"/&gt;
&lt;coverage&gt;United States&lt;/coverage&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A resource about a language for which the controlled vocabulary
            does not yet provide a code:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;subject.language&gt;Ancient Sumerian&lt;/subject.language&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
        <todo> 
          <p>Add an example of specifying a dialect.</p> 
          <p>Write the OLAC-Language document.</p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Publisher</tag> 
        <name>Publisher</name> 
        <definition>An entity responsible for making the resource available
          </definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>Examples of a Publisher include a person, an organization, or a
            service. Typically, the name of a Publisher should be used to indicate the
            entity. <cit>DCMES1.1</cit></p> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to identify a Publisher by means of a
            name and to give the name in a form that is ready for sorting within an index.
            For the names of persons, this means that the name should be given in inverted
            order with the surname first. For the names of organizations, this means that
            any initial article should be omitted. When a resource has more than one
            publisher, use a separate Publisher element for each one.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A typical publisher:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;publisher&gt;Oxford University Press&lt;/publisher&gt;</eg> 
          <p>The URL for a publisher:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;publisher&gt;http://www.oup.com/&lt;/publisher&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Relation</tag> 
        <name>Relation </name> 
        <definition>A reference to a related resource.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>This element is used to document relationships between resources,
            for instance, part-whole relationships, version relationships, dependency
            relationships, and so on. When the related resource is also in a participating
            archive, the reference to the related resource should be by means of an "oai:"
            identifier. A Relation that begins with "oai:" should be presented by service
            providers as an active link that retrieves the metadata for that resource.</p> 
          <p>For a required markup definition (like a DTD or Schema) use
            <xref>Format.markup</xref> rather than Relation. When the required software or
            hardware can be inferred from the <xref>Format</xref> of the resource, do not
            also use Relation for this purpose.</p> 
          <p>When the present resource is a derived work, the source resource
            is typically indicated by <xref>Source</xref>. However, there are two cases in
            which refinements of Relation are used for derived works. The
            <i>isVersionOf</i> refinement is used when the present resource is a new
            version or edition with added intellectual content that has been developed by
            the same creators. When the new version is nothing more than a rendition in a
            new format, then the <i>isForrmatOf</i> refinement is used. </p> 
          <p> </p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>The <i>refine</i> attribute should be used to clarify the nature
            of the relationship using values from a controlled vocabulary (for instance,
            <i>isReplacedBy, requires, hasPart, isPartOf,</i> and so on). The vocabulary
            for refinements to Relation is defined in <cit>DC-Q</cit>. </p> 
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A link to a required font:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;relation refine="requires"&gt;oai:sil:software/ipafont&lt;/relation&gt;</eg> 
          <p>Links to the component pieces of a collected work:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;relation refine="hasPart"&gt;oai:somearchive:holding126&lt;/relation&gt;
&lt;relation refine="hasPart"&gt;oai:somearchive:holding127&lt;/relation&gt;
&lt;relation refine="hasPart"&gt;oai:somearchive:holding128&lt;/relation&gt;
&lt;relation refine="hasPart"&gt;oai:somearchive:holding129&lt;/relation&gt;
&lt;relation refine="hasPart"&gt;oai:somearchive:holding130&lt;/relation&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A chapter that was published in a book (that does not have an
            archived metadata record):</p> 
          <eg>&lt;relation refine="isPartOf"&gt;In Joel Sherzer and Greg Urban (eds.),
    Native South American discourse , 237-306. Berlin: Mouton.
    &lt;/relation&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Rights</tag> 
        <name>Rights Management </name> 
        <definition>Information about rights held in and over the resource.
          </definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p> Typically, a Rights element will contain a rights management
            statement for the resource, or reference a service providing such information.
            Rights information often encompasses Intellectual Property Rights (IPR),
            Copyright, and various Property Rights. If the Rights element is absent, no
            assumptions can be made about the status of these and other rights with respect
            to the resource. <cit>DCMES1.1</cit></p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>code</i> attribute to
            make a summary statement about rights using a controlled vocabulary. If the
            coded value adequately documents the rights management issues, leave the
            element content empty. Otherwise, use the content to add the relevant details.
            See <cit>OLAC-Rights</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. </p> 
        </attributes> 
        <todo> 
          <p>Write the OLAC-Rights document.</p> 
          <p>Add examples after we work out the controlled vocabulary.</p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Source</tag> 
        <name>Source </name> 
        <definition>A reference to a resource from which the present resource
          is derived.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>The present resource may be derived from the Source resource in
            whole or in part. <cit>DCMES1.1</cit> When the Source resource is also
            available in an on-line archive, recommended best practice is to reference it
            by means of an "oai:" identifier. In this case service providers should
            presented the Source as an active link that retrieves the metadata for that
            resource. </p> 
          <p> In the legal parlance of intellectual property rights, a
            "derivative work" is one that is based on one or more preexisting works. This
            includes cases in which a work may be recast, transformed, or adapted in any
            way, such as by translation, abridgement, dramatization, recording,
            transcription, or digital encoding. A work consisting of editorial revisions,
            annotations, elaborations, or other modifications, which, as a whole, represent
            an original work of authorship is also a derivative work
            <cit>Copyright</cit>.</p> 
          <p>This legal definition elucidates the sense of "derived" that is
            intended in the Dublin Core definition of Source. Note, however, that this
            overlaps with <xref>Relation</xref>, since the <i>isFormatOf</i> and
            <i>isVersionOf</i> refinements both refer to derivative works in the technical
            sense.</p> 
          <p>Recommended best practice for OLAC is to reserve the use of Source
            for cases when the present resource has a substantially different
            <xref>Type</xref> or <xref>Creator</xref> or <xref>Title</xref> than the Source
            resource. When the difference from the original work is only a difference of
            <xref>Date</xref> or <xref>Format</xref> or <xref>Publisher</xref> or
            <xref>Identifier</xref> or edition designator in the <xref>Title</xref>, then
            use Relation to encode the relationship to the original work.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <examples> 
          <p>Source for a digital encoding of a manuscript in a participating
            archive:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;source&gt;oai:somearchive:holding1023&lt;/source&gt;</eg> 
          <p>Source for data extracted from a published source:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;source&gt;Kwara'ae flora vocabulary extracted from Guide to the
        Forests of the British Solomon Islands, by T. C. Whitmore.
        Oxford University Press, 1966.&lt;/source&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Subject</tag> 
        <name>Subject and Keywords </name> 
        <definition>The topic of the content of the resource.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>Typically, a Subject will be expressed as keywords, key phrases or
            classification codes that describe a topic of the resource.
            <cit>DCMES1.1</cit></p> 
          <p> Recommended best practice is to select a value from a controlled
            vocabulary or formal classification scheme. The <i>scheme</i> attribute is used
            to identify the scheme.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A Library of Congress subject heading:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;African languages&lt;/subject&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
        <todo> 
          <p>Geographic and temporal aspects of language varieties go in
            Coverage. Subject is where social dimensions of language varieties would go.
            Does the community need to develop an encoding scheme for this? Add an
            example.</p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Subject.language</tag> 
        <name>Subject Language </name> 
        <definition>A language which the content of the resource describes or
          discusses.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>See <xref>Language</xref> for a complete discussion (with
            examples) of using the Language and Subject.language elements.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>As with the <xref>Language</xref> element, a <i>code</i> attribute
            is used to identify the language precisely. </p> 
        </attributes> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Title</tag> 
        <name>Title</name> 
        <definition>A name given to the resource. </definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>Typically, a Title will be a name by which the resource is
            formally known. <cit>DCMES1.1</cit></p> 
          <p>A translation of the title can be supplied in a second Title
            element. Use the <i>lang</i> attribute to identify the language of these
            elements.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>The <i>refine</i> attribute may optionally be used for a single
            refinement supported by <cit>DC-Q</cit>. The value <i>alternative</i> indicates
            a form of the title that is used as a substitute or alternative to the formal
            title of the resource. This qualifier can include abbreviated titles as well as
            translations. Recommended best practice is that only one instance of Title,
            namely the original title, be unqualified.</p> 
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>A typical title:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;title&gt;A Dictionary of the Nggela Language&lt;/title&gt;</eg> 
          <p>A vernacular title with translation:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;title lang="x-sil-LLU"&gt;Na tala 'uria na idulaa diana&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;title refine="alternative" lang="en"&gt;The road to good reading&lt;/title&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Type</tag> 
        <name>Resource Type </name> 
        <definition>The nature or genre of the content of the resource.
          </definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p> Type includes terms describing general categories, functions,
            genres, or aggregation levels for content. To describe the physical or digital
            manifestation of the resource, use the <xref>Format</xref> element.
            <cit>DCMES1.1</cit></p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>code</i> attribute to
            identify the type using the Dublin Core Types controlled vocabulary
            <cit>DC-Type</cit>. The element content is typically left empty. Use the
            element content only when the controlled vocabulary does not offer an
            appropriate type, or when further specification is needed.</p> 
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>The resource is a video recording:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;type code="Image"/&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Type.functionality</tag> 
        <name>The functionality of a software resource.</name> 
        <definition>Software Functionality</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>This element is used with resources that are software applications
            to classify what they are used for.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>code</i> attribute to
            identify the functionality using a controlled vocabulary. See
            <cit>OLAC-Functionality</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. Use the
            element content only when the controlled vocabulary does not offer an
            appropriate code, or when further explanation about the functionality is
            needed. </p> 
        </attributes> 
        <todo> 
          <p>Write the OLAC-Functionality document. We may want to base it on
            the HLT Survey <url>http://cslu.cse.ogi.edu/HLTsurvey/</url> as advocated by
            the ACL/DFKI Natural Language Software Registry.</p> 
          <p>Add examples after we figure out the vocabulary.</p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
      <element> 
        <tag>Type.linguistic</tag> 
        <name>Linguistic Data Type</name> 
        <definition>The nature or genre of the content of the resource from a
          linguistic standpoint.</definition> 
        <comment> 
          <p>For a resource that is information in or about a language,
            Type.linguistic identifies what kind of information it is from a linguistic
            standpoint. For a resource that is a software tool, Type.linguistic identifies
            what kind of information it processes. Service providers may use this
            information to match data files with software tools that might be applied to
            them.</p> 
        </comment> 
        <attributes> 
          <p>Recommended best practice is to the <i>code</i> attribute to
            identify the linguistic data type using a controlled vocabulary. See
            <cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Type</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. The
            vocabulary uses a two-level coding system. There are four primary types
            &#8212;<i>transcription, annotation, description,</i> and <i>lexicon</i>&#8212;
            each of which have a number of subtypes. Use the element content only when the
            controlled vocabulary does not offer an appropriate code, or when further
            explanation about the data type is needed. </p> 
        </attributes> 
        <examples> 
          <p>The resource describes the grammar of a language:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;type.linguistic code="description/grammar"/&gt;</eg> 
          <p>The resource includes the orthographic transcription of text:</p> 
          <eg>&lt;type.linguistic code="transcription/orthographic"/&gt;</eg> 
        </examples> 
        <todo> 
          <p>Write the OLAC-Linguistic-Type document. </p> 
        </todo> 
      </element> 
    </section> 
  </body> 
  <todo> 
    <p>There is not yet a provision for handling subject categorization by
      linguistic classification.</p> 
    <p>Rights.software has been left in limbo. It may be possible to unify it
      with Rights.</p> 
  </todo> 
  <references> 
    <ref abbrev="Copyright">Section 101, Definitions, Copyright Law of the
      United States of America and Related Laws Contained in Title 17 of the United
      States
      Code.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.loc.gov/copyright/title17/92chap1.html#101</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="DCMES1.1">Dublin Core Metadata Element Set, Version 1.1:
      Reference Description.
      <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/1999/07/02/dces/</url>&gt;</ref> 
    <ref abbrev="DC-Q">Dublin Core
      Qualifiers.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/07/11/dcmes-qualifiers/</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="DCQ-HTML">Recording qualified Dublin Core metadata in HTML
      meta
      elements.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/08/15/dcq-html/</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="DCMI-Registry">DCMI Open Metadata
      Registry.<br/>&lt;<url>http://wip.dublincore.org:8080/registry/Registry</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="DCMI-Submit">DCMI Open Metadata Registry: Submit a Scheme for
      Registration.<br/>&lt;<url>http://wip.dublincore.org:8080/registry/authServlet?req_type=newscheme&amp;lang=enUS</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="DC-Type">DCMI Type
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/07/11/dcmi-type-vocabulary/</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="IANA-CS">Internet Character
      Sets.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.isi.edu/in-notes/iana/assignments/character-sets</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="MIME">Internet Media
      Types.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.isi.edu/in-notes/iana/assignments/media-types/media-types</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OAI">Open Archives Initiative.
      <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/</url>&gt;</ref> 
    <ref abbrev="OLAC">Open Language Archives Community.
      <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/</url>&gt;</ref> 
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-CPU">OLAC CPU
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Linguistic-Type">OLAC Linguistic Data Type
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Encoding">OLAC Encoding
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Format">OLAC Format
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Functionality">OLAC Functionality
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Language">OLAC Language
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-OS">OLAC Operating System
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Registration">The OLAC Registration
      Service.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Rights">OLAC Rights
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Role">OLAC Role
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Scheme">OLAC Vocabulary for Encoding
      Schemes.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Sourcecode">OLAC Source Code
      Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="TGN">Getty Thesaurus of Geographical
      Terms.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabulary/tgn/index.html</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-WP">White Paper on Establishing an Infrastructure for
      Open Language
      Archiving<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/docs/white-paper.html</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="W3CDTF">Date and Time Formats, W3C
      Note.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-datetime</url>&gt;</ref> 
    <ref abbrev="OAI-DC">Schema for OAI implementation of Dublin Core
      metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/1.1/dc.xsd</url>&gt;</ref>
    
  </references>
</OLAC_doc>

