<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="OLAC_doc.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc> 
  <header> 
    <status code="proposed" type="standard"/> 
      <title>OLAC Process</title><baseName>process</baseName> 
      <issued>20010521</issued><previousIssued>20010507</previousIssued> 
      <abstract> 
        <p>The document summarizes the governing ideas of OLAC (i.e. the
          purpose, vision, and core values) and then describes how OLAC is organized and
          how it operates.</p> 
      </abstract> 
      <editors>Gary Simons, SIL International
        (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>)<br/>Steven Bird, University of
        Pennsylvania (<url>mailto:sb@ldc.upenn.edu</url>) </editors> <copyright>2001
      Gary Simons (SIL International) and Steven Bird (University of
      Pennsylvania)</copyright> 
      <changes> 
        <p>Following feedback from the Advisory Board, the document was revised
          to address the following issues:</p> 
        <ol> 
          <li> 
            <p>Added paragraph on "Documenting dissent" at the end of section
              5, plus augmented the definition of "Note" in section 4 to clarify their use as
              an outlet for perspectives that are not widely held.</p> 
          </li> 
          <li> 
            <p>Added details to the "Life-cycle phases" of section 5 to clarify
              who has the right to withdraw or retire a document. In short, prior to reaching
              candidate status, the developers of a document may withdraw it; after that only
              an action of the community may withdraw or retire it.</p> 
          </li> 
          <li> 
            <p>Modified "Empowering the players" in section 2 to embody the
              principle that the voice of a participating institution should be commensurate
              with the size of its investment in the OLAC standards. Details of that are
              given in a new subsection on "Voting" in section 5.</p> 
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>Modified "Review" and "Voting" in section 5, and added "Decision
              making" in section 6, to clarify that informal decision making is appropriate
              within working groups but that formal voting should be used when documents are
              reviewed by the whole community.</p>
          </li> 
        </ol> 
      </changes> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section> 
      <heading>Introduction</heading> 
      <p>The document is the standard that defines how the Open Language
        Archives Community (OLAC) is organized and how it operates. In developing this
        standard, many ideas have been adapted from the process documents of four other
        standards efforts: <cit>DCMI-Process</cit>, <cit>IETF-Process</cit>,
        <cit>OASIS-Process</cit>, and <cit>W3C-Process</cit>. The organization and
        process developed for OLAC are much simpler, however. This is fitting since
        OLAC is a small community with limited resources and&#8212;like most open
        source projects&#8212;it crucially depends upon the participation of many
        part-time members. Before defining the organization and process, the
        fundamental ideas that underlie them are first elaborated.</p> 
    </section> 
    <section> 
      <heading>Governing ideas</heading> 
      <p>In a successful enterprise, the participants have shared purpose,
        vision, and core values. These are what Peter Senge calls the "governing ideas"
        of the enterprise <cit>Senge94</cit>. The governing ideas answer three critical
        questions: "Why?" "What?" and "How?" Taken as a unit, they answer the question,
        "What do we believe in?":</p> 
      <ul> 
        <li> 
          <p>Purpose (or mission) is the "Why?"&#8212;the enterprise's answer
            to the question, "Why do we exist?"</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p>Vision is the "What?"&#8212;the picture of the future the
            enterprise seeks to create.</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p>Core values are the "How?"&#8212;these answer the question, "How
            do we want to act consistent with our mission, along the path toward achieving
            our vision?"</p> 
        </li> 
      </ul> 
      <p></p> 
      <p>The purpose (or mission) of OLAC is as follows:</p><blockquote> 
      <p>OLAC, the Open Language Archives Community, is an international
        partnership of institutions and individuals who are creating a worldwide
        virtual library of language resources by:</p> 
      <ul> 
        <li> 
          <p>developing consensus on best current practice for the digital
            archiving of language resources, and</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p> developing a network of interoperating repositories and services
            for housing and accessing such resources.</p> 
        </li> 
      </ul></blockquote> 
      <p>The vision of OLAC is described elsewhere in terms of "the seven
        pillars of language archiving" <cit>OLAC-Vision</cit> and shares much in common
        with the Open Archives Initiative <cit>OAI</cit>. In a nutshell, it is
        that:</p><blockquote> 
      <p>Any user on the Internet should be able go to a single GATEWAY to find
        all the language resources available at all participating institutions, whether
        the resources be DATA, TOOLS, or ADVICE. The community will ensure on-going
        interoperation and quality by following STANDARDS for the METADATA that
        describe resources and services and for processes that REVIEW
        them.</p></blockquote> 
      <p>The following core values guide the means that OLAC will employ to
        achieve its vision:</p><dl><dt>Openness</dt><dd> 
      <p>By <i>open</i> we mean "freely available to all interested parties."
        This implies visibility, accessibility, and reusability. All of the metadata
        published by participating archives will be open. All of the documents
        developed by OLAC will be open. The processes by which those documents are
        developed will also be open.</p></dd><dt>Consensus</dt><dd> 
      <p>Decision making in OLAC will be governed by the principle of
        consensus. A proposed standard or recommendation will be adopted only when
        those who have reviewed it share substantial agreement that it is ready to be
        adopted by the community. This principle does not require unanimous consent,
        but requires far more than a simple majority. As a rule-of-thumb the OLAC
        Coordinators will look for at least 80% approval among those responding before
        moving ahead with a decision.</p></dd><dt>Empowering the players</dt><dd> 
      <p>The standard protocols and processes that define the framework for the
        community will not be set by an executive committee or by members who have paid
        dues. Rather, they will be set by those who are actually "playing the game."
        That is, the price of membership is to implement the standard protocol and
        processes. All institutions who have implemented the OLAC standards will have a
        voice in the consensus process that sets the standards. Furthermore, each
        institution will have a voice that is commensurate with the size of the
        collection they are supporting. This seems only right since implementing any
        changes to the standards will entail a further investment by those
        institutions, and the size of that investment will be related to the size of
        the collection.</p></dd><dt>Peer review</dt><dd> 
      <p>As a part of the academic community, OLAC places a high value on peer
        review. All of the standards and documents of OLAC will go through a process of
        anonymous peer review that is open to all who want to participate. All of the
        resources and services of participating sites will also be open to signed peer
        review.</p></dd></dl> 
    </section> 
    <section> 
      <heading>Organization</heading> 
      <p>This section describes the organization of OLAC in terms of the groups
        of participants that play key roles. This document only defines the groups; see
        <cit>OLAC-Organization</cit> on the OLAC web site for a complete list of the
        currently participating individuals and institutions.</p>
      <dl><dt>Coordinators</dt><dd> 
      <p>The persons who oversee the operation of the process described in this
        document.</p></dd><dt>Advisory Board</dt><dd> 
      <p>The members of the advisory board are persons who are recognized by
        their peers as being leaders within a subcommunity (whether defined by
        discipline or by geography) of the wider language resources and digital
        archiving communities. They
        serve at the invitation of the OLAC Coordinators. Their role is two-fold: to
        advise the Coordinators about how to respond to particular concerns of their
        subcommunities, and to promote OLAC within their subcommunities.
        </p></dd><dt>Participating Archives and Services</dt><dd> 
      <p>The data providers and service providers who are following the OLAC
        standards and have successfully registered their membership on the OLAC
        gateway. For each registered member, there is a designated contact person with
        whom the OLAC Coordinators communicate to conduct community
        business.</p></dd><dt>Prospective Participants</dt><dd> 
      <p>Institutions or projects that have communicated their intent to the
        OLAC Coordinators to become an OLAC data provider or service provider. For each
        prospective participant, there is a designated contact
        person.</p></dd><dt>Working Groups</dt><dd> 
      <p>Groups of individuals who participate in the OLAC process by drafting
        documents that are eventually submitted to the community as proposed standards,
        recommendations, or notes. A working group may also be formed for the purpose
        of cooperating in the implementation of standards, recommendations, or notes.
        For each working group, there is a chairperson who serves as the designated
        contact person.</p></dd><dt>Participating Individuals</dt><dd> 
      <p>Members of the wider user community who are interested in
        participating in the OLAC process and have registered with the OLAC gateway to
        receive community news and invitations to review OLAC documents. </p></dd></dl>
      
    </section> 
    <section> 
      <heading>Type and status of documents</heading> 
      <p>The OLAC process is about how documents are developed and promulgated,
        for it is through documents that OLAC defines itself and the practices that it
        promotes. The documents published by OLAC are of three types:</p>
      <dl><dt>Standard</dt><dd> 
      <p>A standard describes procedures that participating archives and
        services must follow when participating in the activities of the community or
        specifications they must follow when implementing data providers or service
        providers.</p></dd><dt>Recommendation</dt><dd> 
      <p>A recommendation describes the OLAC consensus on the best current
        practice regarding some aspect of language-resource archiving. Data providers
        and service providers (as well as the projects and individuals that create
        language resources) are encouraged, but not required, to follow these
        recommendations. The public review of data providers and service providers may
        include an assessment of degree of conformance to best current
        practice.</p></dd><dt>Note</dt><dd> 
      <p>A note is any document published by OLAC which is neither a standard
        nor a recommendation. One purpose of notes is to ensure that standards and
        recommendations stay focused on rules and principles. Extended discussion or
        details of implementations should be treated separately in supporting notes.
        Another purpose is to provide a venue for perspectives that are not widely
        held. For instance, a note could be:</p> 
      <ul> 
        <li> 
          <p><i>Experimental.</i> A note could propose a new or different
            approach that is not mature enough to be put forward as a standard or a
            recommendation but that has enough merit to put forward within the community
            for peer review.</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p><i>Informational.</i> A note could give helpful information
            related to some aspect of a standard or recommendation, such as a description
            of historical background, an elaboration, a rationale, a non-normative
            explanation, or even an alternative viewpoint.</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p><i>Implementational.</i> A note could give a description of a
            particular approach to implementing a standard or recommendation.</p> 
        </li> 
      </ul></dd></dl> 
      <p>Orthogonal to the classification by type, OLAC documents are also
        classified by status. The first five status categories correspond to phases in
        the life cycle of a document; the sixth category represents withdrawal from the
        life cycle.</p> <dl><dt>Draft</dt><dd> 
      <p>A document has <i>draft</i> status from its inception until the point
        at which its working group achieves consensus on its
        content.</p></dd><dt>Proposed</dt><dd> 
      <p>The status of a document moves from draft to <i>proposed</i> when it
        moves out of its working group and is posted for open peer review by the whole
        community. </p></dd><dt>Candidate</dt><dd> 
      <p>The status of a document moves from proposed to <i>candidate</i> when
        it has been approved by the community, but has not yet had sufficient
        experience with implementation to be considered for full adoption. (A note that
        needs no implementation may skip the candidate status.)
        </p></dd><dt>Adopted</dt><dd> 
      <p>The status of a document moves from candidate to <i>adopted</i> when
        it has been approved by the community following an adequate period of
        experience with implementation.</p></dd><dt>Retired</dt><dd> 
      <p>The status of a document moves from adopted to <i>retired</i> when the
        community decides that it is no longer relevant.</p></dd><dt>Withdrawn</dt><dd>
      
      <p>The status of a document changes to <i>withdrawn</i> when it is
        removed from the document process before attaining adopted status.
        </p></dd></dl> 
    </section> 
    <section> 
      <heading>The document process</heading> 
      <p>The OLAC document process defines how documents get endorsed and
        published by OLAC. This includes treatment of intellectual property rights, as
        well as the means by which documents enter the process and progress from one
        status to the next along the five-phase life cycle. </p> 
      <p><i>Intellectual property rights.</i> All documents published by OLAC
        on its web site are published under the terms of the Open Publication License
        <cit>OPL</cit>. Typically, the authors or editors of the document will be
        listed as the copyright holders.</p> 
      <p><i>Review.</i> Documents must pass a review process in order to move
        to a higher status. The ultimate aim of review is: (1) to reveal specific
        points that need to be improved, and (2) to determine whether there is
        consensus that the document is ready to advance. The basis for consensus
        depends on the type of document:</p> 
      <ul> 
        <li> 
          <p><i>Standard.</i> Is the document ready to serve OLAC as a
            standard? (Reviewers should agree with the content since they will be obligated
            to follow it.)</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p><i>Recommendation.</i> Is the document ready to be put forward to
            the language resources community as best practice? (Reviewers should agree that
            the described practice will produce high-quality reusable data, though they are
            not obligated to follow the practice.)</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p><i>Note.</i> Is the document ready for publication? (Reviewers are
            not asked to agree with the content, only to agree that it is written well
            enough to be published.)</p> 
        </li> 
      </ul> 
      <p><i>Voting.</i> While a document is in draft status, the review process
        may be informal, but once it has achieved proposed status, it must pass a
        formal review process in order to move to a higher status. Reviewers are asked
        to make their summary evaluation of the document by voting for one of four
        options: </p> 
      <ul> 
        <li> 
          <p><i>Release.</i> The document is ready as-is to be released to the
            next phase in the process.</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p><i>Revise.</i> The document is ready for release without further
            review once noted minor revisions are made.</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p><i>Resubmit.</i> The document should be revised and resubmitted
            for another round of review.</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p><i>Reject.</i> The document does not have a solid enough basis to
            build on; it should be withdrawn from the process.</p> 
        </li> 
      </ul> 
      <p>In the case of recommendations and notes, every participating
        individual is invited to vote. As a general guideline, the OLAC Coordinators
        are to look for at least 80% agreement among all those casting votes as an
        indicator of consensus. </p>
      <p>In the case of standards, all participating individuals are invited to
        comment, but not to vote. Only participating archives and services have a
        binding vote. In order to account for the relative sizes of participants, each
        participant will cast a number of votes that is equal to the logarithm (base
        ten) of the number of metadata records that their archive or service is
        managing. In this case as well, consensus will be judged to mean at least 80%
        of the votes cast. Prospective participants will also be asked to vote since
        the outcome could have a significant impact on their anticipated participation.
        Their votes will not be binding, but will be taken into consideration by the
        Coordinators in judging the final outcome of the review.</p> 
      <p><i>Life-cycle phases.</i> The life-cycle phases are now defined in
        terms of expected activity, duration, and criteria for advancing to the next
        phase:</p> <dl><dt>Development phase</dt><dd> 
      <p>A document enters the process by one of two means. (1) Any working
        group may create a draft document. (2) An author who is not part of a working
        group may submit a draft document to the OLAC Coordinators. In the latter case,
        the Coordinators have two options: they may choose for the document to be
        processed in a working group (either by directing the author to join an
        existing working group or by assisting the author to form a new one), or they
        may choose for the document to be reviewed by at least three individuals whom
        they designate.</p>
      <p>When a document is processed by a working group, the development phase
        comes to an end in one of two ways: the working group may decide to withdraw
        the document from the process, or it may reach consensus that the document is
        ready to be presented to the entire community as a proposal. At this point the
        working group chairperson notifies the OLAC Coordinators and the document
        attains proposed status.</p>
      <p>When a document is processed by the Coordinators, the possible
        outcomes are the same: the designated reviewers may recommend that the document
        be withdrawn, or they may reach consensus that the document is ready to be
        presented to the entire community as a proposal. </p></dd><dt>Proposal
      phase</dt><dd> 
      <p>When a document achieves proposed status, the OLAC Coordinators send a
        call for review with a specific deadline date to the entire community. At the
        end of the review period, the tally of votes will be reported to the community
        and the specific comments (protecting reviewer identity when desired) will be
        made visible. </p> 
      <p>The Coordinators will evaluate the results of the review to make a
        judgement as to whether there is a consensus that the document should advance
        to the next phase. If the Coordinators feel that too few participants have
        responded to feel comfortable about declaring a consensus, they may extend the
        review period. If the consensus is to reject the document, then it is withdrawn
        from the process. Otherwise, the Coordinators will advise the document's
        editors as to the next step. A document could remain in the proposal phase for
        multiple rounds of revision and review. The phase ends when either: (1) the
        document is withdrawn (whether following a consensus to reject or following a
        request from the editors after failing to revise the document successfully), or
        (2) the community has indicated consensus that the document is ready for
        release to the next phase and the Coordinators have determined that the editors
        have made any needed revisions.</p> 
      <p>Standards, recommendations, and some notes require implementation and
        community experience to ensure that they are ready for adoption. These
        documents achieve candidate status and enter the testing phase. Notes that
        require no implementation may go straight to adoption. </p></dd><dt>Testing
      phase</dt><dd> 
      <p>When a document enters candidate status, the OLAC Coordinators send a
        call for implementation with a specific deadline date to the entire community.
        The implementation period will be set for a duration not shorter than one month
        nor longer than one year, depending on the anticipated difficulty of
        implementation. At the end of the testing period, a call for review will be
        issued in which the community members who have actually put the document to use
        are invited to describe their experience and vote on whether it is ready to
        advance to adoption. The process for evaluating the results of the review and
        advancing to the next phase is as described for the proposal phase with one
        exception&#8212;a reviewer consensus to reject is the only basis for
        withdrawing a document.</p> </dd><dt>Adoption phase</dt><dd> 
      <p>A document may remain in the adopted status for an indefinite period.
        Its status remains as adopted until community action is taken to move it to
        retired status. (Once adopted a document may not be withdrawn; it may only be
        retired.)</p> </dd><dt>Retirement phase</dt><dd> 
      <p>A document enters the retirement phase when it is given retired
        status. This could happen when it is superseded by the adoption of a newer
        version of the same document, when it is superseded by the adoption of an
        altogether different document, or when the community agrees that it has
        otherwise outlived its usefulness. In all cases an action of the community is
        required to move a document to retired status.</p></dd></dl> 
      <p><i>Changes to adopted documents.</i> In the case of corrections or
        editorial refinements, the OLAC Coordinators may authorize a new version of an
        adopted document without going through community review. However, any
        substantive changes should be processed via a formal call for review. In this
        case, the new version enters the process with proposed status and the adopted
        version maintains its adopted status until it is retired by the adoption of the
        new version. </p> 
      <p><i>Documenting dissent.</i> The appropriate place for the discussion
        of dissenting opinions about aspects of a document is in the mailing list for
        the working group that has sponsored the document. In this way the alternative
        ideas will not be lost, but will become part of the permanent archive of the
        working group's mailing list. At any time, dissenting ideas may be given a more
        prominent form by developing them into an experimental note that proposes an
        alternative approach or into an informational note that discusses the relative
        merits of different approaches. </p> 
    </section> 
    <section> 
      <heading>The working group process</heading> 
      <p>Working groups play a fundamental role in the OLAC process as the
        primary source of the documents that enter the OLAC document process. In
        keeping with the OLAC core value of openness, working groups are open to
        observation and participation by any member of the community. They are
        self-organizing in that members of the community may recognize the need for a
        working group and set it up on their own initiative. </p> 
      <p><i>Formation.</i> A working group is formed by three or more eligible
        participants who represent at least three different institutions. Any person
        who is registered with OLAC as a Participating Individual is eligible to
        participate in an OLAC working group. In order to form a working group, the
        prospective group must submit the following to the OLAC Coordinators:</p> 
      <ul> 
        <li> 
          <p>the name of the working group</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p>a statement of purpose that is germane to the purpose of OLAC</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p>the names and email addresses of members representing at least
            three different institutions</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p>the name of the chairperson</p> 
        </li> 
        <li> 
          <p>a list of planned documents and the projected date for completing
            the development phase of each</p> 
        </li> 
      </ul> 
      <p>When the above conditions are satisfactorily met, the OLAC
        Coordinators will set up a web page for the working group and a mailing list
        that is seeded with the initial membership list. When those are in place, a
        call for participation will be sent out to the entire OLAC community. Any
        person who wants to participate in the development of the planned documents may
        subscribe to the mailing list and thereby become a member of the working
        group.</p> 
      <p><i>Chairperson.</i> The working group chairperson serves as the point
        of contact with the OLAC Coordinators concerning the activities of the working
        group. The chairperson is responsible to keep the working group moving toward
        completing the documents listed on its web page and to communicate changes of
        plans for the working group to the OLAC Coordinators. A chairperson may resign
        or may be removed by a 2/3 vote of the working group members. A vacancy is
        filled by election from among members of the working group.</p> 
      <p><i>Meetings.</i> Working groups typically conduct their business
        electronically, via their web page and their mailing list. If and when working
        groups do want to meet by teleconference or face-to-face, the working group
        members or their institutions will bear such costs.</p> 
      <p><i>Activities.</i> The most concerted activity of a working group
        takes place during the development phase of its documents. Once a document
        reaches proposed status, the working group gets involved only when the
        community review calls for major revisions. Such revisions should be vetted
        within the working group before the document is resubmitted for community-wide
        review.</p>
      <p><i>Decision making.</i> The decision making within a working group
        will generally be done informally by gauging the sense of the traffic on the
        mailing list. However, when deemed necessary, the chairperson may request that
        the OLAC Coordinators set up a formal vote for the working group.</p> 
      <p><i>Dissolution.</i> A working group will remain constituted as long as
        it is making progress towards developing planned documents or as long as
        documents it has developed are in proposed or candidate status. When these
        conditions are not met, the working group may elect to dissolve itself or may
        be dissolved by the OLAC Coordinators.</p> 
    </section> 
  </body> 
  <references> 
    <ref abbrev="DCMI-Process">Dublin Core Metadata Initiative - Structure and
      Operation.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/1999/05/31/dcmi-structure/</url>&gt;<br/>Guidelines
      for Dublin Core Working Groups - Working Draft
      1.4.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/1999/06/02/wgguidelines/</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="IETF-Process">Internet Standards Process - RFC
      2026.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2026.txt</url>&gt;</ref> 
    <ref abbrev="OAI">Open Archives
      Initiative.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/</url>&gt;</ref> 
    <ref abbrev="OASIS-Process">OASIS [Organization for the Advancement of
      Structured Information Standards] Technical Committee Process Overview.
      <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/process.shtml</url>&gt;
      <br/>A Scalable Process for Information Standards, by Jon Bosak.
      <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.xml.com/pub/a/2001/01/17/oasisprocess.html</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="W3C-Process">World Wide Web Consortium Process
      Document.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Process-20010208/</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="Senge94">The Fifth Discipline: The art and practice of the
      learning organization, by Peter M, Senge. New York: Currency Doubleday, 1994.
      See especially, "Anchoring vision in a set of governing ideas," pages 223-225.
      </ref> 
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Organization">OLAC
      Organization.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/organization.html</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OLAC-Vision">The Seven Pillars of Open Language Archiving: A
      Vision Statement.
      <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/docs/vision.html</url>&gt;</ref>
    
    <ref abbrev="OPL">Open Publication
      License.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.opencontent.org/openpub/</url>&gt;</ref> 
  </references>
</OLAC_doc>
