<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="OLAC_doc.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc> 
  <header>
    <status code="candidate" type="standard"/>
      <title> OLAC Repositories</title><baseName>repositories</baseName> 
      <issued>20030528</issued><previousIssued>20021211</previousIssued> 
      <abstract> 
        <p>This document defines the standards OLAC data providers must follow in implementing a metadata repository. </p> 
      </abstract> 
      <editors>Gary Simons, SIL International (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>)<br/>Steven Bird, University of Melbourne and University of Pennsylvania  (<url>mailto:sb@csse.unimelb.edu.au</url>)</editors> <copyright>2002 Gary Simons
      (SIL International) and Steven Bird (University of Melbourne and University of Pennsylvania)</copyright>
      <changes><p>
        Provides updated information about the static repository format
        and validation service.</p>
      </changes> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section> 
      <heading>Introduction</heading> 
      <p>The OLAC standard on metadata repositories is based on the Open Archives Initiative protocol for metadata harvesting <cit>OAI-PMH</cit>. This document assumes familiarity with the OAI protocol. A data provider may take the form of a dynamic repository that implements a CGI interface to query a live database in response to protocol requests, or it may take the form of a static repository that has no interface of its own but is serviced through a static repository gateway <cit>OAI-SR</cit>.</p>
      <p>An OLAC data provider must answer two special description elements as part of the response to the <tt>Identify</tt> request.  It must:</p>
      <ul><li><p>Supply an <xref>OAI identifier description</xref> </p>
      </li><li><p>Supply an <xref>OLAC archive description</xref> </p>
      </li></ul><p>These  elements are described in the next two sections. The remaining sections describe:</p>
      <ul><li><p><xref>Requirements on static repositories</xref> </p>
      </li><li><p><xref>Requirements on dynamic repositories</xref> </p>
      </li></ul> 
       
    </section>
    <section><heading>OAI identifier description</heading>
      <p>  The resource identifiers supplied by an OLAC data provider must comply with the OAI specification for the format of OAI identifiers as defined in <cit>OAI-Ids</cit>.   The data provider must document its compliance with this format by including an <tt>&lt;oai-identifier&gt;</tt> element within a <tt>&lt;description&gt;</tt> container in the <tt>Identify</tt> response.</p>
      <p>The schema for validating an OAI identifier description is found at:</p>
      <blockquote><p><url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai-identifier.xsd</url></p>
      </blockquote><p>In addition to being valid with respect to the schema, these are further requirements on the content of the OAI identifier description:</p>
      <ul><li><p>The <tt>repositoryIdentifier</tt> must be unique among all registered OLAC data providers.</p>
      </li><li><p>The <tt>repositoryIdentifier</tt> must be based on a registered domain name, typically of the sponsoring institution. A single institution may use subdomain names to distinguish data providers that are internally distinct.</p>
      </li><li><p>The <tt>sampleIdentifier</tt> must be of an existing item in the data provider, and not a hypothetical item.</p>
      </li></ul><p>For example,</p>
      <eg>&lt;description&gt;
   &lt;oai-identifier
         xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai-identifier"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai-identifier
                    http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai-identifier.xsd"&gt;
      &lt;scheme&gt;oai&lt;/scheme&gt;
      &lt;repositoryIdentifier&gt;ethnologue.com&lt;/repositoryIdentifier&gt;
      &lt;delimiter&gt;:&lt;/delimiter&gt;
      &lt;sampleIdentifier&gt;oai:ethnologue.com:AAA&lt;/sampleIdentifier&gt;
   &lt;/oai-identifier&gt;
&lt;/description&gt;
</eg></section>
    <section><heading>OLAC archive description</heading>
      <p>The basic <tt>Identify</tt> request supplies minimal information about an archive, namely, its name, base URL, and administrator email. An OLAC data provider must augment the <tt>Identify</tt> response by including an <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt> element within a <tt>&lt;description&gt;</tt> container. This element gives additional information that makes it possible for an OLAC service provider to supply  its users with a basic description of a participating archive. </p>
      <p>The schema for validating an OLAC archive description is found at:</p>
      <blockquote><p><url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.0/olac-archive.xsd</url></p>
      </blockquote><p>The <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt> element has an obligatory attribute, <tt>type</tt>, which must have one of two values:</p>
      <ul><li><p><tt>type="institutional"</tt> indicates that the repository is sponsored and operated by an institution</p>
      </li><li><p><tt>type="personal"</tt> indicates that the repository is sponsored and operated by an individual (or a group of individuals)</p>
      </li></ul><p>These are the elements within an OLAC archive description:</p>
      <dl><dt>archiveURL</dt><dd> <p><i>Optional.</i> The home page of the archive on the Web. This is the home page for human visitors, not the base URL for harvesting.</p>
      </dd><dt>curator</dt><dd><p>The name of the person who curates the  archive collection. If more than one person has collaborated as  personal sponsors of the archive, then this element should contain all the names in the order and format the collaborators want to be cited. </p>
      </dd><dt>curatorTitle</dt><dd><p><i>Optional.</i> The job title of the curator within the sponsoring institution (for an institutional archive) or within the institution of affiliation (for a personal archive).</p>
      </dd><dt>curatorEmail</dt><dd><p><i>Optional.</i> A <tt>mailto:</tt> URI giving the email address for contacting the curator of the archive. (Note that this is distinct from the <tt>&lt;adminEmail&gt;</tt> in the <tt>Identify</tt> response which is the contact address for the maintainer of the  data provider.)</p>
      </dd><dt>institution</dt><dd><p>The name of the sponsoring institution (for an institutional archive) or the institution of affiliation (for a personal archive). The field is obligatory. If the curator of a personal archive has no affiliation, then a value of <i>Unaffiliated</i> should be given.</p>
      </dd><dt>institutionURL</dt><dd><p><i>Optional.</i> A URL for the home page of the institution.</p>
      </dd><dt>shortLocation</dt><dd><p><i>Obligatory.</i> A brief statement of the location  of the institution or the person providing the metadata following the format "City, Country". Multiple locations may be connected with "and".  This information is shown in the location column of the table of participating archives at 
  <url>http://www.language-archives/archives.php4</url>.</p>
      </dd><dt>location</dt><dd><p><i>Optional.</i> A single paragraph (not to exceed 1000 characters)  describing where an archive that houses a collection of physical holdings is located (for instance, include building name, room number, street address). Other information relevant to visiting the collection, such as opening hours or restrictions on access, may also be described. If the archive is purely an on-line repository,  do not use this element.</p>
      </dd><dt>synopsis</dt><dd><p>A single paragraph (not to exceed 1000 characters) summarizing the purpose, scope,  coverage, and so on of the archive.</p>
      </dd><dt>access</dt><dd><p>A single paragraph (not to exceed 1000 characters) summarizing terms of access to the materials described in the published metadata. The statement should mention restrictions on access, licensing
requirements, costs, and so on.  Individual metadata records should use the Rights element to document such things for particular archive holdings. The purpose of <tt>&lt;access&gt;</tt> is to broadly characterize the entire archive.</p>
      </dd></dl><p>For example,</p>
      <eg>&lt;description&gt;
   &lt;olac-archive
         xmlns="http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.0/"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.0/
                    http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.0/olac-archive.xsd"
         type="institutional"&gt;
      &lt;archiveURL&gt;http://www.ethnologue.com&lt;/archiveURL&gt;
      &lt;curator&gt;Raymond G. Gordon, Jr.&lt;/curator&gt;
      &lt;curatorTitle&gt;Ethnologue Editor&lt;/curatorTitle&gt;
      &lt;curatorEmail&gt;mailto:editor_ethnologue@sil.org&lt;/curatorEmail&gt;
      &lt;institution&gt;SIL International&lt;/institution&gt;
      &lt;institutionURL&gt;http://www.sil.org&lt;/institutionURL&gt;
      &lt;shortLocation&gt;Dallas, USA&lt;/shortLocation&gt;
      &lt;location&gt;7500 W. Camp Wisdom Rd., Dallas, TX 75236, U.S.A.&lt;/location&gt;
      &lt;synopsis&gt;The Ethnologue data provider gives a metadata record for every
      language entry in the Web edition of the Ethnologue.  The latter provides
      basic information about each of the 7,000+ modern language of the world
      (both living and recently extinct).&lt;/synopsis&gt;
      &lt;access&gt;Every resource described by the Ethnologue data provider is a
      public Web page that may be accessed without restriction. Reuse of 
      material on the site is subject to the Terms of Use that are
      posted on the site.&lt;/access&gt;
   &lt;/olac-archive&gt;
&lt;/description&gt;
</eg></section>
    <section><heading>Requirements on static repositories</heading>
      <p>A static repository is an XML document that describes the resources made available by a particular institution or individual. It is a convenient way to create a data provider for a relatively small collection (say, up to a couple thousand records). Such a document may be created and maintained manually by means of an XML editor. Alternatively, it might be generated  periodically by a script that extracts information from an existing database. Typically a given institution or individual should publish the metadata for all its resources in a single static repository. An exception is appropriate when different scripts are used to generate repositories for distinct collections from different databases.</p>
      <p> The OAI specification for a static repository is given in <cit>OAI-SR</cit>. The schema for validating a static repository is found at:</p>
      <blockquote><p><url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/static-repository.xsd</url></p>
      </blockquote><p>In addition to being valid with respect to this schema, an OLAC static repository must also:</p>
      <ol><li><p>Include an <tt>&lt;oai-identifier&gt;</tt> description and an <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt> description in its <tt>&lt;Identify&gt;</tt> element.</p>
      </li><li><p>Contain the following element within its <tt>&lt;ListMetadataFormats&gt;</tt> element:</p>
      <eg>&lt;oai:metadataFormat&gt;
   &lt;oai:metadataPrefix&gt;olac&lt;/oai:metadataPrefix&gt;
   &lt;oai:schema&gt;http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.0/olac.xsd&lt;/oai:schema&gt;
   &lt;oai:metadataNamespace&gt;http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.0/&lt;/oai:metadataNamespace&gt;
&lt;/oai:metadataFormat&gt;</eg></li><li><p>Contain a <tt>&lt;ListRecords&gt;</tt> element that specifies an attribute and value of <tt>metadataPrefix="olac"</tt> and in which every embedded record has a metadata description that conforms to the OLAC metadata standard <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>.</p>
      </li></ol><p>A service for validating a repository for conformance to these requirements is found at:</p>
      <blockquote><p><url>http://www.language-archives.org/register/register.php4</url></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>An example of a complete OLAC static repository that conforms to these requirements is found at:</p>
      <blockquote><p><url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.0/static-repository.xml</url></p>
      </blockquote>
      <p>The OLAC Static Repository Gateway is found at:</p>
      <blockquote><p><url>http://www.language-archives.org/sr</url></p>
      </blockquote>
    </section> 
    
    <section> 
      <heading>Requirements on dynamic repositories</heading> 
      <p>A dynamic repository is harder to implement since it requires the implementation of a CGI interface for the complete OAI protocol for metadata harvesting <cit>OAI-PMH</cit>. This is necessary, however, when the collection is large and needs to implement flow control to keep protocol responses to a reasonable size. The OAI community considers half a megabyte to be a reasonable response size. If the <tt>ListRecords</tt> response for all records in a repository would substantially exceed that size, then it may be necessary to implement a dynamic repository with flow control.</p>
      <p>The implementation of a dynamic OLAC data provider  has all the features of a minimal repository implementation <cit>OAI-GRI</cit>, except that an OLAC data provider need not support the <tt>oai_dc</tt> metadata format. This is because the OLAC Aggregator <cit>OLACA</cit> provides that service for data providers that comply with this standard. In fact, unless the institution has reasons of its own to function independently as an OAI data provider, OLAC recommends that a dynamic repository not implement the <tt>oai_dc</tt> metadata format so that the translation of OLAC metadata to the  <tt>oai_dc</tt> format will be done consistently across the community.</p>
      <p>In addition to the requirements of a minimal repository implementation, a dynamic OLAC data provider must comply with the following additional requirements. </p>
      <ol><li><p>The <tt>Identify</tt> response must include an <tt>&lt;oai-identifier&gt;</tt> description and an <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt> description.</p>
      </li><li><p>The <tt>ListMetadataFormats</tt> response (when made with no additional parameters) must contain a specification for the <tt>olac</tt> metadata prefix that declares the schema and namespace for the version of OLAC metadata that is being used. For example,</p>
      <eg>&lt;oai:metadataFormat&gt;
   &lt;oai:metadataPrefix&gt;olac&lt;/oai:metadataPrefix&gt;
   &lt;oai:schema&gt;http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.0/olac.xsd&lt;/oai:schema&gt;
   &lt;oai:metadataNamespace&gt;http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.0/&lt;/oai:metadataNamespace&gt;
&lt;/oai:metadataFormat&gt;</eg></li><li><p>When the <tt>metadataPrefix</tt> argument to <tt>ListIdentifiers</tt> is specified as <tt>olac</tt>, the request must respond with at least one  record.</p>
      </li><li><p>When the <tt>metadataPrefix</tt> argument to <tt>GetRecord</tt> is specified as <tt>olac</tt>, the <tt>&lt;oai:metadata&gt;</tt> element of the response must either be empty (when  no OLAC metadata is available for the given identifier) or it must contain an <tt>&lt;olac:olac&gt;</tt> element that conforms to some  version of the XML schema for OLAC metadata <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>. That element must contain an <tt>xmlns</tt> attribute specifying the URI that identifies the namespace for the version of the OLAC metadata schema that is being used.</p>
      </li><li><p>When the <tt>metadataPrefix</tt> argument to <tt>ListRecords</tt> is specified as <tt>olac</tt>, every <tt>&lt;oai:metadata&gt;</tt> element in the response must contain an <tt>&lt;olac:olac&gt;</tt> element that conforms to some  version of the XML schema for OLAC metadata <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>. Each such element must contain an <tt>xmlns</tt> attribute specifying the URI that identifies the namespace for the version of the metadata schema that is being used.</p>
      </li></ol> 
       
    </section> 
     
     
     
  </body><todo><p>The strategy for forming repository identifiers with personal data repositories needs to be addressed.</p>
      </todo> 
  <references> 
    <ref abbrev="OAI-PMH">The Open Archives Initiative Protocol for Metadata Harvesting, Version 1.1 (2001-07-02).
	 <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/1.1/openarchivesprotocol.htm</url>&gt;</ref><ref abbrev="OAI-SR">Specification for an OAI Static Repository and an OAI Static Repository Gateway.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/guidelines-static-repository.htm</url>&gt;</ref>
    <ref abbrev="OAI-Ids">Specification and XML Schema for the OAI Identifier Format, Document Version 2002/06/21.
	 <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/guidelines-oai-identifier.htm</url>&gt;</ref>
    <ref abbrev="OAI-GRI">Guidelines for Repository Implementers, Document Version 2002/06/09.
	 <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/guidelines-repository.htm</url>&gt;</ref>
<ref abbrev="OLAC-Metadata">OLAC Metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url>&gt;</ref>
<ref abbrev="OLACA">OLAC Aggregator.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/cgi-bin/olaca.pl</url>&gt;</ref>
  </references>
</OLAC_doc>
