<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../OLAC_doc.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "../OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc>
   <header>
      <status code="adopted" type="standard"/>
      <!-- Promoted to Candidate on 2008-07-16 -->
      <!-- Promoted to Adopted on 2008-12-19 -->
      <title>OLAC Repositories</title>
      <baseName>repositories</baseName>
      <issued>20080728</issued>
       <previousIssued>20080531</previousIssued>
       <supersedes>20030917</supersedes>
      <abstract>
         <p>This document defines the standards OLAC archives must follow in implementing a metadata repository. </p>
      </abstract>
      <editors>Gary Simons, SIL International and Graduate Institute of Applied Linguistics
            (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>) <br/>Steven Bird, University of Melbourne and University of
         Pennsylvania (<url>mailto:sb@ldc.upenn.edu</url>) </editors>
      <copyright>2008 Gary Simons (SIL International and Graduate Institute of Applied Linguistics) and Steven Bird
         (University of Melbourne and University of Pennsylvania)</copyright>
      <changes>
         <p>This update to the standard describes the version 1.1 revision of the OLAC repository schemas. In
            addition to changing the version number from 1.0 to 1.1 throughout, the substantive changes are in the
               <xref>OLAC archive description</xref> and are as follows: the attribute for <tt>currentAsOf</tt> is
            added; the elements for <tt>&lt;curator&gt;</tt>, <tt>&lt;curatorTitle&gt;</tt>, and
               <tt>&lt;curatorEmail&gt;</tt> are replaced by a single, repeatable
               <tt>&lt;participant&gt;</tt> element; and an optional
               <tt>&lt;archivalSubmissionPolicy&gt;</tt> element is added. One of these changes manifests itself
            in a new requirement 2 in the requirements on both static and dynamic repositories, namely, that the person
            associated with the <tt>&lt;adminEmail&gt;</tt> must be identified in a
               <tt>&lt;participant&gt;</tt> element. Finally, the guidelines concerning relevance and 
            granularity have been revised to define the standard for
            granularity in terms of shared provenance. (This version
            also incorporates corrections that were made in response
            to feedback during the Candidate testing phase.)</p>
      </changes>
   </header>
   <body>
      <section>
         <heading>Introduction</heading>
         <p>This OLAC standard on metadata repositories is based on the Open Archives Initiative protocol for metadata
            harvesting <cit>OAI-PMH</cit>. This document assumes familiarity with the OAI protocol. A metadata
            repository may take the form of a dynamic repository that implements a CGI interface to query a live
            database in response to protocol requests, or it may take the form of a static repository that has no
            interface of its own but is serviced through a static repository gateway <cit>OAI-SR</cit>.</p>
         <p>An OLAC metadata repository (whether static or dynamic) must answer two special description elements as part
            of the response to the <tt>Identify</tt> request. It must:</p>
         <ul>
            <li>
               <p>Supply an <xref>OAI identifier description</xref>
               </p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Supply an <xref>OLAC archive description</xref>
               </p>
            </li>
         </ul>
         <p>These elements are described in the next two sections. The final sections of the document describe:</p>
         <ul>
            <li>
               <p>
                  <xref>Requirements on static repositories</xref>
               </p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>
                  <xref>Requirements on dynamic repositories</xref>
               </p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>
                  <xref>Guidelines concerning relevance and granularity</xref>
               </p>
            </li>
         </ul>

      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>OAI identifier description</heading>
         <p> The resource identifiers supplied by an OLAC metadata repository must comply with the OAI specification for
            the format of OAI identifiers as defined in <cit>OAI-Ids</cit>. The metadata repository must document its
            compliance with this format by including an <tt>&lt;oai-identifier&gt;</tt> element within a
               <tt>&lt;description&gt;</tt> container in the <tt>Identify</tt> response.</p>
         <p>The schema for validating an OAI identifier description is found at:</p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai-identifier.xsd</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>
         <p>The target namespace is: <tt>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai-identifier</tt></p>
         <p>The schema specifies fixed values of <i>oai</i> for the <tt>scheme</tt> element and <i>:</i> (colon) for the
               <tt>delimiter</tt> element. In addition to being valid with respect to the schema, OLAC places these
            further requirements on the content of the OAI identifier description:</p>
         <ul>
            <li>
               <p>The <tt>repositoryIdentifier</tt> must be unique among all registered OLAC archives.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>The <tt>repositoryIdentifier</tt> must be based on a registered domain name, typically of the
                  sponsoring institution. A single institution may use subdomain names to distinguish metadata
                  repositories that are internally distinct. A host institution may also use subdomain names to create
                  identifiers for personal repositories.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>The <tt>sampleIdentifier</tt> must be of an existing item in the repository, and not a hypothetical
                  item.</p>
            </li>
         </ul>
         <p>For example,</p>
         <eg>&lt;description&gt;
   &lt;oai-identifier
         xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai-identifier"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai-identifier
             http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai-identifier.xsd"&gt;
      &lt;scheme&gt;oai&lt;/scheme&gt;
      &lt;repositoryIdentifier&gt;ethnologue.com&lt;/repositoryIdentifier&gt;
      &lt;delimiter&gt;:&lt;/delimiter&gt;
      &lt;sampleIdentifier&gt;oai:ethnologue.com:aaa&lt;/sampleIdentifier&gt;
   &lt;/oai-identifier&gt;
&lt;/description&gt;
</eg>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>OLAC archive description</heading>
         <p>The basic <tt>Identify</tt> request supplies minimal information about an archive, namely, its name, base
            URL, and administrator email. An OLAC metadata repository must augment the <tt>Identify</tt> response by
            including an <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt> element within a <tt>&lt;description&gt;</tt>
            container. This element gives additional information that makes it possible for an OLAC service provider to
            supply its users with a basic description of a participating archive. </p>
         <p>The schema for validating an OLAC archive description is found at:</p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/olac-archive.xsd</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>
         <p>The target namespace is: <tt>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/olac-archive</tt></p>
         <p>The <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt> element has two obligatory attributes, <tt>type</tt> and
               <tt>currentAsOf</tt>. The <tt>type</tt> attribute must have one of two values:</p>
         <ul>
            <li>
               <p><tt>type="institutional"</tt> indicates that the repository is operated by an institution that is
                  committed to maintaining it in the future, even after the individuals currently associated with it are
                  no longer involved.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p><tt>type="personal"</tt> indicates that the repository is being operated by an individual (or a group
                  of individuals) without the commitment of an institution for maintenance far into the future. </p>
            </li>
         </ul>
         <p>The <tt>currentAsOf</tt> attribute records the date on which this <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt>
            description was last updated or, if no changes needed to be made, the date on which it was verified as
            holding current information. The attribute is obligatory and takes a date in the W3C date format
            <cit>W3CDTF</cit> which is a ten character string in the following format: <tt>YYYY-MM-DD</tt> (e.g.,
            2008-04-19). </p>
         <p>These are the elements that occur within an OLAC archive description, listed in the order in which they must
            appear:</p>
         <dl>
            <dt>archiveURL</dt>
            <dd>
               <p><i>Optional.</i> The home page of the archive on the Web. It may be omitted only if the archive does not
                  have a web page. This is the home page for human visitors, not the base URL for harvesting.</p>
            </dd>

            <dt>participant</dt>
            <dd>
               <p><i>Obligatory and repeatable.</i> Use an instance of this element for each of the persons who plays a
                  significant role with respect to the repository. This must include the system administrator whose
                  email address is given in the <tt>&lt;oai:adminEmail&gt;</tt> element of the <tt>Identify</tt>
                  response. It should also include the curator of the archive, and may include any others who play some
                  role. Identifying a participant in the archive description has two functions: it provides contact
                  information for the OLAC community and it creates a subscription to the automatically generated report
                  on usage and quality metrics for the archive that is emailed quarterly. Thus anyone at the institution
                  who wishes to receive this report should be listed as a participant. </p>
               <dl style="table">
                  <dt>name</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The name of the person who is associated in some way with the repository. Use the normal name
                        form (i.e., uninverted).</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>role</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The job title of the participant, or a label for the role the person plays with respect to the
                        repository.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>email</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The email address for the participant.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </dd>
             <dt>institution</dt>
             <dd>
                 <p><i>Obligatory.</i> The name of the sponsoring institution (for an institutional archive) or the
                     institution of affiliation (for a personal archive). If the curator of a personal archive has no
                     affiliation, then a value of <i>Unaffiliated</i> should be given.</p>
             </dd>
             <dt>institutionURL</dt>
             <dd>
                 <p><i>Optional.</i> A URL for the home page of the institution.</p>
             </dd>
            <dt>shortLocation</dt>
            <dd>
               <p><i>Obligatory.</i> A brief statement (not to exceed 50 characters) of the location of the institution
                  or the person providing the metadata following the format "City, Country". Multiple locations may be
                  connected with "and". This information is shown in the location column of the table of participating
                  archives at <url>http://www.language-archives.org/archives.php</url>.</p>
            </dd>
            <dt>location</dt>
            <dd>
               <p><i>Optional.</i> A single paragraph (of arbitrary length) describing where an archive that houses a
                  collection of physical holdings is located (for instance, include building name, room number, street
                  address). Other information relevant to visiting the collection, such as opening hours or restrictions
                  on access, may also be described. If the archive is purely an on-line repository, do not use this
                  element.</p>
            </dd>
            <dt>synopsis</dt>
            <dd>
               <p><i>Obligatory.</i> A single paragraph (of arbitrary length) summarizing the purpose, scope, coverage,
                  and so on of the archive.</p>
            </dd>
            <dt>access</dt>
            <dd>
               <p><i>Obligatory.</i> A single paragraph (of arbitrary length) summarizing terms of access to the
                  materials described in the metadata repository. The statement can describe restrictions on access,
                  licensing requirements, costs, and so on. Individual metadata records should use the Rights element to
                  document such things for particular archive holdings. The purpose of <tt>&lt;access&gt;</tt>
                  is to broadly characterize the entire archive.</p>
            </dd>
            <dt>archivalSubmissionPolicy</dt>
            <dd>
               <p><i>Optional.</i> A single paragraph (of arbitrary length) describing the institution's policy toward
                  accepting archival submissions. The presence of this element indicates that the repository is an
                  archive that accepts submissions of materials for long-term preservation. The element content should
                  describe the collection policy of the archive (e.g., what kinds of materials are accepted from whom
                  under what terms) so that a person looking for a place to archive a set of language resources may
                  determine whether it would be appropriate to contact the curator about making a submission. A
                  repository that does not accept materials for long-term preservation must not use this element. All
                  institutions that provide an archival submission policy are listed with their policy statement in a
                  page aimed at assisting those looking for a place to archive language resources:
                     <url>http://www.language-archives.org/submission-policies.php</url>.</p>
            </dd>
         </dl>
         <p>For example,</p>
          <eg>&lt;description&gt;
   &lt;olac-archive type="institutional" currentAsOf="2008-04-19"
         xmlns="http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/olac-archive"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/olac-archive
         http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/olac-archive.xsd"&gt;
      &lt;archiveURL&gt;http://www.ethnologue.com/bibliography.asp&lt;/archiveURL&gt;
      &lt;participant name="Vurnell Cobbey" title="Archives director (acting)"
         email="archive_dallas@sil.org"/&gt;
      &lt;participant name="Joan Spanne" title="Database administrator"
         email="joan_spanne@sil.org"/&gt;
      &lt;institution&gt;SIL International&lt;/institution&gt;
      &lt;institutionURL&gt;http://www.sil.org&lt;/institutionURL&gt;
      &lt;shortLocation&gt;Dallas, USA&lt;/shortLocation&gt;
      &lt;location&gt;7500 W. Camp Wisdom Rd., Dallas, TX 75236, U.S.A.&lt;/location&gt;
      &lt;synopsis&gt;The SIL International Language and Culture Archives holds 
         works authored or edited by members of SIL International or produced by
         a publishing unit of SIL. It houses over 13,000 books, journal articles, book
         chapters, dissertations, and other academic papers about languages and 
         cultures. It also has about 8,000 items written in the languages studied, 
         such as literacy primers, books on basic education topics (health, math, 
         social studies), story books, and translated works. The vast majority of 
         works are published. The materials date from 1935 to the present.
      &lt;/synopsis&gt;
      &lt;access&gt;Links are given to publications that are directly accessible 
         via the Internet. Recent SIL publications may be purchased from the 
         International Academic Bookstore (Academic_Books AT sil.org), either 
         in paper or in electronic form. Out-of-print SIL publications may be
         obtained by special order. All materials may be viewed by visiting the 
         Archives by appointment during normal business hours.
      &lt;/access&gt;
      &lt;archivalSubmissionPolicy&gt;The SIL International Language and 
         Culture Archives accepts submissions from active and retired SIL staff 
         in the areas of language and culture documentation and description, 
         and language-based development. Under some circumstances, the 
         Archives will also accept materials from former staff and persons 
         more casually associated with SIL language work, if such materials 
         relate to research done with the assistance of SIL or its staff, and there
         is not a more appropriate institution able to accept and curate the 
         materials long-term. Please address any questions to the Archives 
         by sending email to archive_dallas AT sil.org.
      &lt;archivalSubmissionPolicy&gt;
   &lt;/olac-archive&gt;
&lt;/description&gt;</eg>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>Requirements on static repositories</heading>
         <p>A static repository is an XML document that describes the resources made available by a particular
            institution or individual. It is a convenient way to create a metadata repository for a relatively small
            collection (say, up to a couple thousand records). Such a document may be created and maintained manually by
            means of an XML editor. Alternatively, it might be generated periodically by a script that extracts
            information from an existing database. </p>
         <p> The OAI specification for a static repository is given in <cit>OAI-SR</cit>. The schema for validating a
            static repository is found at:</p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/static-repository.xsd</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>
         <p>In addition to being valid with respect to this schema, an OLAC static repository must also:</p>
         <ol>
            <li>
               <p>Include an <tt>&lt;oai-identifier&gt;</tt> description and an
                  <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt> description in its <tt>&lt;Identify&gt;</tt>
               element.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Include a <tt>&lt;participant&gt;</tt> element within the
                  <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt> description with an email address that exactly matches the
                     <tt>&lt;adminEmail&gt;</tt> within the <tt>&lt;Identify&gt;</tt> element.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Contain the following element within its <tt>&lt;ListMetadataFormats&gt;</tt> element:</p>
               <eg>&lt;oai:metadataFormat&gt;
   &lt;oai:metadataPrefix&gt;olac&lt;/oai:metadataPrefix&gt;
   &lt;oai:schema&gt;http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/olac.xsd&lt;/oai:schema&gt;
   &lt;oai:metadataNamespace&gt;http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/&lt;/oai:metadataNamespace&gt;
&lt;/oai:metadataFormat&gt;</eg>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Contain a <tt>&lt;ListRecords&gt;</tt> element that specifies an attribute and value of
                     <tt>metadataPrefix="olac"</tt> that contains at least one record, and in which every embedded
                  record has a metadata description that conforms to the OLAC metadata standard
                  <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>.</p>
            </li>
         </ol>
         <p>A service for validating a repository for conformance to these requirements is found at:</p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.language-archives.org/register/register.php4</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>
         <p>An example of a complete OLAC static repository that conforms to these requirements is found at:</p>
         <blockquote>
            <p>
               <url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/static-repository.xml</url>
            </p>
         </blockquote>

      </section>

      <section>
         <heading>Requirements on dynamic repositories</heading>
         <p>A dynamic repository is harder to implement since it requires the implementation of a CGI interface for the
            complete OAI protocol for metadata harvesting <cit>OAI-PMH</cit>. This is necessary, however, when the
            collection is large and needs to implement flow control to keep protocol responses to a reasonable size. The
            OAI community considers half a megabyte to be a reasonable response size. If the <tt>ListRecords</tt>
            response for all records in a repository would substantially exceed that size, then it may be necessary to
            implement a dynamic repository with flow control.</p>
         <p>The implementation of a dynamic OLAC metadata repository has all the features of a minimal OAI repository
            implementation (as defined in <cit>OAI-GRI</cit>), except that a dynamic OLAC repository need not support
            the <tt>oai_dc</tt> metadata format. This is because the OLAC Aggregator <cit>OLACA</cit> provides that
            service for repositories that comply with this standard; see <cit>OLAC-Display</cit> for the specification
            of the <tt>olac</tt> to <tt>oai_dc</tt> crosswalk that is implemented by the Aggregator. In fact, unless the
            institution has reasons of its own to function independently as an OAI data provider, OLAC recommends that a
            dynamic repository not implement the <tt>oai_dc</tt> metadata format so that the translation of OLAC
            metadata to the <tt>oai_dc</tt> format will be done consistently across the community.</p>
         <p>In addition to the requirements of a minimal OAI repository implementation, a dynamic OLAC metadata
            repository must comply with the following additional requirements. </p>
         <ol>
            <li>
               <p>The <tt>Identify</tt> response must include an <tt>&lt;oai-identifier&gt;</tt> description and
                  an <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt> description.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Include a <tt>&lt;participant&gt;</tt> element within the
                  <tt>&lt;olac-archive&gt;</tt> description with an email address that exactly matches the
                     <tt>&lt;adminEmail&gt;</tt> within the <tt>Identify</tt> response.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>The <tt>ListMetadataFormats</tt> response (when made with no additional parameters) must contain a
                  specification for the <tt>olac</tt> metadata prefix that declares the schema and namespace for the
                  version of OLAC metadata that is being used. For example,</p>
               <eg>&lt;oai:metadataFormat&gt;
   &lt;oai:metadataPrefix&gt;olac&lt;/oai:metadataPrefix&gt;
   &lt;oai:schema&gt;http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/olac.xsd&lt;/oai:schema&gt;
   &lt;oai:metadataNamespace&gt;http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/1.1/&lt;/oai:metadataNamespace&gt;
&lt;/oai:metadataFormat&gt;</eg>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>When the <tt>metadataPrefix</tt> argument to <tt>ListIdentifiers</tt> is specified as <tt>olac</tt>,
                  the request must respond with at least one record.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>When the <tt>metadataPrefix</tt> argument to <tt>GetRecord</tt> is specified as <tt>olac</tt>, the
                     <tt>&lt;oai:metadata&gt;</tt> element of the response must either be empty (when no OLAC
                  metadata is available for the given identifier) or it must contain an
                  <tt>&lt;olac:olac&gt;</tt> element that conforms to some version of the XML schema for OLAC
                  metadata <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>. That element must contain an <tt>xmlns</tt> attribute specifying
                  the URI that identifies the namespace for the version of the OLAC metadata schema that is being
               used.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>When the <tt>metadataPrefix</tt> argument to <tt>ListRecords</tt> is specified as <tt>olac</tt>, every
                     <tt>&lt;oai:metadata&gt;</tt> element in the response must contain an
                     <tt>&lt;olac:olac&gt;</tt> element that conforms to some version of the XML schema for OLAC
                  metadata <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>. Each such element must contain an <tt>xmlns</tt> attribute
                  specifying the URI that identifies the namespace for the version of the metadata schema that is being
                  used.</p>
            </li>
         </ol>

      </section>
        <section>
            <heading>Guidelines concerning relevance and granularity</heading>
            <p>When a request is made to register a metadata
                repository with OLAC, it is first tested for
                conformance to the requirements listed in the sections
                above. When these are met, the registration request is
                reviewed by the OLAC Council (see
                <cit>OLAC-Process</cit>) before final acceptance. The
                role of the Council in the registration process is to
                ensure that all registered archives meet the following
                guidelines concerning relevance and granularity.</p>
            <p>Regarding relevance, in order to be eligible for
                registration as an OLAC archive:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>The metadata repository must catalog language
                        resources.</p>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>Regarding the granularity of repositories, a repository
                is meant to catalog all the holdings of an archive,
                rather than having separate repositories for each of
                the collections within an archive. Thus,</p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>A given institution or individual should
                        typically publish the metadata for all its
                        resources in a single repository. </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>An exception is appropriate when distinct
                        collections are managed in separate databases
                        and because of this require distinct software
                        for implementing separate repositories.</p>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>Regarding the granularity of the records in a
                repository, the basic guideline is this:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>A metadata repository should treat resources
                        with a single provenance as constituting a single
                        unit with respect to OLAC metadata and should,
                        therefore, describe them within a single
                        record.</p>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>For published resources, the publication unit typically
                constitutes the appropriate unit for the OLAC metadata
                record. For
                unpublished papers presenting findings of research,
                these closely parallel typical published works, and
                can be treated at a comparable level in an OLAC
                metadata record. For primary
                source materials (<i>e.g.,</i> recordings,
                transcriptions, annotations, notes, data sets), the
                typical practice of archivists is to gather such
                materials into collections based on shared
                provenance&#x2014;this is, based on having a common origin and
                history. These collections are then the
                primary units for description  in  OLAC
                metadata records.</p>
            <p>See Section 5 of the OLAC Metadata Usage Guidelines
                    <cit>OLAC-Usage</cit>, for a more in-depth
                discussion of the principle of provenance as applied
                to collections and metadata within the OLAC
            context.</p>
        </section>



   </body>
   <references>
      <ref abbrev="OAI-PMH">The Open Archives Initiative Protocol for Metadata Harvesting, Version 2.0 (2002-06-14).
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/openarchivesprotocol.htm</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OAI-SR">Specification for an OAI Static Repository and an OAI Static Repository
            Gateway.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/guidelines-static-repository.htm</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OAI-Ids">Specification and XML Schema for the OAI Identifier Format, Document Version 2002/06/21.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/guidelines-oai-identifier.htm</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OAI-GRI">Guidelines for Repository Implementers, Document Version 2002/06/09.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/guidelines-repository.htm</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Metadata">OLAC
         Metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Process">OLAC
         Process.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/process.html</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Usage">OLAC
         Metadata Usage Guidelines.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/NOTE/usage.html</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OLACA">OLAC
         Aggregator.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/cgi-bin/olaca.pl</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Display">Specifications for an OLAC metadata display format and an OLAC-to-OAI_DC
            crosswalk.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/NOTE/olac_display.html</url>&gt;</ref>
      <ref abbrev="W3CDTF">Date and Time Formats, W3C
         Note.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-datetime</url>&gt;</ref>
   </references>
</OLAC_doc>
